<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_q4v_5hp_mfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The In’s and the Out’s</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-10-17</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The In’s and the Out’s. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 446, 30. Mai 1846. S. 5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The In’s and the Out’s.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1846-05-30</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’
                            Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X [IX?]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">446</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">4</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-05-01" notAfter="1846-05-29">Mai 1846</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">For the following remarks we are indebted to a correspondent: —</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The In’s and the Out’s.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>The daily papers of Paris have been recently engaged in a squabble about the old
                    adage of M. Thiers: “The King <hi rendition="#i">reigns</hi>, but does not
                        <hi rendition="#i">govern</hi>.” This commenced in the ministerial <hi rendition="#i">Journal des Debats</hi> with a furious attack upon Thiers,
                    who, of course, failed not to reply. It is a mere electioneering speculation for
                    the purpose of securing majorities in the next general election, the chambers
                    being about to be dissolved as soon as the budget is voted. The ministerial
                    papers, the parties <hi rendition="#i">in</hi> office, pronounce their approval
                    of the interference of the king in government affairs; the party out of office,
                    M. Thiers and his paper, the <hi rendition="#i">Constitutionnel</hi>, proclaims
                    such interference to be most dangerous and intolerable in a country like France.
                    The most interesting points in the whole discussion are the disclosures made of
                    the way in which Louis Philippe interferes in the business of the country. M.
                    Thiers relates in the plainest possible manner, that the King strives always to
                    get his private creatures into office, that he has a candidate for the command
                    of every man-of-war (thus competing with the creatures of the ministers), that
                    if his will be not acceded to by ministers, he plots secretly against them, that
                    if his private wishes, as to foreign affairs do not prevail in the council, he
                    sends secret orders to the Ambassadors at foreign courts, that he carries on
                    secret correspondence with all influential employe’s. It is the more
                    ridiculous to complain at this very moment about personal interference on the
                    part of the King, when every paper gives daily proofs of the absolute control
                    over all affairs of government which is exercised by the “haute
                    bourgeois” the large capitalists. But M. Thiers and his complaints
                    represent the “petite <choice>
                        <sic>bourgeoisi”,</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">bourgeoisie”,</corr>
                    </choice> the inferior ranks of the middle classes, who being oppressed by the
                    enormous weight of the “gros-bourgeois” commence to pronounce louder
                    and louder their dissatisfaction with the present state of things. How
                    all-powerful the large capitalists are in France, how well they know how to
                    concentrate the political leadership in their own hands, is shown by the new
                    “loi de patente” which passed some time ago (I believe last year)
                    and by which the number of voters in all France was reduced from 200.000 to
                    150.000. Both the ministerial papers and M. Thiers’s paper reproach each
                    other, that their respective policy would lead to a revolution and the
                    establishment of a republic. The <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> who, of
                    course, enjoys this quarrel very much takes these two confessions down and says, “If these two great heroes, M. Guizot and M. Thiers, both insist that their policy is counter-revolutionary, we have only to bow and to retire with a ‘Thank you, gentlemen’!”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>