<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Violation of the Prussian Constitution</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-04</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] Violation of the Prussian Constitution. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 446, 30. Mai 1846. S. 5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Violation of the Prussian Constitution.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1846-05-30"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X [IX?]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">446</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">4</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-05-01" notAfter="1846-05-29">Mai 1846</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">Last, not least, financial difficulties add to the embarrassments of the
                    Government, and have given rise to a measure involving a further departure from
                    the solemn pledges given by the Crown to the people. On this subject we have
                    been favoured with the following communication from our German Correspondent:
                    —</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Violation of the Prussian Constitution.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>There exists a law in Prussia dated 22nd of June, 1820, forbidding the King to
                    contract any State Debts without the sanction of the States General, an assembly
                    which it is very well known, does not yet exist in Prussia. This law is the only
                    guarantee the Prussians have for ever getting the constitution which, since
                    1815, has been promised to them. The fact of the existence of such a law not
                    being generally known out of Prussia, the government succeeded in 1823 in
                    borrowing <hi rendition="#i">three millions of pounds</hi> in England —
                    first violation. After the French revolution of 1830, the Prussian government
                    being obliged to make extensive preparations for a war which was then likely to
                    break out, they not having any money, made the “interests for transatlantic
                    trade”, a government concern, borrow twelve millions of dollars (£ 1.700.000),
                    which, of course, were under the guarantee of the government, and spent by the
                    government — second violation. Not to speak of the small violations, such
                    as loans of a few hundred thousands of pounds by the same concern, the King of
                    Prussia has, at this moment, committed a third great violation. The credit of
                    this concern being as it seems exhausted, the Bank of Prussia, being just in the
                    same way, exclusively, a government concern, has been empowered by the King to
                    issue bank notes to the amount of ten millions of dollars (£ 1.350.000). This
                    deducting 3⅓ millions as deposit and ⅔ millions for the increased expences of
                    the establishment, amounts in reality to an “indirect loan” of six millions of
                    dollares or nearly one million of pounds, which the government will be
                    responsible for, as up to this time no private capitalists are partners to the
                    Bank of Prussia. It is to be hoped that the Prussians, particularly the middle
                    classes, who are most interested in the constitution, will not let this pass
                    without an energetic protest.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>