<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_ihn_dv2_nfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Belgium</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-10-19</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich, George Julian Harney:] Belgium. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 451,
                    4. Juli 1846. S. 5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Belgium</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1846-07-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’
                            Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X [IX?]</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">451</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-06-21" notAfter="1846-06-30">Ende Juni 1846</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">There has been lately holden in</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Belgium,</hi></hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">in the Town Hall of Brussels, a “Liberal Congress”, consisting of
                    three hundred and sixty deputies, under the presidency of M. Defacqz, a
                    councillor of the Court of Cassation, one of the Chiefs of the Liberal party.
                    The object of this movement, according to the programme of the Congress is
                    “to obtain electoral reform by the adjunction of the Jury lists, and by a
                    certain reduction of the present assessment of the towns; to establish the real
                    independence of the civil power; to organise by authority a system of public
                    instruction for every class under the exclusive direction of the civil power,
                    and rejecting the intervention of the clergy; to increase the number of Deputies
                    and Senators, in the proportion of one Deputy to 40.000 souls, and one Senator
                    to 80.000 souls; to abrogate certain laws; and to ameliorate the condition of
                    the poorer classes”. A central committee will direct the efforts of the
                    local societies to influence public opinion and the elections. From a friend at
                    Brussels we have been put in possession of the following communication
                    explaining the distinction and differences between the “Liberal” and
                    the “Catholic” party: —</hi></p>
                <p>The resolutions of the <hi rendition="#i">Congrés Libérals</hi> are on the whole
                    a victory of what is called here the <hi rendition="#i">young</hi> liberals over
                    the <hi rendition="#i">old</hi> ones; but rather a slight victory. The proposed
                    extension of the suffrage, if carried out even to the utmost limits allowed
                    (reducing the qualification of voters to 20 guilders or 33s. paid annually in
                    taxes) would give the right of voting to the <hi rendition="#i">petite <choice>
                            <sic>bourgeoise</sic>
                            <corr cert="high">bourgeoisie</corr>
                        </choice></hi>, or shopkeeping class, and to some smaller landed
                    proprietors. The mass of the people would remain entirely excluded from
                    representation. The admittance of the <hi rendition="#i">capacities</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.</hi> lawyers, physicians, schoolmasters, and others who
                    have to undergo public examinations and attend the universities, at the above
                    qualification a measure, which the Congress asked for as an immediate necessity,
                    would introduce into the Parliament not supporters of popular measures but
                    advocates of the shopkeeping interests. As to the demanded “real
                    independence of the civil power
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20181022T120851+0200" comment="Fehlt in 1. Ausgabe, korrigiert in 2. Ausgabe."?>of<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    the clergy”, this is futile as long as the other <choice>
                        <sic>measures,</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">measures</corr>
                    </choice> are not carried, and then it will follow as a matter of course. The
                    clergy are the chief advocates of the landed interest, the nobility in
                    particular; the liberals consist of the trading capitalists in the towns. The
                    struggle between Catholics and Liberals is the same as in England, between
                    landlords and money-lords, Protectionists and Freetraders, it is the struggle of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">town</hi> against the <hi rendition="#i">country</hi>. If
                    the <hi rendition="#i">towns</hi>, that is the liberals, pass their measures,
                    which, however, they are yet far from, the civil power <hi rendition="#i">will</hi> naturally be independent of the clergy, because the clergy are
                    merely the interested advocates of the landlords, and their power will be broke
                    as soon as that of the landlords is overturned. The <hi rendition="#i">people</hi> have taken very little interest in the whole Congress
                    affair.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>