<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Prussian Bank Question</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
                </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-04</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The Prussian Bank Question. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 451, 4. Juli 1846. S. 5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Prussian Bank Question.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1846-07-04"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">451</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-06-21" notAfter="1846-06-30"/>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">Again, rumours are rife in</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Germany,</hi></hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">that the long projected Prussian Constitution is at last framed, and will be
                    immediately published. For ourselves, we will believe when we see. The King of
                    Prussia is such a liar that none but asses would repose faith in his most solemn
                    promises. One thing is certain that, if a Constitution is granted, it will be so
                    worthless as to be utterly inadequate to satisfy the popular demands. From our
                    “German correspondent” we have received the following brief but interesting
                    communication which exhibits his Prussian kingship in a new but not very
                    respectable character. He is about to turn swindler on a large scale. He will
                    borrow, and then “repudiate”. We believe a favourite song of his is: —</hi></p>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">Yankee Doodle borrows cash,</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">Yankee Doodle spends it,</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">And then he snaps his fingers at</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">The jolly flat who lends it.</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                </lg>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">Much, however, might be said for the Yankees which will not apply to the Royal
                    Pietist of Prussia. Perhaps he will quiet his conscience with the moral
                    reflection: —</hi></p>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">If humbgg’d thus the jobbers choose to be,</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">Why let them, since it brings the chink to me,</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                    <l><hi rendition="#smaller">There’s non so blind as those who will not see.</hi></l>
                    <lb/>
                </lg>
                <lb/>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">Here follows the letter from our correspondent: —</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Prussian Bank
                    Question.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>You will probably have already heard that the King of Prussia’s plan of making
                    money out of paper has been found impracticable. Two of the administrators of
                    the State Debts refused to sign the new bank notes, as they considered them to
                    be a new public debt, therefore subject to the guarantee of the States-General.
                    Frederick William IV., to show that he can make as much money as he likes,
                    has now hit upon a far better plan. <choice>
                        <sic>In stead</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">Instead</corr>
                    </choice> of making ten millions, he makes thirty — twenty millions of
                    paper-money and ten of good, solid gold and silver coin. He proposes that ten
                    millions of capital be raised by shares, “which shares it appears shall bring no
                    dividends but merely 3½ per cent. interest and which shall not be transferable
                    unless at the owner’s death, in order to keep them out of the reach of
                    speculation”!!! Now would you call such things <hi rendition="#i">shares</hi>?
                    Why not? His Majesty of Prussia decrees that they <hi rendition="#i">are</hi>
                    shares, and fosters the fond hope that he will find a lot of capitalists stupid
                    enough to invest ten millions of dollars in such not transferable, leaden,
                    three-and-a-half Bank Stock! And that at a time, too, when by speculating in
                    railway shares they can make quite another per centage. When the King will have
                    found the parcel of fools he is in want of, and thus borrowed ten millions in
                        <hi rendition="#i">coin</hi>, he will issue <hi rendition="#i">twenty</hi>
                    millions in banknotes, making “a sum total of thirty <choice>
                        <sic>millions</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">millions”</corr>
                    </choice>, increasing the national liabilities. Really this is raising the wind
                    with a vengeance. Raising thirty millions, because one can’t get ten, the King
                    of Prussia bids fair to turn a Yankee Swindler. We cannot but heartily applaud
                    such honest intentions in high quarters.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>