<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Address of the German Democratic Communists of Brussels to Mr. Feargus O’Connor</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                    <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                    <persName>Philippe Gigot</persName>
                </author>
                </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-04</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich, Karl Marx, Philippe Gigot:] Address of the German Democratic
                    Communists of Brussels to Mr. Feargus O’Connor. In: Northern Star. Vol. X.
                    Nr. 454, 25. Juli 1846. S. 1.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Address of the German Democratic Communists of
                            Brussels to Mr. Feargus O’Connor.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1846-07-25"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’
                            Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">454</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">1-2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                <persName>Philippe Gigot</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date when="1846-07-17"/>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Address of the German Democratic Communists of Brussels to Mr. Feargus O’Connor.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Sir.</hi> — We embrace the occasion of your splendid success at the Nottingham
                    election to congratulate you, and through you the English Chartists, on this
                    signal victory. We consider the defeat of a Free-Trade minister at the show of
                    hands by an enormous Chartist majority, and at the very time, too, when
                    Free-Trade principles are triumphant in the Legislature, we consider this, Sir,
                    as a sign that the working classes of England are very well aware of the
                    position they have to take after the triumph of Free-Trade. We conclude from
                    this fact that they know very well that now, when the middle classes have
                    carried their chief measure, when they have only to replace the present weak
                    go-between cabinet by an energetical, really middle-class ministry, in order to
                    be the acknowledged ruling class of your country, that now the great struggle of
                    capital and labour, of <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">proletarian</hi>, must come to a decision. The ground is now cleared by the
                    retreat of the landed aristocracy from the contest; middle class and working
                    class are the only classes betwixt whom there can be a possible struggle. The
                    contending parties have their respective battle cries forced upon them by their
                    interests and mutual position: — the middle class — “extension of
                    commerce by any means whatsoever, and a ministry of Lancashire cotton-lords to
                    carry this <choice>
                        <sic>out”; the</sic>
                        <corr cert="low">out”; — the</corr>
                    </choice> working class — “a democratic reconstruction of the Constitution
                    upon the basis of the People’s Charter”, by which the working class will become
                    the ruling class of England. We rejoice to see the English working men fully
                    aware of this altered state of parties; of the new period Chartist agitation has
                    entered into; with the final defeat of the third party, the aristocracy; of the
                    prominent position which Chartism henceforth will and must occupy, in spite of
                    the “conspiracy of silence” of the middle class press; and finally, of the new
                    task, which by these new circumstances has devolved upon them. That they are
                    quite aware of this task is proved by their intention <hi rendition="#i">to go
                        to the poll</hi> at the next general election.</p>
                <p>We have to congratulate you, Sir, in particular, upon your brilliant speech at
                    the Nottingham election, and the striking delineation given in it of the
                    contrast between working class democracy and middle class liberalism.</p>
                <p>We congratulate you besides on the unanimous vote of confidence in you,
                    spontaneaously passed by the whole Chartist body on the occasion of Thomas
                    Cooper, the would-be <hi rendition="#i">respectable’s</hi> calumnies. The
                    Chartist party cannot but profit by the exclusion of such disguised bourgeois,
                    who, while they show off with the name of Chartist for popularity’s sake, strive
                    to insinuate themselves into the favour of the middle classes by personal
                    flattery of their literary representatives (such as the Countess of Blessington,
                    Charles Dickens, D. Jerrold, and other “friends” of Cooper’s), and by
                    propounding such base and infamous old women’s doctrines as that of
                    “non-resistance”.</p>
                <p>Lastly, Sir, we have to thank you and your coadjutors for the noble and
                    enlightened manner in which the <hi rendition="#i">Northern Star</hi> is
                    conducted. We hesitate not a moment in declaring that the <hi rendition="#i">Star</hi> is the only English newspaper (save, perhaps, the <hi rendition="#i">People’s Journal</hi>, which we know from the <hi rendition="#i">Star</hi> only), which knows the real state of parties in
                    England; which is really and essentially democratic; which is free from national
                    and religious prejudice; which sympathises with the deomocrats and working men
                    (now-a-days the two are almost the same), all over the world; which in all these
                    points speaks the mind of the English working class, and therefore is the only
                    English paper really worth reading for the continental democrats. We hereby
                    declare that we shall do everything in our power to extend the circulation of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Northern Star</hi> on the continent, and to have extracts
                    from it translated in as many continental papers as possible.</p>
                <p>We beg to express these sentiments, Sir, as the acknowledged representatives of
                    many of the German communists in Germany, for all their relations with foreign
                    democrats.</p>
                <p>For the German Democratic Communists of Brussels.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#et2">The Committee,</hi><lb/><hi rendition="#et3">Engels,<lb/>Ph. Gigot,<lb/>Marx.</hi></p>
                <p>Brussels. July 17th, 1846.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>