<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Government and Opposition in France [MEGA1]</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-04</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich, George Julian Harney:] France. In: Northern Star. Vol. IX. Nr. 460, 5. September 1846. S. 1.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">France</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1846-09-05</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">IX</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">460</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">5-6</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-08-21" notAfter="1846-09-02"/>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">From</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">France</hi></hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">the general intelligence of the week is meagre and of
                        little interest. In our seventh page will be found an account of the
                        conviction and sentence of <hi rendition="#k">Joseph Henry</hi>, who has
                        been condemned to perpetual hard labour at the Bagne. The sentence has
                        excited considerable astonishment in Paris, where the opinion prevails that
                            <hi rendition="#k">Henry</hi> is a mere maniac. It is only fair to state
                        that there is another opinion entertained by some, that the whole affair was
                        a hoax got up by the police to serve ministerial ends in the recent
                        elections, and that the sentence just passed is all a <hi rendition="#i">sham</hi>, which will never be put into actual operation. Indeed, some
                        days ago we heard a rumour that <hi rendition="#k">Henry</hi> had been sent
                        over to England, and was at that time at Dover. We must say that we do not
                        credit this report, although there can be no doubt that Guizot and Co. are
                        quite capable of such a piece of villainous humbug. In the Chamber of
                        Deputies, on Saturday, M. Sauzet (Ministerialist) was elected President. M.
                        Sauzet had 223 votes, and his principal opponent, Odillon Barrot, 98. One of
                        the deputies, M. Dessaigne (Ministerialist), has commenced an action at law
                        for defamation against certain electors who issued a protest against his
                        return. The deputy for Poitiers, M. Drault has been deprived of his seat,
                        because he had given a pledge to his constituents to support electoral
                        reform, founded on the formal recognition of the principle that taxes ought
                        to be voted by all these who pay them; 2. Parliamentary reform, which shall
                        exclude public functionaries from the Chamber; 3. Liberty of education,
                        without any preventative measure; 4. The suppression of all sinecures and
                        useless expenses; 5. The refusal of all dotation; 6. The re-establishment of
                        the honour and dignity of <choice>
                            <sic>France.”</sic>
                            <corr cert="high">France.</corr>
                        </choice> In the course of the discussion, M. Guizot vehemently supported
                        the expulsion of the deputy, and in a long harangue gave expression to some
                        most bare-faced hypocritical sophisms, such as: — “The merit, the wisdom,
                        and the beauty of the government was, that nowhere was absolute power to be
                        found in it.” “Among them every where free examination and public discussion
                        attached to all the problems, to all the acts of the government, and nothing
                        was possible, nothing became definitively the law of the country, which had
                        not previously been discussed — discussed everywhere, and by everybody.”
                        “One great fact is made manifest in the recent elections. The country has
                        given its adhesion, its serious and free adhesion, to the policy which was
                        presented before it. Do not search for an explanation of the fact in any
                        pretended manœuvres and electoral <hi rendition="#i">miseres</hi>. Take it
                        as the veritable sentiment of the country on its intelligence, in the idea
                        which it has formed of the situation and of the conduct of the government.”
                        Our readers will admit that these are matchless specimens of “lying made
                        easy”. If any doubt, let them read the following important communication and
                        their doubts will be at once satisfied: —</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our own
                                Correspondent.)</hi></hi></hi></p>
                <p>The Chambers are now <choice>
                        <sic>assembled,</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">assembled.</corr>
                    </choice> The Chamber of Peers have, as usual, nothing to do, now that they have
                    disposed of the case of Joseph Henry, the new-fashioned regicide. The Chamber of
                    Deputies are busily engaged in verifying the returns of members, and they profit
                    by this opportunity to show the spirit which animates them. Never, since the
                    revolution of 1830, has there been displayed such bare-faced impudence and
                    contempt of public opinion. Three-fifths, at least, of the Deputies are thorough
                    friends of the ministry; or, in other words, either great capitalists,
                    stock-jobbers and railway speculators of the Paris Exchange, bankers, large
                    manufacturers, etc., or their obedient servants. The present legislature is,
                    more than any preceding one, the fulfilment of the words of Laffitte, the day
                    after the revolution of July: Henceforth we, the bankers, shall govern France.
                    It is the most striking proof that the government of France is in the hands of
                    the great monied aristocracy, the <hi rendition="#i">haute-bourgeoisie</hi>. The
                    fate of France is decided, not in the Cabinet of the Tuileries, not in the
                    Palace of Peers, not even in the Palace of Deputies, but on the Exchange of
                    Paris. The actual ministers are not Messrs. Guizot and Duchatel, but Messrs.
                    Rothschild, Fould, and the rest of the large Paris bankers, whose tremendous
                    fortunes make them the most eminent representatives of the rest of their class.
                    They govern the ministry, and the ministry take care that in the elections none
                    but men devoted to the present system, and to those who profit by this system,
                    are carried. This time they have had a most signal success; government patronage
                    and bribery of every description, united to the influence of the chief
                    capitalists, upon a limited number of voters (less than 200.000), who all
                    belong, more or less, to their own class, the terror spread among monied men by
                    the timely attempt to shoot the king, and ultimately the certainty that
                    Louis-Philippe will not survive the present Chambers (whose powers expire in
                    1851), all these things united were sufficient to quench all serious opposition
                    in most of the elective assemblies. And now, this precious Chamber having met,
                    they take proper care of themselves. The independent electors have sent in
                    hundreds of petitions and protests against the returns of ministerial members,
                    stating and proving, or offering to prove, that almost in every case the
                    elections have been carried by the grossest illegalities committed by government
                    officers; proving bribery, corruption, intimidation, patronage of every
                    description to have been employed. But the majority never take the slightest
                    notice of these facts. Every opposition deputy who raises his voice to protest
                    against such abomination is hooted down by hisses, noise, or cries of “Division,
                    division”. Every illegality is covered by a sanctioning vote. The money lords
                    rejoice in their strength, and guessing it will not last very long, they make
                    the best of the present moment. You may easily imagine that out of this narrow
                    circle of capitalists there exists a general opposition against the present
                    government, and those whose interests it serves. The centre of this opposition
                    is Paris, where the money lords have so little influence upon constituencies,
                    that of the fourteen deputies of the department of the Seine only two are
                    ministerialists and twelve belong to the opposition. The majority of the middle
                    class, voters of Paris, belong to the party of Thiers and O. Barrot; they want
                    to do away with the exclusive rule of Rothschild and Co., to recover an
                    honourable and independent position for France in her external relations, and
                    perhaps a little bit of electoral reform. The majority of non-voting trades-men,
                    shopkeepers, &amp;c., are of a more radical cast, and demand an electoral
                    reform, which would give them the vote; a number of them are also partisans of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> or <hi rendition="#i">Reforme</hi>, and
                    join themselves to the democratic party, which embraces the great bulk of the
                    working classes, and is itself divided into different sections, the most
                    numerous of which, at least in Paris, is formed by the Communists. The present
                    system is attacked by all these different sections, and, of course, by each in a
                    different manner. But there has been started, a short time ago, a new mode of
                    attack which deserves to be mentioned. A working man has written a pamphlet
                    against the head of the system, not against Louis-Philippe, but against
                    “Rothschild I. King of Jews”. The success of this pamphlet (it has now gone
                    through some twenty editions), shows how much this was an attack in the right
                    direction. King Rothschild has been obliged to publish two defences against
                    these attacks of a man whom nobody knows, and the whole of whose property
                    consists in the suit of clothes he wears. The public have taken up the
                    controversy with the greatest interest. Some thirty pamphlets have been
                    published pro and con. The hatred against Rothschild and the money lords is
                    enormous, and a German paper says, Rothschild might take this as a warning that
                    he had better take up his head-quarters somewhere else than upon the
                    ever-burning volcano of Paris.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>