<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_v34_bpk_kfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Grand Democratic Demonstrations in Paris</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-10-09</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich, George Julian Harney:] Grand Democratic
                    Demonstrations in Paris. In: Northern Star. Vol. IX. Nr. 464,
                    3. Oktober 1846. S. 4/5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Grand Democratic Demonstrations in
                            Paris.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">2</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1846-10-03</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’
                            Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">IX</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">464</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">4-5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">6-1</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1846-09-21" notAfter="1846-10-01">Ende September bis Anfang Oktober
                    1846</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">We stated in last Saturday’s <hi rendition="#i">Northern
                            Star</hi>, that the French Democrats designed to dine together on the
                        20th of September, in celebration of the glorious event celebrated by the
                        Fraternal Democrats in London, but that they had been prevented carrying
                        their design into execution by the arbitrary conduct of the police and
                        government agents. We have since received the following communication from a
                        correspondent, by which it will be seen that the banquet really did take
                        place in Paris, in spite of the brutal <pb n="5"/> tyranny of the agents of
                        the detestable Louis Philippe: —</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Grand Democratic Demonstrations in
                            Paris.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>In France, government seem determined not to allow anybody to have banquets, to
                    give toasts, or to speak publicly their sentiments, except M. Guizot, and his
                    creatures. <hi rendition="#i">They</hi> may meet together, and the police
                    themselves go about and invite the citizens to come and hear the eloquent
                    speeches of Guizot and Co. Here they proclaim that France was never more happy
                    and prosperous than at the present moment — that entire liberty exists, that
                    political factions and corruption are things forgotten. But the moment the
                    political reformers, or the communists, wish to have their banquets, to give
                    their toasts, to make known their grievances, and to show that France is really
                    neither free nor happy — that government only maintains itself by corruption;
                    that moment the <hi rendition="#i">prefects</hi> issue proclamations, the
                    soldiers are called out, the whole police is on foot, and the citizens who do
                    not believe in Louis Philippe, and M. Guizot, are not allowed to dine together.
                    At <hi rendition="#i">Mans, department de la Sarthe,</hi> five hundred political
                    reformers intended to have had a public dinner, on the 20th of September, but
                    the moment the prefect was informed of their intention, he issued a proclamation
                    forbidding the banquet, and declaring that if they persisted he would employ <hi rendition="#i">la force armee</hi> — brute force. Soldiers were marched into
                    Mans, guns arrived, and the town had the appearance of being besieged by some
                    terrible enemy. And for what was all this fuss, for the purpose of preventing
                    five hundred reformers from peaceably dining together. Strange liberty this!</p>
                <p>However, government had it not all their own way, for when <hi rendition="#i">La
                        Reforme</hi> heard of the strange doings of <hi rendition="#i">M. le Prefect
                        de la Sarthe</hi>, it proclaimed that banquets should take place on the 20th
                    of September, in all the twelve arrondissements of Paris — and the reformers
                    have kept their word in spite of the government. About sixty banquets took place
                    in Paris, on the 20th, at which more than three thousand citizens, of all ranks
                    and classes assisted.</p>
                <p>The greatest order reigned during the proceedings, and the speeches and toasts
                    were enthusiastically cheered. We subjoin several of the toasts given in the
                    different arrondissements: —</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. Electoral reform.</item>
                    <item>2. Political probity.</item>
                    <item>3. The sovereignty of the people.</item>
                    <item>4. The resurrection of Poland.</item>
                    <item>5. The union of all Democrats.</item>
                    <item>6. The destruction of the Bastiles.</item>
                    <item>7. The deliverance of Italy and Spain.</item>
                    <item>8. Universal freedom.</item>
                    <item>9. Education of the people.</item>
                    <item>10. The Revolution of 1830.</item>
                    <item>11. The liberty of the press, etc.</item>
                </list>
                <p>At the banquet of working men the following toasts were given, and most
                    enthusiastically received. They show us that our brethren on the other side of
                    the channel are not behind us.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>1. To equality, the noble aim towards which we march; the noble aim of all
                        our wishes — to equality, which shows in every man a brother; learns us to
                        love him, and teaches us that all have a right to the bounties which nature
                        has given us.</item>
                    <item>2. The fraternity of nations, and the union of all democrats of the
                        earth.</item>
                    <item>3. The extinction of all superstitions.</item>
                    <item>4. Political equality the means, social equality the end.</item>
                </list>
                <p>At several places the police entered the rooms after the banquet had been
                    concluded, and commanded the assemblages to disperse. The reformers obeyed,
                    having previously accomplished the purpose of their re-unions. In no case, as
                    regards Paris, did the police succeed in breaking up the assemblages until the
                    banquets were over, and the good work done.</p>
                <p>In the first arrondissement, the president of the Reformers made application to
                    the proprietors of three Hotels for the use of their saloons, but in both cases
                    was told that the proprietors regretted to be compelled to close their doors,
                    but they were forced to this by the police, who had that very morning warned
                    them against granting their saloons to the Reformers, threatening them with
                    vengeance if they disobeyed this tyrannical mandate. Notwithstanding these
                    repulses the banquet was held, in this, as well as in the other
                    arrondissements.</p>
                <p>Since the above was written we have learned that the Reformers of Dole have been
                    subjected to similar treatment to that which the Reformers of <choice>
                        <sic>Manns</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">Mans</corr>
                    </choice> were subjected to. They had assembled to hold a large banquet when
                    they were interrupted by the armed force. They accordingly dispersed, but
                    immediately re-assembled in different groups, and held a number of small
                    banquets, which passed off with the greatest enthusiasm. The proceedings were
                    similar to those described above.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">We are glad that the French Democrats have taught their government such a lesson.
                    They have shown that the spirit which animated their fathers is not dead, and we
                    are convinced that in spite of all Bastilles and all Marshal Bugeauds to command
                    them, they will rise once more and assert and maintain their rights, — the
                    rights of man. — In the <hi rendition="#i">Reformistes</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Communists</hi> is the strength of France and the hope for a
                    better future, they will free her from corruption, they will regenerate her; let
                    them, therefore, unite; let all the Democrats in France unite, and they will
                    form a party great and strong enough to conquer.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">We fully and entirely agree with the sentiments given at the banquets in Paris,
                    and we recognise every Frenchman, who struggles for political and social liberty
                    as our brother. We, therefore, would advise the Reformists, and especially the
                    editors of <hi rendition="#i">La Reform</hi>, to lay aside their prejudices
                    against England — the Communists have already done so — not to cry out against
                    “perfidious Albion”, when they believe the English government has insulted
                    France, but always to make a distinction between the people and the government,
                    and to look also upon those Englishmen, who in their country struggle for
                    political and social freedom, as their friends and brothers. Let the governments
                    of the two countries quarrel about an obscure island in the Pacific Ocean, or
                    about the marriage of a Spanish princess, we will not espouse their quarrels;
                    our principles are the same, we want to extinguish national hatred, we want the
                    fraternity of nations. Let the friends of freedom in both countries bear always
                    in their minds and follow the glorious words pronounced by the leader of the
                    English Chartists, Mr. Feargus O’Connor, at the banquet of the Fraternal
                    Democrats: — “I have never sought to limit the struggle for liberty to country,
                    creed or colour, for I have invariably declared that I cared not where the
                    country, what the colour, or which the creed of the patriot was — that if he
                    loved liberty and struggled for it, I would call him brother, and take him by
                    the hand.”</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>