<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">State of Parties in France</title>
                <title type="sub">Discussion on the Address in the Chamber of Deputies</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-05</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] State of Parties in France. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 488, 27. Februar 1847. S. 1.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">State of Parties in France.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Discussion on the Address in the Chamber of Deputies.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1847-02-27"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">488</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2-3</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-02-11" notAfter="1847-02-20">Mitte Februar 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">State of Parties in France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our own Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Discussion on the Address in the Chamber of Deputies.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Paris.</hi> — This long and tedious discussion has been last brought to a close,
                    and the ministerial address, with very few amendments, has been voted by an
                    immense majority. The discussion itself was, as usual, a sort of programme of
                    the whole session; it showed the spirit in which the different questions will be
                    treated, both by the Ministerialists and the Opposition: it showed the numerical
                    and moral strength of both parties; the arguments and the principles which, in
                    the course of the spring and summer, will be brought forward. This discussion
                    gives us, in short, the spirit of the whole session, and, therefore, deserves
                    attention.</p>
                <p>The great numerical preponderance of the Ministerial party has again been
                    established beyond any doubt. The hopes which were here and there expressed,
                    that this conservative majority would be split into two fractions of <hi rendition="#i">conservateurs bornes</hi>, “whole hog” conservatives, and <hi rendition="#i">conservateurs progressifs</hi>, has, as was to be expected, proved an
                    egregious fallacy. In spite of some impotent “young conservatives” who try, at
                    the same time, to keep up the present system, and march onward towards progress
                    — an impossibility evident to the meanest intelligence — M. Guizot
                    rules and reigns over the votes and conscience, of the fearful host of
                    “centriers”, and “ventrus”, or belly-men, as they are significantly called (big
                    whigs, as I heard a similar party called at Manchester). Indeed, the “belly” is
                    the most prominent and predominant party of the present Chamber; a mass composed
                    of bankers, large merchants, and manufacturers, their agents, and those of the government, extensive landowners, who
                    have started up since the Revolution, by buying up the small and mortgaged
                    properties of the peasants, and such like. They have been elected chiefly by the
                    small electoral districts of the country and petty towns, where their interest
                    either monied or landed, is predominant, and where a constituency of from 100 to
                    300 electors allows the government to hold the balance of power by corruption.
                    The deputies of this party represent generally none but their own class, <hi rendition="#i">i. e.,</hi> the proprietors of the Bank of France, the money
                    lords of the Paris Exchange, &amp;c.; in short, the monied interest above all,
                    and partly the manufacturers, mine proprietors, and large landowners.</p>
                <p>This compact mass of wealth, influence and votes,
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20180905T172952+0200" comment="?"?>in
                    very meanly<?oxy_comment_end?> indeed faced by an opposition, which, besides
                    being much less numerous, are at the same time more than ever divided. That
                    fraction, which in numbers and influence comes next to the majority, is that led
                    on by M. Thiers. It is called the “left centre”, and is made up of elements very
                    similar to the majority. Here we find men almost equal in wealth to those of the
                    majority, but who upon the whole represent rather the manufacturing and shipping than the monied interest; a fact which undoubtedly will
                    be proved when the discussion on the Free Trade question comes on. While the
                    interests of the majority require peace and a good understanding with England,
                    and suffer in no way by the competition of the English manufacturer,<note place="foot" n="*">
                        <p>We must except the coal and iron proprietors, who mostly adhere to M.
                            Guizot, and who could not compete, upon Free Trade terms, with
                            England.</p>
                    </note> M. Thiers rallies round himself the bulk of all those interests which
                    are endangered, both in the home and foreign market, by English competition.
                    This is the reason why M. Thiers and his papers are strongly opposed to Free
                    Trade, while M. Guizot and his party consider it as an open question. One of the
                    ministers has said to some of the Free Traders — “Be strong, and perhaps
                    we may then be with you.” This is, at the <choice>
                        <sic>some</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">same</corr>
                    </choice> time, the solution of Guizot’s “cordial understanding” policy, and
                    Thiers’s anti-English ideas. That the parts of both actors upon the
                    Spanish-marriage question appear exchanged, alters nothing. It is a mere passive
                    affair. M. Guizot and his party <hi rendition="#i">must</hi> necessarily return
                    to the English alliance, and M. Thiers may easily profess friendly feelings
                    toward England, because neither he nor his adherents would venture to involve
                    the country in a war with England. The necessity of the English alliance is
                    allowed by both parties; they differ upon the extent only to which it should be
                    carried.</p>
                <p>The above-mentioned anti-English interests are not exclusively represented by the
                    “left centre”, but more or less by deputies of all fractions of the opposition.
                    The left centre, however, may count upon the assistance of those fractions in
                    every question where these interests are at stake, and therefore may be said to
                    represent them <hi rendition="#i">par excellence</hi>.</p>
                <p>The waverlug policy of M. Thiers and his inseparable Odilon Barrot have induced a
                    portion of the members of the “left centre” to try an alliance with the more
                    moderate members of the “left”, and to constitute a new party under the
                    leadership of Messrs. Billault and Dufaure. They pretended to carry out in good
                    earnest those professions which M. Thiers always abandoned when he got into
                    power, or where he merely got a chance to acquire it. Their attempt has,
                    however, signally failed. Their so-called national policy was limited to some
                    few differences with M. Thiers upon the Spanish question, and their strength was
                    proved, by a division, not to exceed twenty-eight members.</p>
                <p>The whole of the left centre, and particularly M. Thiers’s fraction, speak very
                    much about a “strong government”, and a “national line of policy”, as if this
                    strong government was possible as long as the present class of electors retain
                    their voting monopoly; as if Guizot, with his overwhelming majority, was not the
                    strongest possible government under present circumstances; as if the
                    money-lords, fund and stock-jobbers, under whose influence the deputies are
                    elected, cared a farthing for a national policy, and would not rather put up
                    with any insult than interrupt by a war their profitable jobbing! And such
                    nonsense is demanded by the very men who would not alter an iota of the present
                    electoral system, and who, by their necessity only, have been forced to propose
                    some insensible alterations in a late pamphlet of M. Thiers’s friend, Duvergier
                    de Hauranne!</p>
                <p>Follow the more or less Radical members of the “left”. If the “centre” or
                    majority, represented the bulk and influence of the contended monied and funded
                    interest, the “left centre”, the more or less discounted manufacturing interest,
                    and both together the <hi rendition="#i">“haute-bourgeoisie”</hi> — what
                    you would call money-lords and cotton-lords in England — the “left”
                    represents the more modest portion — the inferior ranks of the middle
                    classes — the <hi rendition="#i">“moyenne et petite bourgeoisie”</hi>
                    — <hi rendition="#k">the shopocracy</hi>. This class is, however, divided into two fractions; a
                    fact arising from its vacillating, undecided position, between the ruling <hi rendition="#i">haute-bourgeoisie</hi> and the people. The inferior ranks of
                    the middle classes, small tradesmen, shopkeepers, &amp;c., have neither the
                    energy nor the influence which would enable them to govern a large country; they
                    cannot form a distinct class, with distinct interests, equally opposed to those
                    of the great money-lords and to those of the people; while they suffer from the
                    pressure of the concentrated capitals and industrial establishments of the
                    ruling large capitalists, are yet inseparably connected with those of that
                    class. From this go-between character of the inferior middle classes, it follows
                    naturally, that those among them who, upon the whole, would rather undergo the
                    present pressure than risk their fortunes by political changes in such a
                    hot-blooded nation as the French go to strengthen the ranks of the ministerial
                    or the Thiers-Barrot party, while those who suffer enough under the present
                    system to drive them on to risk something for bettering their position, form a
                    party of their own, and make more or less concessions to democracy. The first
                    portion, that which rallies around the two “centres”, and which mostly consists
                    of admirers of Mr. Odilon Barrot and his soporific paper <hi rendition="#i">Le
                        Siecle</hi> (the Century), has entirely given itself up to vassalage under
                    the <hi rendition="#i">haute-bourgeoisie</hi>. The other portion supports the
                    deputies of the “left”, who, in their turn, partake of the indecisive character
                    of their supporters. The whole of the left, it is true, demand Parliamentary
                    reform — extension of the suffrage; but to what extent? There begin the
                    differences. The more enlightened clearly see, that there is no chance of a
                    lasting government betwixt high-bourgeoisie rule on the one hand, and popular
                    democracy <choice>
                        <sic>on;</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">on</corr>
                    </choice> the other and that, therefore, all changes of the voting system
                    falling short of Universal Suffrage, will either prove useless against the
                    present system of government, or inevitably lead to pure democracy. They,
                    therefore, resign all hope of erecting a shopocratic government, and openly
                    preach alliance with the people. But the greater part of them continue to hope
                    for the practicability of a system which would place the majority in the hands
                    of the shopkeepers, and small traders and manufacturers, and which, by this
                    means, would unite with equal success the corruption of the present system and
                    the “excesses of democracy”. They are, therefore, supporters of monarchy, while
                    the first-mentioned minority of the left are avowed republicans. There are, on
                    account of the many fractions of this party, and of their numerical weakness, no
                    recognised leaders amongst them.</p>
                <p>The remainder of the chamber is made up by the “Legitimiste”, who are very few in
                    number, particularly since the last election. The south of France is the country
                    where they possess their chief strength; but even there the spread of
                    civilisation continually weakens the influence, and even the convictions of the
                    friends of the “ancien regime”. The utter impotency of this party cannot be more
                    clearly proved than by the speech of M. de Genoude, deputy for Toulouse, and
                    editor of the <hi rendition="#i">Gazette de France</hi>, and the way it was
                    received by the Chamber. M. de Genoude, a clever fellow, he tried everything, to
                    make something attractive of legitimacy; he allied it with democracy, he
                    confessed the faults of the Restoration, he cried out against the treaties of
                    1815; no go, he was not even listened to, and his speech made not the slightest
                    effect.</p>
                <p>In my next article, I shall show these different elements of the Chamber in their
                    action upon each other, and comment on the discussion of the different
                    questions, which, during the first fortnight of February, occupied the heads and
                    tongues of the French collective wisdom.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>