<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Prussian Constitution</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-06</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">E[ngels, Friedrich]: The Prussian Constitution. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 489, 6. März 1847. S. 3.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Prussian Constitution.</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">[Friedrich] E[ngels]</persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1847-03-06"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">489</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">4-5</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-02-21" notAfter="1847-02-26">Ende Februar 1847 (siehe "The Fraternal Democrats", S. 8)</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Prussian Constitution.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our German Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>At last this long-expected piece of workmanship has made its appearance! At last
                    — if we believe the <hi rendition="#i">Times</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">Globe</hi>, some French and some German papers — Prussia has passed
                    over to the ranks of constitutional countries. The <hi rendition="#i">Northern
                        Star</hi>, however, has already sufficiently proved that this so-called
                    Constitution is nothing but a trap offered to the Prussian people to cheat them
                    of the rights promised by the late king, at the time he wanted popular support.
                    That this is the fact, that Frederick William tries by this so-called
                    Constitution to obtain money without being obliged to make concessions to public
                    opinion, is certain beyond all doubt. The democratic papers of all countries
                    — in France, particularly the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Reforme</hi>, nay, the ministerial <hi rendition="#i">Journal
                        des Debats</hi>, — agree in this opinion. The fettered German press
                    itself stammers words which allow no other conclusion, but that the movement
                    party in Prussia is quite aware of the sly intentions of their “open-hearted,
                    generous” king. The question then is this: will the king succeed in his plans?
                    Will the Central Assembly of Estates be either stupid or cowardly enough to
                    guarantee a new loan, without securing to the people extended liberties, and
                    thus give the king the means to continue the present system for an indefinite
                    length of time?</p>
                <p>We answer: No; they will not, they cannot.</p>
                <p>The hitherto followed plan of government in Prussia was the consequence of the
                    relative position of the nobility and the middle classes in Prussia. The
                    nobility had lost too much of its former strength, wealth and influence, to
                    dominate the king as formerly it had done. The middle classes were not yet
                    strong enough to overcome the dead weight of the nobility, which cramped their
                    commercial and industrial progress. Thus the king, representing the central
                    power of the state, and supported by the numerous class of government officers,
                    civil and military, besides having the army at his disposal, was enabled to keep
                    down the middle classes by the nobility, and the nobility by the middle classes,
                    by flattering now the interests of the one, and then those of the other; and
                    balancing, as much as possible, the influence of both. This stage of absolute
                    monarchy has been gone through by almost all the civilized countries of Europe,
                    and in those most advanced it has now given place to the government of the
                    middle classes.</p>
                <p>Prussia, the most advanced of German countries, had hitherto wanted a middle
                    class, wealthy, strong, united and energetic enough to shake off the domination
                    of absolutism, and to crush the remains of feudal nobility. The two contending
                    elements, nobility and middle classes, are, however, placed in such
                    circumstances, that by the natural progress of industry and civilization, the
                    one (the middle classes) must increase in wealth and influence,while the other
                    (the nobility) must decrease, impoverish and lose more and more its ascendancy.
                    While, therefore, the Prussian nobility and large landed proprietors, found
                    themselves every year in a worse position, first, by the ruinous wars with
                    France in the beginning of this century; then by the English Corn Laws, which
                    shut them out from the market of that country; then by the competition of
                    Australia, in one of their chief productions, wool, and by many other
                    circumstances — the middle classes of Prussia increased enormously in
                    wealth, productive powers, and influence in general. The wars with France, the
                    shutting out of English manufactured goods from the Continental markets, created
                    manufacturing industry in Prussia; and when peace was re-established, the
                    upstart manufacturers were powerful enough to force government to grant them
                    protective duties (1818). Soon afterwards, the Zollverein was founded, a union
                    which almost exclusively advanced the interests of the middle classes. And,
                    above all, the violent competitive struggle arising between the different
                    trading and manufacturing nations during these last 30 years of peace, forced
                    the somewhat indolent Prussian middle classes, either to allow themselves to be
                    entirely ruined by foreign competition, or to set to work in good earnest, as
                    well as their neighbours.</p>
                <p>The progress of the middle classes was very little visible up to the year 1840,
                    when the ascension to the throne of a new king appeared to them the proper
                    moment to show that, since 1815, things were rather changed in Prussia. I need
                    not recapitulate how the middle class movement has progressed since that time;
                    how all parts of the kingdom acceded to it, until at last all the middle
                    classes, a great part of the peasantry, and not a few of the nobility, joined in
                    it. A representative constitution, liberty of the press, open courts of law,
                    immoveability of the judges, trial by jury — such were the demands of the
                    middle classes. The peasantry or small landed proprietors saw very well —
                    in the more enlightened parts of the kingdom at least — that such measures
                    were for their interests too, being the only ones by which they could hope to
                    free themselves from the remnants of feudality, and to have that influence upon
                    the making of laws which it was desirable for them to possess. The poorer part
                    of the nobility thought that the constitutional system might, perhaps, give them
                    such a position in the legislature as their interests demanded; and that, at all
                    events, this system could not be more ruinous to them than that under which they
                    lived. It was principally the nobility of Prussia Proper and Posen, who, being
                    severely oppressed by want of markets for their produce, acceded to the Liberal
                    movement from such considerations.</p>
                <p>The middle classes themselves got more and more into an uncomfortable position.
                    They had increased their manufacturing and mining concerns, as well as their
                    shipping, to a considerable extent; they were the chief furnishers for the whole
                    market of the Zollverein; their wealth and numbers had increased very much. But
                    during the last ten or fifteen years the enormous progress of English
                    manufacturers and mining operations have threatened them with a deadly
                    competition. Every glut in the English market threw large quantities of English
                    goods into the Zollverein, where they were sold at prices more ruinous to the
                    Germans than to the English, because these latter made, during the times of
                    flourishing trade, large profits in the American and other markets, while the
                    Prussians could never sell their produce anywhere but within the circle of their
                    own line of customs. Their shipping were almost excluded from the ports of
                    foreign nations, while ships of all flags entered the Prussian ports on equal
                    conditions with the Prussians. Thus, although there is comparatively little
                    capital in Prussia, there commenced a difficulty of investing this capital
                    profitably. Trade appeared to be labouring under a continual pressure;
                    factories, machinery, stock in trade, were slowly, but continually, depreciated;
                    and this general uneasiness was for a moment only interrupted by the railway
                    speculations which, within the last eight years, were started in Prussia. These
                    speculations, by raising the value of ready money, increased the depreciation of
                    stock in trade, and were themselves, on an average, not very profitable on
                    account of the comparatively thin population and trade of the greater part of
                    the country. They offered, however, a still better chance of profit than other
                    industrial investments; and thus every one who could dispose of some capital
                    engaged n them. Very soon these speculations assumed, as usual, a feverish
                    character, and ended in a crisis which now for about a twelvemonth has oppressed
                    the Prussian money markets. Thus the middle classes found themselves in a very
                    uncomfortable position in the beginning of the present year: the money markets
                    under the pressure of an extraordinary want of coin; the manufacturing districts
                    requiring more than ever those protective duties which the government refused to
                    grant; the coast towns requiring navigation laws as the only means to relieve
                    them; and, over and above all, a rise in the corn markets, which brought the
                    country to a state approaching famine. All these causes of discontent operated
                    at the same time, and more strongly so upon the people: the Silesian
                    linenweavers in the greatest distress; the cotton factories stopped; in the
                    large manufacturing district of the Rhine almost all hands out of work, the
                    potato crop mostly ruined, and bread at famine prices. The moment was evidently
                    come for the middle classes to take the government out of the hands of an
                    imbecile king, weak nobility, and self-conceited <choice>
                        <sic>bureaucracry</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">bureaucracy</corr>
                    </choice>, and to secure it to themselves.</p>
                <p>It is a curious fact, but which is repeated at every revolutionary epoch, that at
                    the very moment when the leading class of a movement ist most favourably placed
                    for the accomplishment of that movement, the old worn-out government is reduced
                    to beg the assistance of this same leading class. Thus in 1789, in France, when
                    famine, bad trade, and divisions among the nobility pushed, so to say, the
                    middle classes to a revolution — at that very moment the government found
                    its money resources exhausted, and was reduced to begin the revolution by the
                    convocation of the States-General. Thus in 1847 in Prussia. At the very moment
                    when the more indolent Prussian middle classes are almost forced by
                    circumstances to change the governmental system, at that moment the king, by
                    want of money, is forced to commence that change of system, and to convocate in
                    his turn the Prussian States-General. It is indubitable that the States would
                    offer him much less resistance than they will now, if the money market was easy,
                    the factories at full work (which would be caused by a flourishing trade and
                    ready sale, and consequent high prices for manufactured goods in England) and
                    corn at a reasonably low price. But so it is: in times of approaching
                    revolution, the progressive classes of society have always all chances on their
                    side.</p>
                <p>I have, during the course of 1845 and 1846, more than once shown to the readers
                    of the <hi rendition="#i">Star</hi>, that the King of Prussia was in a very
                    embarrassed financial situation; I have at the same time called their attention
                    to the several clever plans by which his ministers sought to extricate him; and
                    predicted that the whole affair must end by a convocation of the States-General.
                    The event, then, was neither unexpected, nor, as it now is represented, caused
                    by the free grace of his squandering majesty; nothing but sheer necessity,
                    poverty and distress could move him to such a step, and there is not a child in
                    Prussia but knows this. The only question, then, is this: — Will the
                    Prussian middle classes, by investing a new loan with their guarantee, allow the
                    king to go on as he has done hitherto and to disregard for another seven years
                    their petitions and their wants?</p>
                <p>We have already answered this question. They cannot do this. We have proved it
                    from the situation of the respective classes, and we shall now prove it from the
                    composition of the States-General themselves.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Members of high and low nobility <space dim="horizontal"/> 311</item>
                    <item>Do. for towns and peasantry <space dim="horizontal"/> 306</item>
                </list>
                <p>As the king has declared his intention to increase the members of the high
                    nobility (80 in all) by new creations of peers, we may add to the nobility,
                    about 30 more; 341 members of nobility, or government party. Deduct from this
                    number the liberal fractions of the lower nobility, namely, all the nobility of
                    Prussia Proper, two-thirds of that of Posen, and some members of the Rhenish,
                    Silesian, Brandenburg and Westphalian nobility, say 70 liberal members, voting
                    with the towns and peasantry, and the position of the parties is as <choice>
                        <sic>follow</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">follows</corr>
                    </choice>: —</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Nobility, or government party <space dim="horizontal"/>271</item>
                    <item>Towns and peasantry, or liberal opposition <space dim="horizontal"/>376</item>
                </list>
                <p>Thus, even allowing that thirty or forty towns or peasantry members from the
                    remote districts should vote for the government, there will always be a liberal
                    majority of from twenty-five to fifty votes remaining, and with a little energy
                    on the part of the Liberals, it will be easy to meet every demand for money with
                    another demand for liberal institutions. There is besides, no doubt, that, under
                    present circumstances, the people will support the middle classes, and by their
                    pressure from without, which indeed is very much wanted, strengthen the courage
                    and enliven the energies of those within.</p>
                <p>Thus, the Prussian constitution, insignificant in itself, is, for all that, the
                    beginning of a new epoch for that country, and for all Germany. It marks the
                    downfall of absolutism and nobility, and the ascendancy of the middle classes;
                    it marks the beginning of a movement which will very soon lead to a
                    representative constitution for the middle classes, a free press, independent
                    judges and trial by jury, and which will end God knows where. It marks the
                    repetition of 1789 in Prussia. And if the revolutionary movement which now
                    begins, will directly interest the middle classes only, it is yet not at all
                    indifferent to the interests of the people. From the moment the power of the
                    middle classes is constituted, from that moment begins the separate and distinct
                    democratic movement. In the struggle against despotism and aristocracy, the
                    people, the democratic party, cannot but play a secondary part; the first place
                    belongs to the middle classes. From the moment, however, the middle classes
                    establish their own government, identify themselves with a new despotism and
                    aristocracy against the people, from that moment the struggle is simplified,
                    reduced to two parties, and changes, by that circumstance, into a “war to the
                    knife”. The history of the French and English democratic parties fully proves
                    this.</p>
                <p>There is another circumstance to be remarked. The conquest of public power by the
                    middle classes of Prussia will change the political position of all European
                    countries. The alliance of the North will be dissolved. Austria and Russia, the
                    chief spoliators of Poland, will be entirely isolated from the rest of Europe,
                    for Prussia carries along with her the smaller states of Germany, who all have
                    constitutional governments. Thus the balance of power in Europe will be entirely
                    changed by the consequences of this insignificant constitution; the desertion of
                    three-fourths of Germany from the camp of stationary Eastern Europe into that of
                    progressive Western Europe. In February, 1846, broke out the last Polish
                    insurrection. In February, 1847, Frederick William convocates his
                    States-General. <hi rendition="#i">The vengeance of Poland is drawing nigh!</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#right">E.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>