<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Decline and Approaching Fall of Guizot. — Position of
                    the French Bourgeoisie</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-06</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The Decline and Approaching Fall of Guizot. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 506, 3. Juli 1847. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Decline and Approaching Fall of Guizot. — Position of the French Bourgeoisie.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication" when="1847-07-03"/>
                        <date type="creation" when="1847-06-26"/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">506</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">1-2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date when="1847-06-26"/>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">The following important communication from our own correspondent in the French
                    capital unveils the tottering position of the Guizot Ministry, and foreshadows
                    the tremendous changes of which, ere long, France will be the scene.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Decline and approaching Fall of Guizot. — Position of the French Bourgeoisie.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>The English stage had better give over playing <hi rendition="#i">The School for
                        Scandal</hi>, for, indeed, the greatest school of this sort has been set up
                    in Paris, in the Chamber of Deputies. The amount of scandalous matter collected
                    and brought forward there during the last four or five weeks, is really
                    unprecedented in the annals of parliamentary discussion. You recollect the
                    inscription Mr Duncombe once proposed for your own glorious House of Commons,
                        <hi rendition="#i">“The most degrading and infamous proceedings take place
                        within these <choice>
                            <sic>walls”</sic>
                            <corr cert="high">walls”.</corr>
                        </choice></hi> Well, here is a match for your own set of middle-class
                    legislators; here are proceedings which will put British rascality to the blush.
                    The honour of Old England is saved; Mr Roebuck is outdone by M. de Girardin; Sir
                    James Graham is beaten by M. Duchatel.</p>
                <p>I shall not undertake to give you the whole list of scandalous affairs brought to
                    light within the last few weeks; I shall not say a word about the several dozen
                    of bribery cases brought before the juries; not a word about M. Gudin, the
                    ordnance officer of the King, who, not without some degree of cleverness, made
                    an attempt to introduce the habits of the swell mob into the palace of the
                    Tuileries; I shall not give you a lengthy report of the dirty affair of Gen.
                    Cubières, peer of France, formerly Minister of War, who, under pretext of
                    bribing the ministry into granting the concession of allowing the formation of a
                    mining company, cheated the said company out of forty shares, which he cooly put
                    into his own pocket, and on account of which he is now under trial before the
                    Chamber of Peers. No; I shall give you only a few choice bits — a few samples
                    taken from two or three sittings of the Deputies, which will enable you to judge
                    of the rest.</p>
                <p>M. Emile de Girardin, deputy, and editor of the daily paper <hi rendition="#i">La
                        Presse</hi>, supporting in both characters the new party of <hi rendition="#i">Progressive Conservatives</hi>, and for a considerable time
                    past one of the most violent opponents of the Ministry, whom until lately he had
                    supported, is a man of great talent and activity, but without any principles.
                    From the beginning of his public career he unhesitatingly employed any means to
                    make himself an important public character. It was he who forced Armand Carrel,
                    the celebrated editor of the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi>, to a duel, and
                    shot him, thus delivering himself from a dangerous competitor. The support of
                    such a man, proprietor of an influential paper, and member of the Chamber of
                    Deputies, was of course very important to the government; but M. de Girardin
                    sold his support (for he always <hi rendition="#i">sold</hi> it) at a very high
                    price. There was a deal of business transacted between M. de Girardin and the
                    Ministry, but not always to the complete satisfaction of both parties. In the
                    meantime, M. de Girardin prepared himself for any turn which affairs might take.
                    Foreseeing the probability of a rupture with the Guizot ministry, he collected
                    accounts of scandalous transactions, bribings, and traffickings, which he was in
                    the best position to learn, and which were brought to him by his friends and
                    agents in high places. The turn which party discussions took this session showed
                    to him that the fall of Guizot and Duchatel was approaching. He was one of the
                    principal actors in the formation of the new “Progressive Conservative” party,
                    and repeatedly threatened the government with the full weight of his wrath, if
                    they persisted in their course. M. Guizot refused, in pretty scornful terms, any
                    compromise with the new party. These detached themselves from the majority, and
                    annoyed the government by their opposition. The financial and other discussions
                    of the Chamber unveiled so much scandal, that MM. Guizot and Duchatel were
                    obliged to throw several of their colleagues overboard in order to save
                    themselves. The vacant places, however, were filled by such insignificant men,
                    that no party was satisfied, and the Ministry were rather weakened than
                    fortified. Then came Cubieres’ affair, which elicited some doubts, even in the
                    majority, as to the possibility to keep M. Guizot in office. Now, at last, when
                    he saw the Ministry totally disorganised and weakened, now M. de Girardin
                    thought the moment had arrived when he might bring forth his Pandora’s box of
                    scandal, and achieve the ruin of a tottering government, by revelations fit to
                    shake the faith even of the <hi rendition="#k">“belly”</hi> of the Chamber.</p>
                <p>He commenced by accusing the Ministry of having sold a peerage for 80.000 francs,
                    but of not having kept their promise, after pocketing the money! The House of
                    Peers found themselves insulted by this assertion made in <hi rendition="#i">La
                        Presse</hi>, and asked leave from the Deputies to bring M. de Girardin
                    before their bar. The demand occasioned a discussion in the Deputies, in the
                    course of which M. de Girardin fully maintained his assertion, declaring he was
                    in possession of the proofs, but refusing to give any names, as he would not
                    play the part of a <hi rendition="#i">delator</hi>. He said, however, that three
                    times he had mentioned the matter privately to M. Guizot, who never denied the
                    fact, and that once he spoke about it to M. Duchatel, who replied — “It
                    was done during my absence, and I afterwards disapproved of it; it was M. Guizot
                    who did it.” The whole of this was flatly denied by M. Duchatel. “Then”, said M.
                    de Girardin, “I will give you the proof that the Ministry is quite in the habit
                    of proposing such transactions”; and he read a letter from General Alexander de
                    Girardin (the father, I believe, of M. Emile de Girardin; the latter is an
                    illegitimate child) to the King. This letter expressed General de G.’s gratitude
                    for the offer of a peerage made to him, but said at the same time, that M.
                    Guizot having afterwards made it a condition of the grant, that he (General de
                    G.) should use his influence with M. Emile de G. to prevent him opposing the
                    government. Gen. de G. would be no party to such a transaction, and, therefore,
                    declined the peerage. “O!” said M. Duchatel, “if this is all, we will just
                    mention, that M. Emile de Girardin himself offered to us to cease his opposition
                    if we would make him a peer, but we declined that offer.” <hi rendition="#i">Hinc illæ lachrymæ!</hi> But Duchatel replied not a word to the allegation
                    in the letter. The Chamber then voted that M. Emile de G. should be delivered up
                    to the peers for trial. He was tried, sustained the allegation, but declared,
                    the sold peerages not having been made out, he could not have attacked the
                    Chamber of Peers, but only the government. The peers then <hi rendition="#i">acquitted</hi> him. Girardin then brought forward another scandalous
                    affair. There was got up last year a large paper, called the <hi rendition="#i">Epoque</hi>, which was to support the government, to beat all opposition
                    papers out of the market, and to supersede the costly support of M. de
                    Girardin’s <hi rendition="#i">Presse</hi>. The experiment signally failed;
                    partly, too, through the intrigues of M. de Girardin himself, who has his finger
                    in every pie of that sort. Now, M. Duchatel had answered, when charged with
                    bribing the press, that the government had never paid any subsidies to any
                    paper. M. de Girardin, against this assertion, maintained the notorious fact,
                    that M. Duchatel, after a deal of begging on the part of the editors of the <hi rendition="#i">Epoque</hi>, had told them: “Well, gold and silver I have
                    non; but what I have that will I give unto you”; and had given them the
                    privilege for a third opera-house for Paris, which privilege the “gents” of the
                        <hi rendition="#i">Epoque</hi> sold for 100.000 f., of which sum 60.000 f.
                    were spent in support of the paper, and the remaining 40.000 f. went nobody
                    knows where to. This, too, was flatly denied by M. Duchatel; but the fact is
                    notorious.</p>
                <p>There were, besides, some similar transactions brought forward by M. de Girardin,
                    but these samples will be quite sufficient.</p>
                <p>Yesterday, in the Chamber of Deputies, M. de Girardin again got up and read some
                    letters, from which it appeared that M. Duchatel had caused the discussion in
                    the above peerage affair to be printed at the public expense, and sent it to all
                    town councils in the country; but that in this ministerial report neither M. de
                    Girardin’s nor M. Duchatel’s speeches were correctly reported; but; on the
                    contrary, both of them were arranged so as to make M. de Girardin appear as a
                    ridiculous calumniator, and M. Duchatel in the light of the purest and most
                    virtuous of men. As to the matter itself, he repeated all his assertions, and
                    defied the government either to have them disproved by a parliamentary
                    committee, or to bring him before a jury as a slanderer. In both cases, he said,
                    he should be bound to give the names of the parties and all particulars, and
                    thus be enabled to prove his accusations without placing himself in the position
                    of a common informer. This excited a general storm in the Chamber. M. Duchatel
                    denied; M. de Girardin re-asserted; M. Duchatel re-denied; M. de Girardin
                    re-reasserted, and so on, the whole accompanied by the shouts and counter-shouts
                    of the “choruses” of the Chamber. Other opposition members again defied the
                    ministry to have the matter looked into either by parliamentary inquiry, or by a
                    trial. At last M. Duchatel said, —</p>
                <p>“A parliamentary inquiry, gentlemen, would presuppose a doubt in the integrity of
                    the government on the part of the majority; and, therefore, the day this inquiry
                    should be granted our places would be occupied by others than us; if you have
                    any doubt tell us so plainly, and we shall resign immediately.”</p>
                <p>“Then”, said M. de Girardin, “there remains nothing but a trial. I am ready to
                    undergo it; place me before a jury, if you dare.”</p>
                <p>“No”, said M. Hebert, Minister of Justice, “we shall not, because the majority of
                    the Chamber will judge.”</p>
                <p>“But”, said M. Odillon Barrot, “this is not a political question; it is a <hi rendition="#i">legal</hi> one, and such a question is not within our
                    competence, but of that of the public courts of law. If M. de Girardin has
                    calumniated the government in his paper, why do you not have him tried for
                    it?”</p>
                <p>“We won’t!”</p>
                <p>“Well, but there is a plain allegation against other parties, too, of trafficking
                    in peerages; why not bring them up? And this affair with the <hi rendition="#i">Epoque</hi> and the opera privilege — if you are no parties to that,
                    as you say, why do you not bring up those who <hi rendition="#i">are</hi>
                    parties to such villanous traffic? Here are plain incriminations, and even
                    partial proofs of crimes said to have been committed; why do not the lawyers of
                    the Crown prosecute the alleged perpetrators of these crimes, as is their
                    duty?”</p>
                <p>“We do not get up a prosecution”, replied M. Hebert, “because the character of
                    the allegations and the character of those who bring them forward, is not such
                    as to make the truth of these allegations anything like probable to the legal advisers of
                    the Crown!”</p>
                <p>All this was every moment interrupted by groaning, shouting, knocking, and all
                    sorts of noises in general. This incomparable sitting, which has shaken the
                    Guizot Ministry to its very foundation, was concluded by a vote, which proves,
                    that if the faith of the majority may be shaken, their system of voting is not!
                    “The Chamber, after having heard the <choice>
                        <sic>explinations</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">explanations</corr>
                    </choice> of the Ministry, and found them <hi rendition="#k">satisfactory</hi>,
                    passes to the order of the day!”</p>
                <p>What do you think of that? Which do you prefer, the ministry or the majority, the
                    Deputies of France or your own Commons? M. Duchatel or Sir James Graham? I dare
                    say you will find the choice is a difficult one. There is, however, one
                    difference betwixt them. The English middle-classes have, up to this day, to
                    struggle against an aristocracy, which, although in a state of dissolution and
                    decomposition, is not yet removed. The aristocracy of England always found some
                    support in one fraction or the other of the middle-classes themselves, and it
                    was this division of the middle-classes that saved the aristocracy from total
                    ruin. At this moment the aristocracy is supported by the fundholders, bankers
                    and owners of fixed incomes, and by a large part of the shipping trade against
                    the manufacturers. The whole agitation for the repeal of the corn laws proves
                    this. The advanced fraction of the English <choice>
                        <sic>middle-classes, therefore, (I mean the manufacturers)</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">middle-classes (I mean the manufacturers),
                            therefore,</corr>
                    </choice> will yet be able to carry out some progressive political measures
                    which will more and more decompose the aristocracy. They will even be <hi rendition="#i">obliged</hi> to do so; they must extend their markets, which
                    they cannot do without reducing their prices, which reduction must be preceded
                    by a reduced cost of production, which reduced cost of production is mainly
                    obtained by reduced wages, for reducing which there is no safer means than
                    reduced price of the necessaries of life; and, to obtain this, they have no
                    other means but reducing the taxes. This is the logical chain which ties the
                    manufacturers of England to the necessity of destroying the Established Church,
                    and reducing, or “equitably adjusting”, the National Debt. Both these measures,
                    and others in the same spirit, they will be forced to carry out, as soon as they
                    find, which they must, the market of the world insufficient to continually and
                    regularly buy up their produce. Thus the English middle-classes are, as yet, in
                    a progressive direction; they have an aristocracy and a privileged clergy to
                    overthrow; there are certain progressive measures which they will be forced to
                    carry, and which they are the fit and proper persons to carry. But the French
                    middle-classes are in a different position. There is no aristocracy of birth,
                    nor a landed aristocracy, in that country. The revolution has swept it entirely
                    away. Neither is there a privileged or Established Church; but on the contrary,
                    both Catholic and Protestant clergy receive their salaries from the government,
                    and are upon a footing of perfect equality. There is no important struggle
                    possible in France between the fundholders, bankers, shippers, and
                    manufacturers, because, of all fractions of the middle-classes the fundholders
                    and bankers (who, at the same time, are the principal shareholders in the
                    railway, mining, and other companies) are decidedly the strongest fraction, and
                    have, with a few interruptions only, ever since 1830, held the reins of
                    government. The manufacturers, kept down by foreign competition in the foreign
                    market, and theatened in their own, have no chance of growing to such a degree
                    of power, that they successfully might struggle against the bankers and
                    fundholders. On the contrary, their chance decreases every year; their party in
                    the Deputies, formerly one-half, is now not more than a third part of the
                    Chamber. It results from all this that neither a single fraction, nor the whole
                    of the ruling middle-classes, are in a position to carry out anything like
                    “progress”; that the government of the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> is so
                    fully established in France since the revolution of 1830, that the ruling class
                    could do nothing but <hi rendition="#i">wear themselves out</hi>. This they have
                    done. Instead of progressing, they were obliged to go backwards, to restrain the
                    liberty of the press; to take away the right of free association and meeting; to
                    make all sorts of exceptional laws in order to keep down the working people. And
                    the scandalous affairs brought forward within the last few weeks are the evident
                    proof that the ruling <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> of France are entirely
                    worn out, totally “used up”.</p>
                <p>Indeed, the high <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> are in an awkward position.
                    They had found, at last, in Guizot and Duchatel, the men to govern them. They
                    kept them in office seven years, and sent them at every election larger and
                    larger majorities. And now, when all opposing fractions had been reduced to the
                    utmost incompetency in the Chamber, — now, when Guizot and Duchatel’s days
                    of glory seemed to have arrived, at that very moment a mass of scandal is
                    discovered in the doings of the ministry, that makes it impossible for them to
                    remain in office, even if supported unanimously by the Chambers. There can be
                    not doubt that Guizot and Duchatel will, with their colleagues, resign very
                    shortly; they may drag on their ministerial existence a few weeks longer, but
                    their end is drawing nigh — very nigh. And who is to govern after them?
                    God knows! They may say, as Louis XV., “after me the deluge, ruin, and
                    confusion”. Thiers is unable to bring together a majority. <choice>
                        <sic>Molè</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">Molé</corr>
                    </choice> is an old, worn-out, and insignificant man, who will meet with all
                    sorts of difficulties, and who, in order to secure the support of the majority,
                    must commit similar scandalous actions, and therefore end in the same way as
                    Guizot. This is the principal difficulty. The present electors will always elect
                    a majority like that now sitting; the present majority will always require a
                    ministry like that of Guizot and Duchatel, commiting all sorts of scandal; any
                    ministry doing so will be overthrown by the mere weight of public opinion. This
                    is the vicious circle in which the present system moves. But to go on as
                    hertofore is impossible. What, then, is to be done? There is no other course but
                    to leave this circle, to pass a measure of Electoral Reform; and Electoral
                    Reform means admission of the smaller tradesmen to the Suffrage, and this means,
                    in France, “the beginning of the end”. Rothschild and Louis Philippe know very
                    well, both of them, that admission of the smaller “bourgeoisie” to the Suffrage
                    means nothing but <hi rendition="#k">“la republique”</hi>!</p>
                <p>Paris, June 26th, 1847.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>