<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Movements of the Week</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-07</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Harney, George Julian, Friedrich Engels:] Movements of the Week. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 506, 3. Juli 1847. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Movements of the Week.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-07-03</date>
                        <date type="creation">1847-06-26</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">506</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2-3</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>George Julian Harney</persName>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-06-26" notAfter="1847-07-02">Ende Juni/Anfang Juli 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Movements of the Week.</hi></hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">The arrival from India this week has brought no later news from China —
                    indeed, no news at all from that region. As yet, therefore, we are uninformed of
                    any good and sufficient reasons for the violent attack by the British upon the
                    Chinese, reported in our last. The “Celestials” evidently entertain a wholesome
                    horror of the encroachments of the British, and with the fate of India before
                    their eyes this is not to be wondered at. Still more atrocious has been the
                    conduct of the French towards the Cochin-Chinese. That the arms of a nation so
                    notoriously indifferent to the Christian religion should have been employed to
                    support the insolent pretensions of a crew of meddling priests, is exceedingly
                    disgraceful to the French authorities. The French priests could not convert the
                    Cochin-Chinese, so, forsooth, had recourse to the old orthodox system of slaying
                    their bodies to save their souls! More than a thousand of the natives ruthlessly
                    butchered in the name of Christianity, is an unmistakeable exposition of the
                    religion of “peace on earth and goodwill to men”.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">The admirable summary of the recent extraordinary scenes and astounding
                    disclosures in the French legislature by our Parisian correspondent, together
                    with his able comments thereon, leave us nothing to say on a subject pregnant
                    with vast results for France and Europe; for important to the entire continent
                    will be the fall of Guizot, which cannot now be much longer postponed. His
                    overthrow will be the fall of the strongest prop of the Monarchy of the
                    Barricades, which will hence the sooner perish. A friend of ours, writing from
                    Paris, says: —</hi> “Guizot and Duchatel are, in future, <hi rendition="#i">impossible,</hi> as the French say, but after them no one is <hi rendition="#i">possible</hi>. There are days of great sorrow and tribulation
                    coming on for the rich in the land. ‘A cabinet, a cabinet, my kingdom for a
                    cabinet’, will be the cry of old Louis Philippe. A great many will be weighed,
                    and all will be found wanting. There is already wailing and gnashing of teeth in
                    the palace of the Tuilleries. ‘I’d rather be a kitten and cry <hi rendition="#i">mew</hi>’; than one of the French <hi rendition="#i">haute
                    bourgeoisie</hi>, and partake of the mess M. de Girardin has put them in. This
                    Girardin is the greatest rogue in Paris, but the cleverest one too. He is sold
                    to Russia, sold to the Anti-Corn Law League. Guizot has been ass enough to anger
                    this dangerous man, by neglecting to satisfy his cupidity, and now see the
                    result. A worse scoundrel than Girardin never escaped the gallows (whether he
                    will, time will tell), but in shaking the existing ‘system’ to its foundation,
                    he is doing France and mankind a service. I repeat, the days of Guizot’s
                    supremacy are numbered.” <hi rendition="#smaller">Mulhouse, the Manchester of France, has been the scene
                    of a violent outbreak, occasioned by the high prices of food. The people
                    generally in the departments are suffering intensely, and are greatly
                    exasperated against the government. They ask why Paris should be so especially
                    favoured as it has been, as regards the distribution of food and the forced
                    reduction of prices. “The reason is obvious”, say the people of the provinces,
                    “order and tranquillity must be preserved in Paris at any price.” This state of
                    things, and these expressions of popular discontent, combined with the
                    scandalous disclosures in high places, significantly attest the ticklish
                    position of Louis Philippe and his worthy comrogues, whose reign is evidently
                    drawing to a close.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>