<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Free Trade Congress at Brussels</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                    <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-10</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich, Karl Marx:] The Free Trade Congress at Brussels. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 520, 9. Oktober 1847. S. 8.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Free Trade Congress at Brussels.</title>
                        <author>
                            <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                        </author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-10-09</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">520</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">3-5</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <persName key="ed_ats_ysj_wx">Karl Marx</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-09-18" notAfter="1847-10-06">Ende September / Anfang Oktober 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Free Trade Congress at Brussels.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">(From our German Correspondent.)</hi></p>
                <p>On the 16th, 17th, and 18th of September, there was held here (Brussels) a
                    congress of political economists, manufacturers, tradesmen, &amp;c., to discuss
                    the question of Free Trade. There were present about 150 members of all nations.
                    There assisted, on the part of the English Free Traders, Dr Bowring, M.P., Col.
                    Thompson, M.P., Mr Ewart, M.P., Mr Brown, M.P., Jonas Wilson, Esq., editor of
                    the <hi rendition="#i">Economist</hi>, &amp;c; from France had arrived M.
                    Wolowski, professor of jurisprudence; M. Blanqui, deputy professor of political
                    economy, author of a history of that science, and other works; M. Horace Say,
                    son of the celebrated economist; M. Ch. Dunoyer, member of the Privy Council,
                    author of several works upon politics an economy, and others. From Germany there
                    was no Free Trader present, but Holland, Denmark, Italy, &amp;c., had sent
                    representatives. Senor Hamon de la Sagra, of Madrid, intended to come, but came
                    too late. The assistance of a whole host of Belgian Free Traders, need hardly be
                    mentioned, it being a matter of course.</p>
                <p>Thus the celebrities of the science had met to discuss the important question
                    — whether Free Trade would benefit the world? You will think the
                    discussions of such a splendid assembly — discussions carried on by
                    economical stars of the first magnitude must — have been interesting in
                    the highest degree. You will say that men like Dr Bowring, Colonel Thompson,
                    Blanqui and Dunoyer, must have pronounced speeches the most striking, must have
                    produced arguments the most convincing, must have represented all questions
                    under a light the most novel and surprising imaginable. Alas! sir, if you had
                    been present, you would have been piteously undeceived. Your glorious
                    expectations, your fond illusions would have vanished within less than an hour.
                    I have assisted at innumerable public meetings and discussions. I heard the
                    League pour forth their Anti-Corn-Law arguments more than a hundred times, while
                    I was in England, but never, I can assure you, never did I hear such dull,
                    tedious, trivial stuff, brought forward with such a degree of self-complacency.
                    I was never before so disappointed. What was carried on did not merit the name
                    of a discussion — it was mere pot-house talk. The great scientific
                    luminaries never ventured themselves upon the field of political economy, in the
                    strict sense of the word. I shall not repeat to you all the worn-out stuff which
                    was brought forward on the first two days. Read two or three numbers of the <hi rendition="#i">League</hi> or the <hi rendition="#i">Manchester
                        Guardian</hi>, and you will find all that was said, except, perhaps, a few
                    specious sentences brought forward by M. Wolowski, which he, however, had stolen
                    from M. Bastiat’s (chief of the French Free Traders) pamphlet of “Sophismes
                    Economiques”. Free Traders did not expect to meet with any other opposition but
                    that of M. Kissinghausen, a German Protectionist, and generally an insipid
                    fellow. But up got M. Duchateau, a French manufacturer and Protectionist —
                    a man who spoke for his purse, just as Mr Ewart or Mr Brown spoke for theirs,
                    and gave them such a terrible opposition, that on the second day of the
                    discussion, a great number, even of Free Traders, avowed that they hab been
                    beaten in argument. They took, however, their revenge at the vote — the
                    resolutions passed, of course, almost unanimously.</p>
                <p>On the third day, a question was discussed which interests your readers. It was
                    this: “Will the carrying out of universal Free Trade benefit the working
                    classes?” The affirmative was supported by Mr Brown, the South Lancashire Free
                    Trader, in a lengthy speech, in English; he and Mr Wilson were the only ones who
                    spoke that language, the remainder all spoke French — Dr Bowring, very
                    well — Colonel Thompson, tolerably — Mr Ewart, dreadfully. He
                    repeated a part of the old League documents, in a whining tone, very much like a
                    Church-of-England parson. After him got up</p>
                <p>Mr <hi rendition="#k">Weerth</hi>, of Rhenish Prussia. You know, I believe, this
                    gentleman — a young tradesman whose poetry is well known and very much
                    liked throughout Germany, and who, during several years’ stay in Yorkshire, was
                    an eye-witness of the condition of the working people. He has a great many
                    friends amongst them there, who will be glad to see that he has not forgotten
                    them. As his speech will be to your readers the most interesting feature of the
                    whole Congress, I shall report it at some length. He spoke als follows:
                    —</p>
                <p>“Gentlemen — You are discussing the influence of Free Trade upon the condition of
                    the working classes. You profess the greatest possible sympathy for those
                    classes. I am very glad of it, but yet I am astonished not to see a
                    representative of the working classes amongst you! The monied classes of France
                    are represented by a peer — those of England by several M.P.s — those of Belgium
                    by an ex-minister — and even those of Germany by a gentleman who gave us a
                    faithful description of the state of that country. But where, I ask you, are the
                    representatives of the working men? I see them nowhere; and therefore,
                    gentlemen, allow me to take up the defence of their interests. I beg to speak to
                    you on behalf of the working people, and principally on behalf of those five
                    millions of English working men, amongst whom I spent several of the most
                    pleasant years of my life, whom I know and whom I cherish. (Cheers.) Indeed,
                    gentlemen, the working people stand in need of some generosity. Hitherto they
                    have not been treated like men, but like beasts of burden, nay — like
                    merchandise, like machines; the English manufacturers know this so well, that
                    they never say, we employ so many workmen, but so many hands. The monied
                    classes, acting upon this principle, have never hesitated a moment to profit by
                    their services as long as they require them, and then turn them out upon the
                    streets, as soon as there is no longer any profit to be squeezed out of them.
                    Thus the condition of these outcasts of modern society has become such, that it
                    cannot be made worse. Look wherever you like; to the banks of the Rhone; into
                    the dirty and pestilential lanes of Manchester, Leeds, and Birmingham; on the
                    hills of Saxony and Silesia, or the plains of Westphalia; everywhere you will
                    meet with the same pale starvation, the same gloomy despair, in the eyes of men
                    who in vain claim their rights and their position in civilised society. (Great
                    sensation.) Mr Weerth then declared his opinion to be, that the protective
                    system in reality did not protect the working people, but that Free Trade — and
                    he told it them plainly and distinctly, although he himself was a Free Trader —
                    that Free Trade would never change their miserable condition. He did not at all
                    join in the delusions of the Free Traders, as to the beneficial effects of the
                    carrying out of their system upon the working classes. On the contrary, Free
                    Trade, the full realisation of free competition, would force the working people
                    as much into a keener competition amongst themselves as it would make
                    capitalists compete more selfishly against each other. The perfect freedom of
                    competition would inevitably give an enormous impulse to the invention of new
                    machinery, and thus supersede more workmen than even now were daily superseded.
                    It would stimulate production in every way, but for this very reason it would
                    stimulate over production, overstocking of markets, and commercial revulsions,
                    just in the same measure. The Free Traders pretended that those terrible
                    revulsions would cease under a system of commercial freedom; why, just the
                    contrary would be the case, they would increase and multiply more than ever.
                    Possible, nay certain it was, that at first the greater cheapness of provisions
                    would benefit the workpeople, — that a lessened cost of production would
                    increase consumption and the demand for labour, but that advantage very soon
                    would be turned into <choice>
                        <sic>misery</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">misery,</corr>
                    </choice> the competition of the working people amongst themselves would soon
                    reduce them to the former level of misery and starvation.” After these and other
                    arguments (which appeared to be quite novel to the meeting, for they were
                    listened to with the greatest attention, although the “Times” reporter deigns to
                    rid himself of them with the impudent but significant sneer — “Chartist
                    commonplace”), Mr <hi rendition="#k">Weerth</hi> concluded as follows: — “And do
                    not think, gentlemen, that these are but my individual opinions; they are the
                    opinions, too, of the English working men, a class, whom I cherish, and respect,
                    because they are intelligent and energetic men, indeed, (cheers, ‘by courtesy’),
                    I shall prove that by a few facts. During full six years the gentlemen of the
                    League, whom we see here, courted the support of the working people, but in
                    vain. The working men never forgot that the capitalists were their natural
                    enemies; they recollected the League riots of 1842, and the masters’ opposition
                    against the Ten Hours Bill. It was only towards the end of 1845, that the
                    Chartists, the <hi rendition="#i">elite</hi> of the working classes, associated
                    for a moment with the League, in order to crush their common enemy, the landed
                    aristocracy. But it was for a moment only, and never were they deceived by the
                    delusive promises of Cobden, Bright, and Co., nor did they hope the fulfilment
                    of cheap bread, high wages, and plenty to do. No, not for a moment did they
                    cease to trust in their own, exertions only; to form a distinct party, led on by
                    distinct chiefs, by the indefatigable Duncombe, and by Feargus O’Connor, who, in
                    spite of all calumnies, — (here Mr Weerth looked at Dr Bowring, who made a
                    quick, convulsive movement) — who, in spite of all calumnies, within a few weeks
                    will sit upon the same bench with you in the House of Commons. In the name,
                    then, of those millions who do not believe that Free Trade will do wonders for
                    them, I call upon you to seek for some other means to effectively better their
                    condition. Gentlemen, I call upon you for your own interests. You have no longer
                    to fear the Emperor of all the Russians; you dread not an invasion of Cossacks;
                    but if you do not take care you will have to fear the irruption of your own
                    workmen, and they will be more terrible to you than all the Cossacks in the
                    world. Gentlemen, the workpeople want no more words from you, they want deeds.
                    And you have no reason to be astonished at that. They recollect very well, that
                    in 1830 and 31, when they conquered the Reform Bill for you in London, when they
                    fought for you in the streets of Paris and Brussels, that then they were
                    courted, shaken hands with, and highly praised; but that when a few years after
                    they demanded bread, then they were received with grape shot and the bayonet.
                    (Oh! ‘no, no! yes, yes! Buzançais, Lyons’.) I repeat, therefore, to you, carry
                    your Free Trade, it will be well; but think, at the same time, about other
                    measures for the working-classes, or you will repent it.” (Loud cheers.)</p>
                <p>Immediately after Mr Weerth, up got Dr <hi rendition="#k">Bowring</hi> to reply.
                    “Gentlemen”, said he, “I can tell you that the hon. member who has just sat down
                    has not been elected by the English working people to represent them in this
                    Congress. On the contrary, the English people generally have given us their
                    suffrages for this purpose, and, therefore, we claim our places as their true
                    representatives.” He then went on to show the beneficial effects of Free Trade,
                    as proved by the increased importation of articles of food into England since
                    the introduction of last year’s tariff. So many eggs, so many cwt. of butter,
                    cheese, ham, bacon, so many heads of cattle, &amp;c., &amp;c.; who could have
                    eaten all that if not the working people of England? He quite forgot, however,
                    telling us what quantities of the same articles have been produced less in
                    England since foreign competition has been admitted. He took it for granted that
                    increased importation was a decisive proof of increased consumption. He never
                    mentioned wherefrom the working people of Manchester, Bradford, and Leeds, who
                    now walk the streets and cannot get work, wherefrom these men got the money to
                    pay for this supposed increase of consumption and Free Trade comforts, for we
                    never heard of the masters making them presents of eggs, butter, cheese, ham,
                    and meat, for not working at all. He never said a word about the present
                    depressed state of the trade, which in every public paper is represented as
                    really unexampled. He seemed not to know that all the predictions of the Free
                    Traders since the carrying of the measures have proved just the reverse of
                    reality. He had not a word of sympathy for the sufferings of the working
                    classes, but, on the contrary, represented their present gloomy condition as the
                    brightest, happiest, and most comfortable they  could reasonably desire.</p>
                <p>The English working people, now, may choose betwixt their two representatives. A
                    host of others followed, who spoke about every imaginable subject upon earth,
                    except the one under discussion. Mr M’Adam, M.P. for Belfast (?) spun an
                    eternally long yarn upon flax-spinning in Ireland, and almost killed the meeting
                    with statistics. Mr Akersdych, a Dutch professor, spoke about Old Holland and
                    Young Holland, the university of Liege, Walpols, and Dewit. M. Van de Casteele
                    spoke about France, Belgium, and the ministry. M. Asker, of Berlin, about German
                    patriotism and some new article he called spiritual manufacture. M. Den Tex, a
                    Dutchman, about God knows what. At last, the whole meeting being half asleep,
                    was awakened by M. Wolowski, who returned to the question and replied to Mr
                    Weerth. His speech, like all speeches delivered by Frenchmen, proved how much
                    the French capitalists dread the fulfilment of M. Weerth’s prophecies; they
                    speak with such pretended sympathy, such canting and whining of the sufferings
                    of the working classes, that one might take it all for good earnest, were it not
                    too flagrantly contradicted by the roundness of their bellies, by the stamp of
                    hypocrisy deeply imprinted on their faces, by the pitiful remedies they propose,
                    and by the unmistakeably striking contrast between their words and their deeds.
                    Nor have they ever succeeded in deceiving one single working man. Then, up got
                    the Duc d’Harcourt, peer of France, and claimed, too, for the French
                    capitalists, deputies, &amp;c., present the right of representing the French
                    working people. They do so in the same way as Dr Bowring <choice>
                        <sic>represent</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">represents</corr>
                    </choice> the English Chartists. Then, spoke Mr Jonas Wilson, repeating, most
                    brazen-facedly the most worn-out League-argument, in the drowsy tone of a
                    Philadelphia quaker.</p>
                <p>You see from this, what a nice discussion it was. Dr Marx, of Brussels, whom you
                    know as by far the most talented representative of German Democracy, had also
                    claimed his turn to speak. He had prepared a speech, which, if it had been
                    delivered, would have made it impossible for the congressional “gents” to vote
                    upon the question. But, Mr Weerth’s opposition had made them shy. They resolved
                    to <choice>
                        <sic>les</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">let</corr>
                    </choice> none speak, of whose orthodoxy they were not quite sure. Thus Messrs
                    Wolowski, Wilson, and the whole precious lot spoke against time, and when it was
                    four o’clock, there were still six or seven gentlemen who wanted to speak, but
                    the chairman closed the discussion abruptly, and the whole set of fools,
                    ignorants, and knaves, called a congress of political Economists, voted all
                    votes against one (that poor German fool of a Protectionist aforesaid) — the
                    Democrats did not vote at all — that Free-trade is extremely beneficial to the
                    working people, and will free them from all misery and distress.</p>
                <p>As Mr Marx’s speech, although not delivered, contains the very best and most
                    striking refutation of this barefaced lie, which can be imagined, and as its
                    contents, in spite of so many hundred pages having been written <hi rendition="#i">pro</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">con</hi> upon the subject,
                    will yet read quite novel in England, I enclose you some extracts from it.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Speech of Dr Marx on Protection, Free Trade, and the Working Classes.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>There are two sects of protectionists. The first sect, represented in Germany by
                    Dr List, who never intended to protect manual labour, on the contrary, they
                    demanded protective duties in order to crush manual labour by machinery, to
                    supersede patriarchal manufacture by modern manufacture. They always intended to
                    prepare the reign of the monied classes (the <choice>
                        <sic><hi rendition="#i">Bourgeoisie</hi>r</sic>
                        <corr cert="high"><hi rendition="#i">Bourgeoisie</hi></corr>
                    </choice>), and more particularly that of the large manufacturing capitalists.
                    They openly proclaimed the ruin of petty manufacturers, of small tradesmen, and
                    small farmers, as an event to be regretted, indeed, but, quite inevitable, at
                    the same time. The second school of protectionists, required not only
                    protection, but absolute prohibition. They proposed to protect manual labour
                    against the invasion of machinery, as well as against foreign competition. They
                    proposed to protect by high duties, not only home manufactures, but also home
                    agriculture, and the production of raw materials at home. And where did this
                    school arrive at? At the prohibition, not only of the importation of foreign
                    manufactured produce, but of the progress of the home manufacture itself. Thus
                    the whole protective system inevitably got upon the horns of this dilemma.
                    Either it protected the progress of home manufactures, and then it sacrificed
                    manual labour, or it protected manual labour, and then it sacrificed home
                    manufactures. Protectionists of the first sect, those who conceived the progress
                    of machinery, of division of labour, and of competition, to be irresistible,
                    told the working-classes, “At any rate if you are to be squeezed out, you had
                    better be squeezed by your own countrymen, than by foreigners.” Will the working
                    classes for ever bear with this? I think not. Those who produce all the wealth
                    and comforts of the rich, will not be satisfied with that poor consolation. They
                    will require more substantial comforts in exchange for substantial produce. But
                    the protectionists say, “After all, we keep up the state of society as it is at
                    present. We ensure to the working man, somehow or other, the employment he
                    wants. We take care that he shall not be turned out of work in consequence of
                    foreign competition.” So be it. Thus, in the best case, the protectionists avow
                    that they are unable to arrive at anything better than the continuation of the
                        <hi rendition="#i"><choice>
                            <sic>statu quo</sic>
                            <corr cert="high">status quo</corr>
                        </choice></hi>. Now the working classes want not the continuation of their
                    acutal condition, but a change for the better. A last refuge yet stands open to
                    the protectionist. He will say that he is not at all adverse to social reform in
                    the interior of a country, but that the first thing to ensure their success will
                    be to shut out any derangement which might be caused by foreign competition. “My
                    system”, he says, “is no system of social reform, but if we are to reform
                    society, had we not better do so within our own country, before we talk about
                    reforms in our relations with other <choice>
                        <sic>countries?</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">countries?”</corr>
                    </choice> Very specious, indeed, but under this plausible appearance, there is
                    hid a very strange contradiction. The protectionist system, while it gives arms
                    to the capital of a country against the capital of foreign countries, while it
                    strengthens capital against foreigners, believes that this capital, thus armed,
                    thus strengthened, will be weak, impotent, and feeble, when opposed to labour.
                    Why, that would be appealing to the mercy of capital, as if capital, considered
                    as such, could ever be merciful. Why, social reforms are never carried by the
                    weakness of the strong, but always by the strength of the weak. But it is not at
                    all necessary to insist on this point. From the moment the protectionists agree
                    that social reforms do not necessarily follow from, and that they are not part
                    and parcel of their system, but form quite a distinct question, from that moment
                    they abandon the question, which we discuss. We may, therefore, leave them in
                    order to review the effects of Free Trade upon the condition of the working
                    classes. The problem: What will be the influence of the perfect unfettering of
                    trade upon the situation of the working classes, is very easy to be resolved. It
                    is not even a problem. If there is anything clearly exposed in political
                    economy, it is the fate attending the working classes under the reign of Free
                    Trade. All those laws developed in the classical works on political economy, are
                    strictly true under the supposition only, that trade be delivered from all
                    fetters, that competition be perfectly free, not only within a single country,
                    but upon the whole face of the earth. These laws, which A. Smith, Say, and
                    Ricardo, have developed, the laws under which wealth is produced and distributed
                    — these laws grow more true, more exact, then cease to be mere
                    abstractions, in the same measure in which Free Trade is carried out. And the
                    master of the science, when treating of any economical subject, tells us every
                    moment that all their reasonings are founded upon the supposition that all
                    fetters, yet existing, are to be removed from trade. They are quite right in
                    following this method. For they make no arbitrary abstractions, they only remove
                    from their reasoning a series of accidental circumstances. Thus it can justly be
                    said, that the economists — Ricardo and others — know more about
                    society as it will be, than about society as it is. They know more about the
                    future than about the present. If you wish to read in the book of the future,
                    open Smith, Say, Ricardo. There you will find described, as clearly as possible,
                    the condition which awaits the working man under the reign of perfect Free
                    Trade. Take, for instance, the authority of Ricardo, authority than which there
                    is not better. What is the natural normal price of the labour of, economically
                    speaking, a working man? Ricardo replies, “Wages reduced to their minimum
                    — their lowest level”. Labour is a commodity as well as any other
                    commodity. Now the price of a commodity is determined by the time necessary to
                    produce it. What then is necessary to produce the commodity of labour? Exactly
                    that which is necessary to produce the sum of commodities indespensable to the
                    sustenance and the repairing of the wear and tear of the labourer, to enable him
                    to live and to propagate, somehow or other, his race. We are, however, not to
                    believe that the working man will never be elevated above this lowest level, nor
                    that he never will be depressed below it. No, according to this law, the working
                    classes will be for a time more happy, they will have for a time more than the
                    minimum, but this surplus will be the supplement only for what they will have
                    less than the minimum at another time, the time of industrious stagnation. That
                    is to say, that during a certain space of time, which is always periodical, in
                    which trade passes through the circle of <choice>
                        <sic>prosperity</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">prosperity,</corr>
                    </choice> over production, stagnation, crisis — that, taking the average
                    of what the labourer received more, and what he received less, than the minimum,
                    we shall find that on the whole he will have received neither more or less than
                    the minimum; or, in other words, that the working class, as a class, will have
                    conserved itself, after many miseries, many sufferings, and many corpses left
                    upon the industrial battle field. But what matters that? The class exists, and
                    not only it exists, but it will have increased. This law, that the lowest level
                    of wages is the natural price of the commodity of labour, will realise itself in
                    the same measure with Ricardo’s supposition that Free Trade will become a
                    reality. We accept every thing that has been said of the advantages of Free
                    Trade. The powers of production will increase, the tax imposed upon the country
                    by protective duties will disappear, all commodities will be sold at a cheaper
                    price. And what, again, says Ricardo? “That labour being equally a commodity,
                    will equally sell at a cheaper price” — that you will have it for very
                    little money indeed, just as you will have pepper and salt. And then, in the
                    same way as all other laws of political economy, will receive an increased
                    force, a suplus of truth, by the realisation of Free Trade — in the same
                    way the law of population, as exposed by Malthus, will, under the reign of Free
                    Trade, develop itself in as fine dimensions as can possibly be desired. Thus you
                    have to choose: Either you must disavow the whole of political economy as it
                    exists at present, or you must allow that under the freedom of trade the whole
                    severity of the laws of political economy will be applied to the working
                    classes. Is that to say that we are against Free Trade? No, we are for Free
                    Trade, because by Free Trade all economical laws, with their most astounding
                    contradictions, will act upon a larger scale, upon a greater extent of
                    territory, upon the territory of the whole earth; and because from the uniting
                    of all these contradictions into a single group, where they stand face to face,
                    will result the struggle which will itself eventuate in the emancipation of the
                    proletarians.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>