<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Feargus O’Connor and the Press-Gang</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-13</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] Feargus O’Connor and the Press-Gang. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 524, 6. November 1847. S. 5.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Feargus O’Connor and the Press-Gang.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-11-06</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">524</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">6</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-10-30" notAfter="1847-10-31">30./31. Oktober 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Feargus O’Connor and the Press-Gang.</hi></hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller">The following article, translated from the <hi rendition="#i">Reforme</hi>, the
                    most able of the French journals, and a consistent supporter of the rights of
                    labour in all countries, will cheer the working classes of England with the
                    proud consolation, that henceforth the battle of universal liberty is not to be
                    confined within the limits of our sea-bound dungeon. The <hi rendition="#i">Reforme</hi> says: —</hi></p>
                <p><choice>
                        <sic>About</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">“About</corr>
                    </choice> two years since the Chartist working men of England founded an
                    association for the purpose of purchasing land and dividing it in small
                    allotments among the members. It is hoped by these means to reduce the pressure
                    of competition in the manufacturing labour market, and by drafting a number of
                    working men on to the Land to establish on democratic principles a new class of
                    small proprietors. This undertaking, founded by Mr Feargus O’Connor, has already
                    achieved such success, that it consists of a vast number of members, and has at
                    its command a sum of £ 60.000, while its subscription list, as published in the
                        <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi>, exceeds £ 2.500 per week. In fact,
                    this Society, of which I purpose ere long to give you a more detailed account, has assumed so powerful
                    an attitude, that it begins to disquiet the landed aristocracy; since it is
                    evident that, if it progresses as it has commenced, it will end by becoming a
                    national movement for the re-possession of the land by the people. This plan
                    finds no better favour at the hands of the middle classes, since they behold in
                    it an agent of popular power, capable of redeeming the working classes from
                    their tyranny. The members of the trading class, indeed, whether calling
                    themselves more or less liberal, are particularly opposed to the Land Company,
                    as they find, the Chartists, since its formation, already more independent of
                    their patronage. These so-called radicals, therefore, astonished at the cold way
                    in which the people receive their lukewarm liberalism, incessantly attack Mr
                    O’Connor as the only obstacle in their way towards attaching the working classes
                    to their views. It was sufficient that the Land Plan was originated by Mr
                    O’Connor for it to receive the unmitigated hostility of the middle classes. At
                    first they affected to ignore it; then, when the <hi rendition="#i">conspiracy
                        of silence</hi> was no longer of use, they attacked the plan, endeavouring
                    to show that it was founded on erroneous premises, and must end in a signal
                    failure. And, last of all, when the society kept prospering in despite of them,
                    they returned to the tactics they had followed for the last ten years, but
                    always without the least success, — they assailed Mr O’Connor himself,
                    tried to throw suspicion on his character, and to undermine his reputation as
                    the incorruptible and unpaid Bailiff of the Working Classes. In pursuance of
                    this object, five or six papers, that had evidently preconcerted their plan,
                    seized on the occasion of Mr O’Connor’s publishing the balance sheet of the Land
                    Company, to open their attack. <hi rendition="#i">The Weekly Dispatch</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">The Globe</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">The Nonconformist</hi>,
                        <hi rendition="#i">The Manchester Examiner</hi>, <hi rendition="#i">Lloyd’s
                        Weekly Newspaper</hi>, and <hi rendition="#i">The Nottingham Mercury</hi>,
                    accused Mr O’Connor of the most barefaced robbery, and tried to give a colouring
                    of proof to their accusations, by quoting and disturbing the very figures of the
                    balance sheet. Not satisfied even with this, they dived into the private life of
                    this celebrated Agitator, and hurled at him a mountain of accusations, in the
                    expectation that he would be crushed by their serious nature and accumulated
                    weight. But O’Connor, who, for the last ten years, has never ceased contending
                    with the sham-radical press, instead of bending before the storm, published in
                    the <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi> of the 23rd of October, a reply to the
                    six editors, which, as a masterpiece of polemical writing, recals to our minds
                    the happiest efforts of <hi rendition="#i">William Cobbett</hi>; refutes each
                    accusation <hi rendition="#i">seriatim</hi>, and, in its turn assuming the
                    offensive, retorts by a crushing and truly dignified rejoinder. This vile
                    attack, and this convincing answer, have, if possible, but increased the
                    people’s confidence in Mr O’Connor. The <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi> of
                    the 30th of October, contains unanimous votes to that effect, passed at public
                    meetings held by Chartists of more than fifty localities. But O’Connor still
                    desired to give his opponents an opportunity to attack him before the public. He
                    therefore challenged them to prove their charges against him in a public meeting
                    at Manchester and Nottingham. Not one of them ventured to appear. At Manchester
                    Mr O’Connor addressed more than ten thousand men in a speech of four hours,
                    hailed throughout with thunders of applause, and receiving, amidst rapturous
                    acclamations, an unanimous vote of confidence from the meeting. So great was the
                    crowd, that besides those within, another meeting of from ten to fifteen
                    thousand men was held simultaneously without the walls, and addressed by several
                    speakers.</p>
                <p>When his address was concluded, Mr O’Connor announced that he was ready to
                    receive the payments of the members of the Land Company, and received, on the
                    platform, a sum exceeding £ 1.000.</p>
                <p>On the following evening, Mr O’Connor held, at Nottingham, one of the largest
                    meetings ever known in that town, amid equal demonstrations of enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>This is at least the hundredth time Mr O’Connor has similarly and signally
                    triumphed over the calumnies of the middle-class press. Unmoved by his
                    assailants, this indefatigable patriot pursues the even tenor of his way, and
                    the unanimous confidence of the English people is the best proof of his courage,
                    his energy, and his integrity.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>