<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Manifesto of M. de Lamartine</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-13</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The Manifesto of M. de Lamartine. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 525, 13. November 1847. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Manifesto of M. de Lamartine.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-11-13</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">525</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-11-01" notAfter="1847-11-11">Anfang November 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Manifesto of M. de Lamartine.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></hi></p>
                <p>You recently published this curious piece of workmanship. It consists of two very
                    distinct parts: <hi rendition="#i">political</hi> measures and <hi rendition="#i">social</hi> measures. Now the <hi rendition="#i">political</hi> measures are, one and all, taken from the constitution of
                    1791, with almost no alteration; that is, they are the return to the demands of
                    the middle classes in the beginning of the revolution. At that time the whole of
                    the middle classes, including even the smaller tradesmen, were invested with
                    political power, while at present the participation in it is restrained to the
                    large capitalists. What, then, is the meaning of the political measures proposed
                    by M. de Lamartine? To give the government into the hands of the inferior <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, but under the semblance of giving it to the
                    whole people (this, and nothing else, is the meaning of his universal suffrage,
                    with his double system of elections). And his <hi rendition="#i">social</hi>
                    measures? Why they are either things which presuppose that a successful
                    revolution has already given the political power to the people — such as
                    gratuitous education for all; or measures of pure charity, that ist measures to
                    soften down the revolutionary energies of the proletarians, or mere
                    high-sounding words without any practical meaning, such as extinction of
                    mendicity by order in council, abolition of public distress by law, a ministry
                    of the people’s life, &amp;c. They are, therefore, either totally useless to the
                    people, or calculated to benefit them in such a degree only as will assure some
                    sort of public tranquillity, or they are mere empty promises, which no man can
                    keep — and in these two last cases they are worse than useless. In short,
                    M. de Lamartine proves himself, both under a social and a political point of
                    view, the faithful representative of the small tradesman, the inferior <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, and who shares in the illusion particular
                    to this class: that he represents the working people. And, in the end he is
                    foolish enough to address himself to the government with the demand of their
                    support for his measures. Why, the present government of the great capitalists
                    will do anything but that. The <hi rendition="#i">Réforme</hi>, therefore, is
                    perfectly right in attacking, though with a deal of good will, and recognising
                    his good intentions, the practicability both of his measures, and his mode of
                    setting about having them carried.</p>
                <p>“Certainly”, says the <hi rendition="#i">Réforme</hi>, “these are high words,
                    revealing a mighty heart, a spirit sympathising with the cause of right.” The
                    fraternal feeling is panting visibly under the cloak of words, and our poets and
                    philosophers will be excited by them into enthusiasm similar to that produced
                    upon Periclean Greece by the sentence of Plato. But we have not now anything to
                    do with Pericles, we live under the reign of Messrs Rothschild, Fulchiron and
                    Duchâtel, that is under the triple incarnation of Money, blockheaded Fear, and
                    Police; we have for a government, profits, privilege, and the municipal guard.
                    Now, hopes M. de Lamartine that the league of consolidated interests, that the
                    Sonderbund of dollars, place and monopoly, will surrender and lay down arms at
                    his appeal to national sovereignty and social fraternity? Why, for good as for
                    evil, all things in this world are connected — one keeps up the other,
                    nothing is isolated — and that is the reason why the most generous
                    programme of the deputy for Mâçon will pass like perfumed zephyrs of summer,
                    will die like empty trumpet sounds, as long as they shall bear the mother-stain
                    of all monopoly — feudal violation of Right and of Equality. And this
                    league of the privileged classes is particularly closely united at this very
                    moment, when the governmental system is the prey of convulsive fear.</p>
                <p>As to the institutions he proposes, the official country and its leaders call
                    such things the sweet-meats of philosophy: Messrs Duchâtel and Guizot will laugh
                    at them, and if the deputy of Mâçon does not look out elsewhere for arms and
                    soldiers to defend his ideas, he will pass all his life at making fine words and
                    no progress! And if he addresses himself to the million instead of the
                    government, we tell him that he follows a false route, and never will win over
                    to his system of graduated election, poor rate, and philanthropic charity,
                    neither the Revolution, nor thinking men, nor the people. The principles,
                    indeed, of social and political regeneration have been found fifty years ago.
                    Universal suffrage, direct election, paid representation — these are the
                    essential conditions of political sovereignty. Equality, liberty, fraternity
                    — these are the principles which ought to rule all social institutions.
                    Now, the poor rate is far from being based upon fraternity, whilst at the same
                    time it is an insolent and very impotent denial of equality. What we want, is
                    not English middle-class expediency, but quite a new system of social economy,
                    to realise the right and satisfy the wants of all.</p>
                <p>A few days after appeared the second manifesto of M. de Lamartine upon the
                    foreign policy of France. In this he maintains that the peace system followed by
                    the French government after 1830 was the only convenient mode of action. He
                    covers by pompous sentences the infamous manner in which the French government
                    first excited Italy and other countries to rebellion, and afterwards abandoned
                    them to their fate. Here is the forcible reply of the <hi rendition="#i">Réforme</hi> to this buttermilk manifesto: — “M. de Lamartine
                    sacrifices the legitimate and only instrument of freeing us — the holy war
                    of principle — to a theory of peace which will be a mere weakness, a lie,
                    and even an act of treason, as long as the relations from people to people are
                    based upon the policy of diplomatists, and the egotism of governments. No doubt,
                    peace is the ultimate necessity of civilisation; but what is peace with Nicholas
                    of Russia? the disemboweller of whole nations, the hangman who nails infants to
                    the gallows, who carries on a deadly war against even hope and recollection, who
                    drowns in her tears and her blood a great, a glorious country! For mankind, for
                    civilisation, for France herself, peace with this mad-man of a Jack Ketch is
                    cowardice; for justice, for right, for the revolution, it is a crime! What is
                    peace with Metternich, who hires hosts of assassins, who confiscates for the
                    benefit of crowned epilepsy, the liberties — nations? What is peace with
                    all those little Cæsars of Europe, ruined debauchees, or villanous bigots who
                    reign, to-day for the Jesuits, to-morrow for the courtezan? What is peace with
                    the aristocratic and money-mongering English government, which tyrannises the
                    seas, which kills liberty in Portugal, which squeezes money even out of the rags
                    of its people? Peace with these Jews, these poison-mongers, we repeat it, is,
                    for a country in revolution, cowardice, shame, crime, moral desertion,
                    bankruptcy not only of interest but of right and honour.” The other Paris papers
                    have equally expressed their dissent from M. de Lamartine’s programme in
                    different respects. He continues, however, illustrating its principles in his
                    paper, the <hi rendition="#i">Bien Public</hi> of Mâçon. We shall in a few
                    months, be enabled to judge what effect his <hi rendition="#i">new move</hi> will make upon the Chamber of Deputies.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>