<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Reform Movement in France</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-13</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The Reform Movement in France. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 526, 20. November 1847. S. 6.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Reform Movement in France.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-11-20</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">526</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">3-4</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-11-01" notAfter="1847-11-18">Anfang / Mitte November 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Reform Movement in France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#smaller"><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></hi></p>
                <p>When, during the last session of the Legislative Chambers, M. E. de Girardin had
                    brought to light those numerous and scandalous facts of corruption which he
                    thought would overthrow the government; when, after all, the government had
                    maintained themselves against the storm; when the celebrated Two Hundred and
                    Twenty-five declared themselves “satisfied” as to the innocence of the ministry,
                    all seemed to be over, and the Parliamentary Opposition, towards the close of
                    the session, fell back into the same impotency and lethargy which they had
                    manifested at the beginning. But all was not over. Though Messrs Rothschild,
                    Fould, Fulchiron, and Co. were satisfied, the people were not, nor was a large
                    portion of the middle classes. The majority of the French <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, especially those of the second and third rank, could not
                    but see that the present class of electors became more and more the obedient
                    servants of a small number of bankers, stock-jobbers, railway-speculators, large
                    manufacturers, landed and mining proprietors, whose interest was the only
                    interest cared for by the government. They saw that there was no hope for them
                    ever to regain the position in the Chambers which, since 1830, they had been
                    losing more and more every day, unless they extended the suffrage. They knew
                    that electoral and parliamentary Reform, was a dangerous experiment for them to
                    try; but what could they do? Seeing that the <hi rendition="#i">haute
                        finance</hi>, the lords of the Paris Exchange, bought up the government and
                    both the Chambers; seeing their own interests openly trampled upon; they were
                    obliged either to submit patiently, and await humbly and quietly the day when
                    the encroachments of the ruling money lords would make them bankrupts, or to
                    risk parliamentary Reform. They preferred the latter.</p>
                <p>The Opposition, of all shades, therefore, united, some four months ago, in
                    getting up a demonstration in favour of Electoral Reform. A public dinner was
                    arranged and took place in July, at the Chateau-Rouge ball-rooms, at Paris. All
                    fractions of Reformers were represented, and the assembly was rather mixed; but
                    the Democrats, having been the most active, evidently predominated. They had
                    made it a condition of their assistance, that the king’s health should not be
                    drank, but be replaced by a toast in favour of the sovereignty of the people;
                    the committee knowing well that in the most democratic town of France they could
                    not get up a decent demonstration without the Democrats, were obliged to comply.
                    If I recollect rightly, you gave, at the time, a full account of the banquet,
                    which was in every respect more like a demonstration of the strength, both in
                    number and intellect, of democracy at Paris, than anything else.</p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">Journal des Debats</hi> failed not to raise a terrible
                    outcry about this banquet. “What! no toast to the king? and this toast not
                    omitted by negligence, by want of a sense of propriety — no, this omission
                    put as a condition for their support by part of the getters-up! Why, what pretty
                    company this calm and peaceful M. Duvergier de Houranne — this
                    moral-force, monarchical M. Odillon Barrot have got into! Why this is not mere
                    republicanism — this is revolutionism, physical-forcism, socialism,
                    utopianism, anarchism and communism! Ah, but, gentlemen, we know you — we
                    have had samples of your bloody deeds, we have proofs of what you are contending
                    for! Fifty years ago, gentlemen, you called yourselves the <hi rendition="#i">club of the Jacobins</hi>!”</p>
                <p>Next day’s <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> replied to the fierce and furious
                    vituperation of the <hi rendition="#i">furiously moderate</hi> paper by a host
                    of quotations from Louis Philippe’s private journal, written in 1791 and 1792,
                    where every day’s note of the then “Citizen Egalité junior” commenced with the
                    words: “To-day I was at the Jacobins” — “To-day I took the liberty of
                    saying a few words at the Jacobins which were warmly applauded” — “To-day
                    I was called to the office of door-keeper at the Jacobins”, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The central committee of the Opposition had invited their friends in the country
                    to imitate the example given by the metropolis, in getting up every where
                    similar banquets in favour of Reform. This was done accordingly, and a great
                    number of Reform dinners were held in almost all parts of France. But not
                    everywhere the same union of all fractions of Reformers could be made to
                    prevail. In a great number of the smaller towns the middle class Liberals were
                    strong enough to carry the king’s health being drank, by which the Democrats
                    were excluded. In other localities they tried to make it pass in the shape of a
                    toast: — “The constitutional king, and the sovereignty of the people.” This
                    being not yet sufficient to the Democrats, they went on shuffling, and replaced
                    the “constitutional king” by the “constitutional institutions”, among which
                    royalty, of course, was tacitly comprised. The great question now agitated among
                    the provincial Liberals is, whether they are to give up even this, and to resign
                    all attempts at carrying the king’s health in whatever shape or disguise it be,
                    or whether they are to separate openly from the Democrats, who, in that case,
                    would get up separate and competing banquets. For the democratic party insist
                    upon the original agreement, that the king be not mixed up at all with the
                    affair, and if in one case the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> has been
                    wavering a little, the party of the <hi rendition="#i">Réforme</hi> stand firmly
                    on the side of republicanism. In all the large towns the Liberals have been
                    forced to give way, and if in the localities of lesser importance they have
                    carried the king’s health, it is because such banquets cost a great deal of
                    money, and, therefore, the people are naturally excluded from them. On the
                    occasion of the banquet of Bar-le-Duc, the <hi rendition="#i"><choice>
                            <sic>Reforme</sic>
                            <corr>Réforme</corr>
                        </choice></hi> says: “Whoever would take such demonstration as a sample of
                    the state of public opinion in France, would be very much mistaken indeed: they
                    are got up by the middle classes only, and the people are entirely shut out from
                    them. This agitation, if it be confined to the limits of the Bar-le-Duc banquet,
                    will vanish like all <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> movements; like the Free
                    Trade movement, which after a few hollow speeches died away very soon.”</p>
                <p>The first large banquet, after that of Paris, was held at Strasburg, in the
                    beginning of September. It was rather a democratic one, and a working man, at
                    the close of it, proposed a toast to the organistation of labour, which term, in
                    France, expresses that which in England the National Association of United
                    Trades are trying to carry out; viz. the freeing of labour from the oppression
                    of capital by carrying on manufacturing, agricultural, and other purposes, for
                    the account, either of the associated working men themselves, or of the people
                    at large, under a democratic government.</p>
                <p>Then came the banquets of Bar-le-Duc, a <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi>
                    demonstration, finished by the Mayor proposing the health of the Constitutional
                    King (very constitutional, indeed); of Colmar, Rheims, and Meaux, all of them
                    entirely dominated by the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, who, in those
                    secondary towns, always have it all their own way.</p>
                <p>But the banquet of Saint Quentin, again, was more or less democratic; and that of
                    Orleans, in the last days of September, was, from beginning to end, a thoroughly
                    democratic meeting. Judge of it by the toast to the working classes, responded
                    to by M. Marie, one of the most celebrated barristers of Paris, and a democrat.
                    He commenced his speech in the following terms: — “To the working men
                    — to those men, always neglected and forgotten, but always faithful to the
                    interests of their country, always ready to die for its cause, be it in
                    defending their native land against foreign aggression, be it in guarding our
                    institutions, when menaced by inward foes! To those, from whom we demanded the
                    days of July, and who gave them to us; terrible in their action, generous in
                    their triumph, resplendent with courage, probity, and disinterestedness!” and
                    concluded the toast in these words: “Liberty, equality, fraternity!” It is
                    characteristic that the Orleans banquet was the only one at which we find it
                    stated that covers were reserved for the representatives of the working
                    people.</p>
                <p>The banquet of Culommiers, Melun, and Cosne, again, were mere <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> gatherings. The <hi rendition="#i">“Left Centre”</hi>, the
                    middle-class Liberals of the <hi rendition="#i">Constitutionnel</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">Siécle</hi>, amused themselves in listening to the speeches
                    of <choice>
                        <sic>M. M.</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">MM.</corr>
                    </choice> Barrot, Beaumont, Drouin de L’huys, and such like retailers of reform.
                    At Cosne, the democrats openly declared against the demonstration, because the
                    king’s health was insisted upon. The same narrow spirit prevailed at the banquet
                    of La Charité, on the Loire.</p>
                <p>In return, the Reform dinner of Chartres, was thoroughly democratic. No toast for
                    the king — toasts for Electoral and Parliamentary Reform upon the largest
                    base, for Poland and Italy, for the organisation of labour.</p>
                <p>This week banquets will take place at Lille, Valenciennes, Avesnes, and
                    throughout the Department of the North generally. Those of Lille and
                    Valenciennes, at least, will probably take a decidedly democratic turn. In the
                    South of France, at Lyons, and in the West, other demonstrations are preparing.
                    The Reform Movement is far from being near to its close.</p>
                <p>You see from this account that, from its very beginning, the Reform Movement of
                    1847 has been marked by a struggle betwixt the Liberals and the Democrats; that
                    while the Liberals carried their ends in all the smaller localities, the
                    Democrats were the stronger in all large towns; in Paris, Strasburg, Orleans,
                    Chartres, and even in one smaller town, in Saint-Quentin; that the Liberals were
                    very anxious of having the support of the Democrats; that they shuffled and made
                    concessions, while the Democrats never retracted an iota of the condition under
                    which they were ready to give their support, and that wherever the Democrats
                    assisted, they had it all their own way. Thus, after all, the whole movement has
                    been turned to the profit of democracy, for all those banquets which excited
                    public attention in some degree, were, one and all, democratic.</p>
                <p>The Reform Movement was seconded by the Departmental Councils, who met in
                    September, and who are entirely composed by <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi>.
                    The Councils of the Departments of the Côte-d’Or, of Finisterre, of the Aisne,
                    the Moselle, the <choice>
                        <sic>Hautr Rhin</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">Haut-Rhin</corr>
                    </choice>, the Oise, the Vosges, the North, and others, demanded, more or less,
                    extensive reforms, all of them, of course, confined to the limits of <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> Liberalism.</p>
                <p>But what, will you ask, are the reforms demanded? There are as many different
                    systems of reform, as there are shades of Liberals and Radicals. The least thing
                    asked for, is the extention of the Suffrage, to what is called the <hi rendition="#i">capacities</hi>, or what you, in England, would call the
                    learned professions, even, if they do not pay the 200 francs of direct taxes,
                    which make, at present, a man a voter. Then the Liberals have some other
                    propositions, more or less in common with the Radicals. These are: —</p>
                <p>1st. The extension of the <hi rendition="#i">incompatibilities</hi>, or the
                    declaring of certain government offices to be incompatible with the functions of
                    a representative. The government have, at present, more than 150 of their
                    subordinate employers in the Deputies, all of which may, at any moment, be
                    cashiered, and are, therefore, entirely dependent upon the Ministry.</p>
                <p>2nd. The enlargement of some electoral districts, some of which are composed of
                    less than 130 voters, who are, therefore, entirely ruled through the influence
                    of the government upon their local and personal interests.</p>
                <p>3rd. The electing of all deputies of a Department in a full meeting of all the
                    electors, assembled at its principal town, by which means local interests are
                    intended to be more or less submerged in the common interests of the whole
                    Department, and thus render nugatory the corruption and influence of the
                    government.</p>
                <p>Then, there are proposals for lowering the amount of the voting qualification in
                    different degrees. The most Radical of these propositions is that of the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi>; the paper of the Republican small tradesmen,
                    for extending the suffrage to all men belonging to the National Guard. This
                    would give the vote to the entire class of small tradesmen and shopkeepers, and
                    extend the suffrage in the same degree as the Reform Bill has done in England;
                    but the consequences of such a measure would, in France, be much more important.
                    The small <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> in this country, are so much
                    oppressed and squeezed by the large capitalists, that they would be obliged to
                    have recourse to direct aggressive measures against the moneylords, as soon as
                    they get the suffrage. As I said in an article I sent you some months ago, they
                    would be carried further and further, even against their own consent; they would
                    be forced either to give up the positions already won, or to form an open
                    alliance with the working classes, and that would, sooner or later, lead to the
                    Republic. They know this in some measure. Most of them support Universal
                    Suffrage, and so does the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi>, which goes for the
                    above measure only, as far as it is considered as a premliminary step in the
                    road of reform. Of all Parisian daily papers, there is, however, but one which
                    will not be satisfied with anything less than Universal Suffrage, and which, by
                    the term “Republic”, understands not merely Political Reforms, which will, after
                    all, leave the working classes as miserable as before — but Social
                    Reforms, and very definite ones too. This paper is the <hi rendition="#i"><choice>
                            <sic>Reforme</sic>
                            <corr cert="high">Réforme</corr>
                        </choice></hi>.</p>
                <p>The Reform movement is, however, not to be considered as the totality of the
                    agitation now going on in France. Far from it! At all these banquets, be they
                    Liberal or Democratic, the middle classes were predominating; that of Orleans
                    was the only one in which working men took part. The movement of the working
                    people is going on, side by side, with these banquets, silently, underground,
                    almost invisible, for every one who does not take the trouble of looking after
                    it. But it is going on more lively than ever. The government know this very
                    well. They have given their permission to all these middle class banquets; but
                    when the typographic working men of Paris, in September, asked for the
                    permission to hold their annual banquet, which, up to the present time, they had
                    held every year, and which was in no manner of a political character, it was
                    refused to them. The government are so afraid of the working people, that they
                    do not allow them the slightest liberty. They are afraid, because the people
                    have entirely given up all attempts at insurrection and rioting. The government
                    desire a riot, they provoke it by every means. The police throw out small
                    bomb-shells filled with incendiary papers; which, by the explosion of the shell,
                    are spread all over the streets. A trades’ affair in the Rue St Honoré, was
                    profited by, to make the most brutal attacks upon the people, in order to
                    provoke them to riot and violence. Tens of thousands assembled every evening
                    during a fortnight; they were treated in the most infamous manner; they were on
                    the very brink of repelling force by force; but they held out and no pretext for
                    more gagging laws are to be forced from them. And think, what a tacit
                    understanding, what a common feeling of what was to be done, at the moment, must
                    have prevailed; what an effort it must have cost to the people of Paris, to
                    submit to such infamous treatment rather than try <choice>
                        <sic>a a</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">a</corr>
                    </choice> hopeless insurrection. What an enormous progress this forbearance
                    proves in those very same working men of Paris, who seldom went into the streets
                    without battering to pieces every thing before them; who are accustomed to
                    insurrection, and who go into a revolution just as gaily as they go to the
                    wineshop! But if you would draw from this the conclusion that the revolutionary
                    ardour of the people is decreasing, you would be quite mistaken. On the
                    contrary, the necessity of a revolution, and a revolution more thorough-going,
                    more radical by far than the first one, is deeper than ever felt by the working
                    people here. But they know from the experience of 1830, that mere fighting will
                    not do; that the enemy once beaten, they must establish measures that will
                    guarantee the stability of their conquest; that will destroy not only the
                    political, but the social power of capital, that will guarantee their social
                    welfare, along with their political strength. And, therefore, they very quietly
                    await their opportunity, but, in the meantime, earnestly apply themselves to the
                    study of those questions of social economy, the solution of which will show what
                    measures alone can establish, upon a firm basis, the welfare of all. Within a
                    month or two, six thousand copies of M. Louis Blanc’s work on “The Organisation
                    of Labour”, have been sold in the workshops of Paris, and you must consider,
                    that five editions of this book had been published before. They read likewise a
                    number of other works upon these questions; they meet in small numbers of from
                    ten to twenty, and discuss the different plans propounded therein. They talk not
                    much of revolution, this being a thing admitting of no doubt, a subject upon
                    which they one and all agree; and when the moment will have arrived, at which a
                    collision between the people and the government will be inevitable, down they
                    will be in the streets and squares at a moment’s notice, tearing up the
                    pavement, laying omnibuses, carts, and coaches across the streets, barricading
                    every alley, making every narrow lane a fortress, and advancing, in spite of all
                    resistance, from the Bastile to the Tuileries. And then, I fear, most of the
                    reform banquet gentry will hide themselves in the darkest corner of their
                    houses, or be scattered like dead leaves before the popular thunderstorm. Then
                    it will be all over with Messrs Odillon Barrot, de Beaumont and other Liberal
                    thunderers, and then the people will judge them quite as severely as they now
                    judge the Conservative governments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>