<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Reform Movement in France</title>
                <title type="sub">Split in the Camp — The “Reforme” and the “National”
                    — March of Democracy</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-17</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] The Reform Movement in France. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 528, 4. Dezember 1847. S. 3.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Reform Movement in France.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Split in the Camp. — The “Reforme” and the “National”. — March of Democracy.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-12-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">528</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">6</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris?</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London?</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-11-21" notAfter="1847-11-30">Ende November 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Reform Movement in France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Split in the Camp. — The “Reforme”
                            and the “National”. — March of Democracy.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>Since my last the banquets of Lille, Avesnes, and Valenciennes, have been held.
                    Avesnes was merely constitutional; Valenciennes half-and-half; Lille a decided
                    triumph of democracy over middle-class intrigue. Here are, shortly, the facts
                    concerning this most important meeting: —</p>
                <p>Besides the liberals and the party of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, the
                    democrats of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> had been invited, and Messrs
                    Ledru-Rollin and Flocon, editor of the last-named paper, hat accepted the
                    invitation. M. Odillon Barrot, the virtuous middle-class thunderer was also
                    invited. Everything was ready, the toasts were prepared, when all of a sudden M.
                    Odillon Barrot declared he could not assist, nor speak to his toast,
                    “Parliamentary Reform”, unless that reform was qualified by adding: — “as
                    a means to insure the purity and sincerity of the institutions conquered in
                    July, 1830”. This addition excluded, of course, the republicans. Great
                    consternation of the committee ensued. M. Barrot was inflexible. At last it was
                    resolved to submit the decision to the whole meeting. But the meeting very
                    plainly declared they would have no alterations in the programme; they would not
                    violate the understanding upon which the democrats had come to Lille. M. Odillon
                    Barrot, along with his tail of liberal deputies and editors, scornfully retired;
                    Messrs Flocon and Ledru-Rollin were sent for, the banquet took place in spite of
                    the liberals, and M. Ledru’s speech was rapturously applauded.</p>
                <p>Thus the treacherous plot of the middle-class reformers resulted in a glorious
                    triumph of democracy. M. Odillon Barrot had to decamp shamefully, and will never
                    dare to show his face again in the democratic city of Lille. His only excuse
                    was, he had understood the gentlemen of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>
                    intended to profit by the Lille banquet to get up a revolution — in the
                    very depth of tranquillity!</p>
                <p>A few days after, M. Barrot got some consolation in the Avesnes banquet, a mere
                    family meeting of some middle-class liberals. Here he had the pleasure of
                    toasting the King. But at Valenciennes he was again obliged to pocket his
                    favourite sentiment, dropped so sadly at Lille; no King’s health was to be
                    drunk, although the formidable getters-up of revolutions, at the shortest
                    notice, were not at hand. The discomfited thunderer will have to devour his
                    virtuous indignation until another hole-and-corner banquet will allow him to
                    denounce “anarchism”, “physical forcism”, and “communism”, to the astounded
                    grocers and tallow-chandlers of some petty provincial town.</p>
                <p>The Lille banquet produced extraordinary discussions in the press. The
                    Conservative papers shouted triumph at the division in the ranks of the
                    reformers. M. Thiers’s old and drowsy <hi rendition="#k">Constitutionnel</hi>,
                    and the <hi rendition="#k">Siecle</hi>, M. Barrot’s “own”, all of a sudden were
                    seized with the most dreadful convulsions. “No”, shouted the indignant <hi rendition="#k">Siecle</hi> to its shopkeeping public, “no, we are none of
                    these anarchists, we have nothing in common with these restorers of the reign of
                    terror; with these followers of Marat and Robespierre; we would prefer to their
                    reign of blood the present system, were it even a hundred times worse than it
                    is!” And quite rightly; for such peaceful grocers and tallow-chandlers the white
                    nightcap is a hundred times more fit than the red cap of the Jacobin. At the
                    same time, however, that these papers heaped their vilest and most virulent
                    abuse upon the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, they treated the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> with the utmost esteem. The <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> indeed, has behaved, on this occasion, in a more than
                    doubtful manner. Already at the banquet of Cosne, this paper blamed the conduct
                    of several democrats who would not assist on account of the king’s health being
                    proposed. Now, again, it spoke very coolly of the Lille banquet, and deplored
                    the accident which for a moment troubled the demonstration, while several
                    provincial allies of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> openly attacked the
                    conduct of Messrs Ledru and Flocon. The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> now
                    asked of that paper a more explicit delaration. The <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> declared his article to be quite explicit enough. Then, asked
                    the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, what was the deplorable accident at Lille?
                    What is it you deplore? Is it M. Barrot’s impudence or his bad luck you deplore?
                    Is it M. Ledru’s speech in favour of Universal Suffrage? Is it the discomfiture
                    of monarchism, the triumph of democracy, you deplore? Do you avow, or not, what
                    your provincial allies say on this occasion? Do you accept the praise of the <hi rendition="#k">Siecle</hi>, or do you take your part of the abuse it heaps
                    upon us? Would you have advised M. Marie, your friend, to submit, if, at
                    Orleans, M. Odillon Barrot had made similar pretensions? The <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> replied, from party motives they would have no controversy
                    with the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>; they were not responsible for articles
                    sent to provincial papers by a <hi rendition="#i">“friend”</hi> of theirs; as to
                    the other questions, the past of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> allowed
                    them to pass them unnoticed, and not to trouble themselves with a reply. The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> gave the whole of this reply with this remark
                    only: — “Our questions remain.” Democrats now have the documents under
                    their eyes — they may judge for themselves. This they have done; a whole
                    host of radical, and even liberal, papers of France have declared in the most
                    decided terms for the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>. The conduct of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, indeed, deserves the strongest blame. This
                    paper is getting more and more into the hands of the middle-classes. It has of
                    late always deserted the cause of democracy at the decisive moment; it has
                    always preached union with the middle-classes, and has on more than one occasion
                    served none but Thiers and Odillon Barrot. If the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> does not very soon change its conduct, it will cease to be
                    counted as a democratic paper. And in this Lille affair, the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, out of mere personal antipathy against men more radical than
                    itself, has not hesitated to sacrifice the very priniciples upon which itself
                    had contracted an alliance with the liberals in order to get up banquets. After
                    what has passed, the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> will never again be able
                    to oppose seriously toasting the King at future banquets. The “past” of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> is not so very bright as to allow of its
                    answering by silence only the questions of its contemporary. Think only of its
                    defence of the Parisian Bastiles!</p>
                <p>P.S. — The Reform Banquet of Dijon has come off this week. Thirteen hundred
                    sat down at dinner. The whole affair was thoroughly democratic. No toast to the
                    king, of course. All the speakers belonged to the party of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>. MM. Louis Blanc, Flocon, E. Arago, and
                    Ledru-Rollin, were the chiefspeakers. M. Flocon, editor of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, spoke to the toast of the foreign democrats,
                    and mentioned the English Chartists in a very honourable manner. Next week I
                    shall give you his speech at full lenght, as well as a full report of the whole
                    proceedings of this most important meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>