<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Reform Movement in France</title>
                <title type="sub">Banquet of Dijon</title>
                <title type="sub">Reform Banquet at Lisle — Speech of M. Ledru-Rollin</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-17</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] Reform Movement in France. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 530, 18. Dezember 1847. S. 2.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Reform Movement in France.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Banquet of Dijon.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Reform Banquet at Lisle — Speech of M. Ledru-Rollin.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-12-18</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">530</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">4-6</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-12-01" notAfter="1847-12-15">Erste Hälfte Dezember 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Reform Movement in France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Banquet of Dijon.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>This meeting of the Democracy of the department of the Côte d’Or, was
                    incontestibly the most splendid one of the whole series of Reform Banquets. 1300
                    sat down to dinner. There were present deputations from almost all the
                    neighbouring towns, and even a Swiss deputation, composed of citizens from
                    Neufchâtel, Geneva, and Lucerne. The character of the meeting is very clearly
                    marked out by the names of the principal speakers — <choice>
                        <sic>M.M.</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">MM.</corr>
                    </choice> Louis Blanc, Flocon, Ledru-Rollin, Etienne Arago — all of them
                    belonging to the Ultra-Democratic party, represented by the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>. We need not say that Louis Philippe was not toasted at this
                    dinner.</p>
                <p>M. Signard, of Gray, a neighbouring town, spoke to the toast — “The
                    Democrats of Lille who, at the late banquet of their town, sternly refused to
                    compromise with the sham-Liberals; and by their energy, union, and intelligence,
                    saved the honour of Democracy.”</p>
                <p>M. Etienne Arago, a well-known literary character of Paris, and who but recently
                    brought upon the stage an exceedingly successful comedy, entitled “The
                    Aristocracies”, then spoke to the sentiment — “The development of
                    literature, science, and the fine arts”; exposing, in a brilliant speech, the
                    rapid advance literature and science were sure to make under a free and
                    democratic system.</p>
                <p>At the toast — “The future progress of France”, the chairman called upon M.
                    Louis Blanc, who was very enthusiastically received by the meeting. He delivered
                    a splendid speech, containing many just and striking observations on the past
                    developement of France; on the conclusions to draw from it with regard to the
                    future; on the particular character impressed indelibly upon the French
                    Democratic Movement by the revolution. He was repeatedly and deservedly
                    interrupted by applause. It was a speech quite worthy of the first historical
                    writer France now possesses. There is, however, one point upon which we would
                    make a few observations, which we hope will be taken in the same friendly spirit
                    in which we write them.</p>
                <p>M. Blanc says — “We want union in Democracy. And no one may deceive
                    himself, we do not think and labour for France only, but for the whole world,
                    because the future of France contains in it the future of mankind. In fact, we
                    are placed in this admirable position, that, without ever cessing to be
                    national, we are necessarily cosmopolite, and are even more cosmopolite than
                    national. Whoever would call himself a Democrat, and be at the same time an
                    Englishman, would give the lie to the history of his own country, for the part
                    which England has always played, has been a struggle of egotism against
                    fraternity. In the same manner, he who is a Frenchman, and would not be a
                    cosmopolite, would give the lie to his country’s part; for France never could
                    make predominant any idea, except it was for the benefit of the whole world.
                    Gentlemen, at the time of the Crusades, when Europe went to conquer the grave of
                    Christ, it was France who took the movement under her wings. Afterwards, when
                    the priests would impose upon us the yoke of Papist supremacy, the Gallican
                    bishops defended the rights of conscience. And in the last days of the ancient
                    monarchy, who supported young, republican America? France, always France! And
                    what was true of monarchical France, how should it not be true of Republican
                    France? Where, in the book of history, do we find anything resembling that
                    admirable, self-sacrificing, disinterestedness of the Republic, when, exhausted
                    by the blood she had shed on our frontiers and on the scaffold, she found yet
                    more blood to shed for her Batavian brethren? When beaten or victorious, she
                    enlightens her very enemies by the sparks of her genius! Let Europe send us
                    sixteen armies, and we shall send her liberty in return.”</p>
                <p>Now, without intending to deprecate in any manner the heroic efforts of the
                    French Republic, and the immense gratitude the world owes to the great men of
                    the Republic, we think that the relative position of France and England, with
                    regard to cosmopolitism, is not at all justly delineated in the above sketch. We
                    entirely deny the cosmopolitic character ascribed to France before the
                    revolution, and the times of Louis XI., and Richelieu, may serve as proofs. But
                    what is it M. Blanc ascribes to France? That she never could make predominant
                    any idea, except it was to benefit the whole world. Well, we should think M.
                    Louis Blanc could not show us any country in the world which could do otherwise
                    than France is said to have done. Take England, for instance, which M. Blanc
                    places in direct opposition to France. England invented the steam engine;
                    England erected the railway; two things which, we believe, are worth a good many
                    ideas. Well, did England invent them for herself, of for the world? The French
                    glory in spreading civilisation everywhere, principally in Algiers. Well, who
                    has spread civilisation in America, Asia, Africa, and Australia, but England?
                    Who founded the very Republic, in the freeing of which France took some part?
                    England — always England. If France assisted in freeing the American republic
                    from English tyranny, England freed the Dutch republic, just two hundred years
                    sooner, from Spanish oppression. If France gave, at the end of the last century,
                    a glorious example to the whole world, we cannot silently pass by the fact that
                    England, a hundred and fifty years sooner, gave that example, and found at that
                    time, not even France prepared to follow. And, as far as ideas are concerned,
                    these very ideas, which the French philosophers of the 18th century — which
                    Voltaire, Rousseau, Diderot, D’Alembert, and others, did so much to popularise —
                    where had these ideas first been originated, but in England? Let us never forget
                    Milton, the first defender of regicide, Algernon Sydney, Bolingbroke, and
                    Shaftesbury, over their French more brilliant followers.</p>
                <p>If an Englishman “would call himself a democrat he would give the lie to the
                    history of his own country”, says M. Blanc. Well, we consider it as the veriest
                    proof of sterling democracy, that it <hi rendition="#i">must</hi> give the lie
                    to its country, that it <hi rendition="#i">must</hi> repudiate all
                    responsibility for a past filled up with misery, tyranny, class-oppression, and
                    superstition. Let the French not make an exception to the other democrats; let
                    them not take the responsibility for the doings of their Kings and Aristocrats
                    of former times. Therefore, what M. Blanc thinks a disadvantage to English
                    democrats, we think to be a great advantage, that they <hi rendition="#i">must</hi> repudiate the past, and only look to the future.</p>
                <p>A Frenchman is necessarily a cosmopolite. Yes, in a world ruled over by French
                    influence, French manners, fashions, ideas, politics. In a world in which every
                    nation has adopted the characteristics of French nationality. But that is
                    exactly what the democrats of other nations will not like. Quite ready to give
                    up the harshness of their own nationality, they expect the same from the French.
                    They will not be satisfied in the assertion, on the part of the French, that
                    they <hi rendition="#i">are</hi> cosmopolites; assertion which amounts to the
                    demand urged upon all others to become Frenchmen.</p>
                <p>Compare Germany. Germany is the fatherland of an immense number of inventions
                    — of the printing press, for instance. Germany has produced — and
                    this is recognised upon all hands — a far greater number of generous and
                    cosmopolitic ideas than France and England put together. And Germany, in
                    practice, has always been humiliated, always been deceived in all her hopes. She
                    can tell best what French cosmopolitism has been. In the same measure as France
                    has to complain — and quite justly — of the treachery of English
                    policy, Germany has experienced a policy quite as treacherous on the part of
                    France, from Louis XI. down to Louis Philippe. If we were to apply the measures
                    of M. Louis Blanc, the Germans would be the true cosmopolites, and yet they do
                    not pretend to this.</p>
                <p>So much upon this point. We wish to establish a discussion upon it, as this will
                    only lead to a mutual understanding; to a firm union of French and English
                    Democracy.</p>
                <p>After M. Blanc, M. Flocon spoke to the toast: “The Democrats of Europe”.</p>
                <p>M. Flocon said: Look around you, listen to the voices which arise from foreign
                    countries; complaints or menace; sighs of hopes; what tell they? They invoke the
                    principle of the French Revolution; they proclaim in the face of all despotisms,
                    its immortal motto: <hi rendition="#i">Liberte, Egalite, Fraternite.</hi> Yes,
                    those very nations, which in the delusions of slavery and ignorance, made an
                    impious war on the revolution; they now come by thousands to take up its
                    standard, and promise to be most ardent defenders of the glorious principles
                    they did not understand in times past. This striking fact is before the eyes of
                    the world, and I know nothing more terrible to our enemies, nothing which could
                    more effectually recall to our minds our duty. In England, at the side of the
                    old factions, in the face of the richest and most tyrannical aristocracy of the
                    world, the people are organising. An immense association, conducted by
                    experienced leaders, enrols daily thousands of working men, who will undertake
                    to avenge the wrongs of humanity. And the rights of man are not a new watchword
                    in England. At the time of the old civil wars, in the midst of religious
                    fanaticism and political passions, several parties clearly saw the great social truth:</p>
                <lg type="poem">
                <l>When Adam delved and Eve span,</l><lb/>
                <l>Where was then the gentleman?</l><lb/>
                </lg>
                <p>That was proclaimed by the Covenanters almost three
                    hundred years ago. The same question is again put; and the cotton lords disdain
                    as much to listen to the complaint of the children of toil, as did the landlords
                    in by-gone times. Therefore, asking what is right will not suffice, the people
                    must be strong enough to take it, and the English people know this. In Belgium,
                    at this very moment, a society is organising, uniting Democrats of all nations,
                    a Democratic Congress is being prepared. In Germany, while the princes play the
                    game of granting gracious constitutions, the people prepare themselves for
                    working out their own salvation. The speaker then reviewed briefly the Polish,
                    Italian, and Swiss movements, and closed this speech as follows: — Yes,
                    the seed of the revolution is germinating, the soil is fertile, the splendid
                    flower of hope adorns the fields of the future. But the winter has been long,
                    and we ought soon to take to the sickle, to make our harvest. Let us then take
                    up again the work of the revolution, where our fathers left it. Let us make
                    haste, else we shall have to take it up where they commenced. (Loud
                    applause.)</p>
                <p>The next toast: “The Sovereignty of the people”, was spoken to by M.
                    Ledru-Rollin, deputy.</p>
                <p>Letters of apology were read from <choice>
                        <sic>M.M.</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">MM.</corr>
                    </choice> François Arago, Lamennais, Dupont de l’Eure, and the meeting
                    separated.</p>
                <p>This demonstration proves that the provincial Democrats are more and more leaving
                    the party of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, in order to rally around the party of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>.</p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Reform Banquet at Lisle — Speech
                            of M. Ledru-Rollin.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>In response to the toast: — “To the Labourers, — to their
                    imprescriptible rights, — to their sacred interests, hitherto
                    unknown”.</p>
                <p>“<hi rendition="#k">Citizens</hi>, — Yes, to the labourers! to their
                    imprescriptible rights, — to their sacred interests, hitherto unknown. To
                    the unalienable rights of man, proclaimed in principle, by two glorious
                    revolutions; but artfully eluded in their application, and successfully
                    re-wrested from the people, and which are now only a glorious, yet bitter
                    remembrance! Political rights of the people, it is said, is madness. How entrust
                    them with them, in their state of incapacity, of ignorance, of moral depravity?
                    To give the people political freedom is a blind and dangerous power; it is
                    revolution — blood — anarchy — chaos! Gentlemen, you know the
                    people; you in this industrial city, at once so wealthy and so poor, believe you
                    this picture to be true! Oh! doubtless, if we cast our eyes over the pages of
                    certain romance writers, to whom the grand side of things has appeared trivial,
                    vulgar — who have sought for effect in the humorous, the fantastic, the
                    exceptional, the people — is it thus! Taking the normal life of our towns,
                    from one point, where criminals escaped from justice, find a refuge, the way of
                    life, the dregs of society, they have said, ‘Such are the people!’ Doubtless
                    such would still be the people, did we put faith in those mercenary writers,
                    who, to terrify the wealthy, cry out against the invasion of the barbarians! <hi rendition="#i">Barbarians!</hi> they have cast that epithet upon the people,
                    as the most outrageous of insults. Ah! if barbarians always signify men full of
                    simplicity, of strength, of social and youthful energy, those barbarians can
                    alone save our worn-out official world, fast hastening to decay in powerlessness
                    and corruption. No; a thousand times no, it is not the people. It is not upon
                    the theatre of crime and debauchery, that it must be sought for. To be
                    acquainted with it, we must transport ourselves into those manufacturing towns,
                    where the merchant, struggling against unrestricted competition which crushes
                    him, between the tyrannical pressure of capital and opposition to wages, which
                    eat him up, he is compelled to reduce those wages, in order to avoid bankruptcy
                    and dishonour. Ah! believe not that the people, in their spirit of justice,
                    always accuse the masters as the cause of that cruel necessity. Know they not
                    that our industry fails for want of outlet; that we have seen the greatest
                    number of the markets of the world closed against us; and that our commerce has
                    perished, where our flag has been trampled under foot! Well; in the midst of
                    those vicissitudes, of those fluctuations, of this crisis of wages, what befals
                    the workman? The labour of the father, no longer sufficing to procure bread for
                    the family, the daughter prostitutes herself for food; the child must go to aid
                    the formidable machine, and exhaust his unevolved strength; and by the side of
                    those beauteous fabrics, the product of our industry, the eye wanders over
                    ricketty boys, faded girls, worn-out men, bent under the pressure of premature
                    labour. And, nevertheless, of that physically decayed population — those
                    who have escaped enervation, sickness — who have attained their proper
                    height, will go forth to do battle for their country — nobly to encounter
                    death beneath her banner. Such are the people of the towns, sociable, good,
                    patient in the midst of those daily evils, — doing more, deriving from
                    within themselves the light of knowledge, dealt out to them with such a
                    niggardly hand, reading, sometimes composing verses upon their sufferings or
                    their prospects, publishing journals, which enlighten and prepare those
                    formidable problems, respecting the future fate of mankind! It is those people
                    of the towns whom some writers, who only judge by their own flimsy mindes, call
                    barbarians! In this slight and rapid sketch, we have only seen the people in
                    their habitual life — their daily struggles; but were one of those
                    unforeseen scourges in which a fearful inundation seeps off everything in its
                    destructive course, a terrific fire, or a severe cholera suddenly to arise, who
                    would be foremost in the cause of humanity? who would forget their families and
                    their wives, upon their lowly couches? their children, who might die on the
                    morrow? who would peril life, without counting the cost; and fly when the
                    service was performed, without even leaving their names? — the people!
                    Intelligence or devotedness, head or heart, the people are, therefore, worthy to
                    exercise the rights to which they lay claim. And who are better aware of it than
                    the citizens, who by the superhuman efforts of the people have conquered the
                    twofold tyranny of the nobility and the priesthood. It was to that clergy, to
                    that nobility, as to the States of 1617, that a member of the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> once said — ‘You, our elder brothers, you, our
                    younger brothers — for we are all brothers — forming but one and the
                    same nation’. And the clergy and the nobles attempted to make that courageous
                    member of the third retract and their minions to scourge him, regarding a
                    plebeian as of a conquered and inferior race. Not only are the people worthy to
                    represent themselves, but if justice is to be rendered, they can only be
                    efficiently represented <hi rendition="#i">by themselves</hi>. Who, then, in a
                    legislative chamber knows sufficiently, at this present moment, their interests,
                    there wants to dare to defend them? There are many men, gentlemen, who would
                    unite in our principle of Reform; for it is now made evident — but they
                    still dread the advance of democracy; yet never has a solemn and decisive
                    moment, in the onward march of humanity, been preceded by more significant
                    auguries! Let us pass rapidly in review those transcendant men of our own age.
                    Towering above all is one, whose prophetic speech is engraven on every heart.
                    ‘Before fifty years’, said Napoleon, ‘Europe will be Cossack or Republican.’ It
                    shall not be Cossack — and in this patriotic city exists the right so to
                    say. If doubt could ever have prevailed, it would assuredly not have been in the
                    midst of those whose love of national independence and of the revolution of
                    1792, transformed each citizen into a hero! Republican — but I pause,
                    gentlemen — the laws of September are in force, and in order to be strong,
                    when armed in a good cause, we must know how to keep within the law. I shall,
                    therefore, only permit myself to choose, as interpreters of my thoughts, a few
                    men, whose very names shed a glory over their country. He, for example, who has
                    sung the high hymn of legitimacy, and who has achieved renown, in essaying to
                    restore the ancient ruins of the past. Chateaubriand, in his sincerity, has been
                    unable to avoid regarding the approaching future of the world, as tending
                    towards democracy. Beranger, whose patriotic hymns will be eternally repeated by
                    the world — hymns, which we, his contemporaries, ought to teach to our
                    children as a prayer, whilst a Waterloo remains to be avenged!! Beranger
                    believes in the approaching sovereignty of the people. And Lamartine, sparkling
                    with poetry, with eloquence, has passed by legitimacy — he has traversed
                    the marches of the plain, in order to approach nearer to us. Though an ardent
                    admirer of the Girondists, yet the noble candour of his mind leads him to draw
                    conclusions favourable to the Radicals. There is something, however, which still
                    divides him from pure democracy; as for myself, I only behold the steps of
                    giants, each day rapidly striding towards us. So much for men of letters,
                    gentlemen, and that unanimous testimony rendered by such illustrations in favour
                    of our party, might suffice for its hopes. But cast your eyes into the domain of
                    science; behold a man who is at the summit of all — of whom the two worlds
                    would deprive us — Arago! But for an imperious duty he would, much better
                    than I am able, have spoken to you of the rights of the people; he who was the
                    first to advocate their cause in another assembly, where to do so required no
                    small amount of moral courage. Is not, then, Arago entirely for democracy? And
                    in the arts, who with his powerful chisel draws forth from marble, those men who
                    have best served the people? Who confides to the eternity of bronze those grand
                    revolutionary figures, to bequeath them to the admiration of future ages? David
                    of Angers! Is he not, also, for the cause of the people? Well, when so many
                    illustrious men declare in favour of democracy, or struggle for its attainment,
                    how conclude otherwise than that right and Providence combat with us, and for
                    us? Those are the teachings of talented men; but have not the teachings of the
                    people also their manifestations? Look at Poland — heroic Poland —
                    the last pulsations of whose heart still <choice>
                        <sic>throbs</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">throb</corr>
                    </choice> for liberty — no longer possessing an army; each day some martyr
                    consecrates himself to her cause. Italy; she too longs for unity. She emerges
                    from her ruins, which constituted her glory, in order to acquire fresh renown.
                    May she on awakening distrust herself; let her remember Masianello. Switzerland;
                    — I feel that I ought well to weigh my words at this solemn moment. We can
                    do one thing, gentlemen, we can unite ourselves for an instant, by recollection,
                    by thought, with those whom we look upon as brothers, in order to pray that
                    victory may be with them, as have hitherto been right and reason! The cause of
                    Switzerland is ours, gentlemen; the Radicals there wage war against two things,
                    which are the plague-spots of our era — aristocrats and worthless priests.
                    Respect our creeds, but war against those who, under the mask of religion, are
                    the abettors of despotism, and of tyranny. Short-sighted beings! who see not in
                    this double association of genius and of the people, the near advent of a
                    Messiah of equality! Thus then, O people, to whom I would sacrifice all that I
                    possess of devotedness and strength, <hi rendition="#i">hope</hi> and <hi rendition="#i">believe</hi>. Between this period, in which thy ancient faith
                    is extinguished, and in which the new light has not yet been showered upon you,
                    each evening in thy desolate dwelling piously repeat the immortal symbol —
                        <hi rendition="#k">Liberty, Equality, Fraternity!</hi> Yes, liberty for all;
                    liberty of conscience, liberty of thought, liberty of association; for man
                    cannot become moral without communing with man, and it is in order the better to
                    subjugate him that he is isolated by a system of corruption. They know that a
                    bundle of sticks cannot be broken. Equality likewise for all — equality in
                    presence of civil law, equality in political matters, equality in education, in
                    order that man may have no superior, except in morals or in virtue! Fraternity
                    — inexhaustable source, from whence will spring noble and celebrated
                    institutions; of association, of strength. Then labour will no longer be a
                    right, it will be a duty. Let there be no mere revenues, except from labour and
                    for labour. Yes, salvation. O great and immortal symbol, thy advent draws nigh!
                    People, may the plaudits bestowed on thy humble interpreter be wafted to thee,
                    and prove at once a consolation and a hope!”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>