<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">France</title>
                <title type="sub">The “Satisfied” Majority —
                    Guizot’s Scheme of “Reform” — Queer Motions of M. Garnier Pages
                    — Democratic Banquet at Chalon — Speech of M. Ledru-Rollin
                    — A Democratic Congress — Speech of M. Flocon — The
                    “Reforme” and the “National”</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-18</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] France. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 533, 8. Januar 1848. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">France.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">The “Satisfied” Majority — Guizot’s Scheme of “Reform” — Queer Motions of M. Garnier Pages — Democratic Banquet at Chalon — Speech of M. Ledru-Rollin — A Democratic Congress — Speech of M. Flocon — The “Reforme” and the “National”.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1848-01-08</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">533</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2-3</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1848-01-01" notAfter="1848-01-06">Anfang Januar 1848</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The “Satisfied” Majority —
                            Guizot’s Scheme of “Reform” — Queer Motions of M. Garnier Pages
                            — Democratic Banquet at Chalon — Speech of M. Ledru-Rollin
                            — A Democratic Congress — Speech of M. Flocon — The
                            “Reforme” and the “National”.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>The French Chambers are now open, and we shall very soon have the pleasure of
                    seeing what effect the Reform agitation has had upon the 225 “satisfied” members
                    of the majority. We shall see whether they will be satisfied, too, with the
                    manner in which Guizot has exposed France in the Swiss question to the ridicule
                    of all Europe. Why, this fat, corrupting and corrupted, stock-jobbing,
                    swindling, bloodsucking, and cowardly majority, are the very men to swallow down
                    even that — to say “amen” to the trick which Palmerston, in return for the
                    Spanish marriages, played on his worthy colleague Guizot — to declare that
                    never was France so great, so glorious, so respected, so “satisfied” — as
                    at this very moment.</p>
                <p>And it is at this very moment that all the papers of Paris, from the <hi rendition="#k">Debats</hi> to the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, discuss,
                    as openly as can be done under the circumstances, the eventuality consequent
                    upon the death of Louis-Philippe. The <hi rendition="#k">Debats</hi>, afraid of
                    seeing the majority split itself up, warns them every day that this inevitable
                    event, whenever it takes place, will be the signal for the general rendezvous of
                    all political parties; that “republicanism”, <choice>
                        <sic>communism”</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">“communism”</corr>
                    </choice>, “anarchism”, “terrorism”, and so forth, will then break from their
                    subterraneous caverne, to spread desolation, horror, and destruction; that
                    France will be lost — liberty, safety, property will be lost, unless the friends
                    of order (M. Guizot and Co., of course) keep them down with a strong hand; that
                    this perilous moment may occur any day; and that, if M. Guizot is not supported
                    in office, all will be lost. The other papers, the <hi rendition="#k">Presse</hi>, the <hi rendition="#k">Constitutionnel</hi>, the <hi rendition="#k">Siecle</hi>, on the contrary, say that quite the reverse will
                    take place, that all the horrors of a bloody revolution will overrun the
                    country, unless that abominable corruptor, Guizot, shall, at the moment of the
                    king’s death, have been replaced by their respective political heroes, by M. de
                    Girardin, M. Thiers, or M. O. Barrot. The Radical papers discuss the question
                    from another point of view, as we shall see by and by.</p>
                <p>Thus, even the <hi rendition="#k">Debats</hi> agrees indirectly that “satisfied”
                    France only awaits the proper moment for proving her dissatisfaction, in a
                    manner which the frightened <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> imagination of the
                        <hi rendition="#k">Debats</hi> depicts most ludicrously to its terrified
                    reason. This, however, does not matter to the “satisfied” two
                    hundred and twenty-five. They have a logic of their own. If the people are
                    satisfied, then there is no reason for a change of system. If they are
                    dissatisfied, why, then, their very dissatisfaction is a reason to stick more to
                    the system; for if only one inch was abandoned, there would be a sudden eruption
                    of all the horrors of revolution. Do whatever you like, these <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> will always draw the conclusion from it that they are the
                    best rulers of the country.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, Guizot will give a small bit of reform. He will add to the
                    electoral list the “capacities”, that is, all persons possessing a
                    university degree, lawyers, doctors, and other such humbugs. A glorious reform,
                    indeed! But this will suffice to disarm the “Progressive
                    Conservatives”, or, as they call themselves now — for, in want of
                    something else to do, they change names every quarter — the Conservative
                    opposition. And it will be a ready stroke for M. Thiers, who, while sending his
                    second, M. Duvergier de Hauranne, on a Reform banquetting errand, slily prepared
                    his reform plan, with which he was to surprise the Chambers, and which was
                    equally the same as the one now to be proposed by his rival, Guizot.</p>
                <p>There will be a deal of crying, shouting, and noise-making generally in the
                    Chambers; but I hardly think M. Guizot has anything serious to apprehend from
                    his faithful two hundred and twenty-five.</p>
                <p>So much for the official world. In the meantime the Reform banquets and the
                    polemic between the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> and the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> have continued. The allied oppositions, that is the left
                    centre (M. Thier’s party), the left (M. Odillon Barrot’s party), and
                    the “sensible Radicals” (the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>), had
                    the banquets of Castres, Montpellier, Neubourg, and others; the ultra-Democrats
                    (the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>), had the banquet of Châlon. The chief
                    speaker of the banquets of Montpellier and Neubourg was M. Garnier-Pages,
                    brother of the well-known democrat of that name, deceased a few years ago. But
                    M. Garnier-Pages, the younger, is far from being like his brother; he totally
                    lacks that energy, that courage and never compromising spirit which secured so
                    prominent a position to the deceased leader of French Democracy. At Neubourg, M.
                    Garnier-Pages, the younger, came out with assertions proving him to be entirely
                    ignorant of the actual state of society, and consequently of the means of
                    improving it. While all modern democracy is based upon the great fact, that
                    modern society is irreparably divided into two classes — the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, or possessors of all means of production
                    and all produce, and the proletarians, or possessors of nothing but their labour
                    to live upon; that the latter class is socially and politically oppressed by the
                    former; while the acknowledged tendency of modern Democrats in all countries is
                    to make political power pass from the middle classes to the working classes,
                    these latter constituting the immense majority of the people — in the face
                    of all these facts, M. Garnier boldly asserts that the division of the people
                    into middle classes and working classes does in reality not exist, that it is a
                    mischievous invention of M. Guizot’s got up to divide the people; that in
                    spite of Guizot he recognises that all Frenchmen <hi rendition="#i">are</hi>
                    equal — that they all participate of the same life, and that he recognises
                    in France none but <hi rendition="#i">French citizens</hi>! According to M.
                    Garnier-Pages, then, the monopolising of all instruments of productions in the
                    hands of the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi>, which abandons the
                    proletarians to the tender mercies of the economical law of wages, reducing the
                    share of the working men to the lowest level of food, is an invention of M.
                    Guizot’s too! According to him, the whole of that desperate struggle now
                    going on in all civilised countries of the world, between Labour and Capital, a
                    struggle the different phases of which are marked by coalitions, trades’
                    unions, murders, riots, and bloody insurrections — a struggle whose
                    reality is testified by the death of the proletarians shot at Lyons, at Preston,
                    at Langenbielau, at Prague, this struggle has been carried on upon no better
                    grounds than a lying assertion of a French professor! What else do the words of
                    M. Garnier-Pages mean but this? “Let the capitalists continue to
                    monopolise all powers of production — let the working men continue to live
                    upon the merest pittance, but give him, as a compensation for his suffering, the
                        <hi rendition="#i">title</hi> of a citizen!” Ay, M. Pages would under
                    certain circumstances, and with certain restrictions, perhaps, consent to give
                    the people the suffrage; but let them never think of profiting by the gift by
                    passing measures which would essentially alter the actual mode of production and
                    distribution of wealth — which would, in course of time, give to the
                    entire people the command of the productive powers of the country, and do away
                    with all individual “employers”! The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> was perfectly right in styling this honourable gentleman a <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois radical</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Ultra Democrats had, as I said before, only one banquet, but it was a bumper,
                    and worth a dozen of the coalition party. More than two thousand citizens sat
                    down to dinner at Châlon-sur-Saone. The <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> had
                    been invited, but very significantly had not come. The men of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, accordingly, had it all their own way. M.
                    Ledru-Rollin, who had been designated by the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> as
                    the chief of the ultra-democratic party, here accepted this position. He
                    explained his position and the position of his party, by relating in a brilliant
                    abstract, the different phases of French democracy since 1789. He then justified
                    himself against the attacks of the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, attacked
                    that paper in turn, and proposed a jury of democrats to be nominated from all
                    parts of France — one-half by either party — to decide between the
                        <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> and the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>.
                    And now (he said), after having settled this home affair, would it not be a good
                    thing if the French democracy entered into relation with the other democracies?
                    There is at this moment a great movement going on in Europe amongst all the
                    disinherited, who suffer by heart or by hunger. This is the moment to console
                    them, to strengthen them, and to enter into communion with them. Let us, then,
                    hold a congress of Democrats of all nations, now, when the congress of kings has
                    failed! There is one republic in Europe, which just now has secured in its own
                    territory the ascendancy of democracy — there is Switzerland, a country
                    worthy of seeing the Democrats of all nations upon its free soil! And thus,
                    citizens, let me conclude, by coupling to my toast: “To the Unity of the French Revolution”, that other one, “The Union of all Democracies”.</p>
                <p>This speech excited loud applause, and it merited it. We heartily rejoice in M.
                    Ledru-Rollin’s oratorial success at Châlon, but at the same time, must
                    protest against an unguarded expression, which, we are sure, has been said
                    without intention to hurt. M. Ledru-Rollin says, that the moment has arrived for
                    French Democrats to console and to strengthen the suffering working men of other
                    nations. The Democrats of <hi rendition="#i">no country</hi>, we are sure, want
                    consolation from whomsoever it be. They admire the revolutionary pride of French
                    Democrats, but they take for themselves the right to be quite as proud and
                    independent. The four millions of English Chartists certainly are strong enough
                    to do their own work for themselves. Glad as we are to see the French democracy
                    take up with enthusiasm the idea of a Democratic Congress, and an alliance of
                    all democracies, we expect, before all things, a perfect reciprocity and
                    equality. Any alliance, which should not recognise this equality as its
                    foundation, would itself be anti-democratic. We know, however, too well the
                    profoundly democratic sentiments of the men of the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> to doubt of their perfectly agreeing with us; we only wish
                    them to drop, for the interest of our common cause, certain expressions, which
                    far from expressing their real sentiments, are an inheritance from the time when
                    the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> alone represented the French Democracy.</p>
                <p>At the same banquet, M. Flocon spoke to the toast: — “The Rights of
                    Man and of the Citizen”. He read the declaration of rights of the National
                    Convention, which he declared to be, up to this day, the faithful abstract of
                    true Democratic principles. To this, what he called the true French principle,
                    he opposed the present system of moneyocracy, which places man upon a lower
                    level than even cattle, because man is over abundant, and costs more than he
                    gives in nature when his labour is not required. This system, from the country
                    in which it first arose, he called the English system. But lo, he said, while
                    the English principle is introduced into the fatherland of the revolution, the
                    English people themselves strive to throw its yoke off their shoulders, and
                    write upon their banners the glorious motto: — “Liberty, Equality,
                    Fraternity!” Thus, by one of those painful turns, of which history offers
                    more than one example, the very nation which first gave truth to the world,
                    fallen back into darkness and ignorance, would soon be obliged to ask from its
                    neighbours the revolutionary traditions which itself could not conserve. Shall
                    it ever come thus far with us? No, never, as long as there are Democrats like
                    you, and meetings like this! No, we never will prop up the worm-eaten frame of
                    those English institutions, which the English themselves will no longer support!
                    (No, no!) Well then, to your tents, O Israel! Every one of you rally round his
                    standard! Every one for his faith! Here, on our side, Democracy with her
                    twenty-five millions of proletarians to free, whom she greets with the names of
                    citizens, brothers, equal and free men; there the bastard-opposition, with her
                    monopolies and aristocracy of capital! They speak of reducing the qualification
                    by one half; we, we proclaim the rights of man and of the citizen! (Loud and
                    long-continued applause, which ended by the whole meeting singing the <hi rendition="#i">Chant du Depart</hi>.) We regret not to have room for giving
                    more of the speeches delivered at this splendid and thoroughly Democratic
                    banquet.</p>
                <p>At last, the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> has forced the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> to enter into a <hi rendition="#i">polemic</hi>. The former
                    journal, in declaring its adhesion to the principles announced by M.
                    Garnier-Pages, at the Montpellier banquet, in a speech on the French revolution,
                    at the same time disputed the right of men, like M. Garnier, who had sacrificed
                    the interests of Democracy to M. Odillon Barrot and the middle-class opposition,
                    to act as the representatives of the principles of the Revolution. This, at
                    last, brought out a reply from the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>, in which
                    Ledru-Rollin in his turn was attacked. The principal points of accusation
                    against the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> were: 1st. Its support of the
                    bastiles around Paris, by which the inheritance of the revolution was placed
                    under the control of twelve hundred pieces of cannon. 2nd. Its silence last
                    year, upon a pamphlet of M. Carnot, in which he engaged the Democrats to join
                    the Left Centre and the Left, to get them into office as soon as possible, to
                    drop for the moment the Republican principle, and to agitate for an extension of
                    the Suffrage within the limits of the Charter. M. Garnier-Pages, the younger,
                    had about the same time announced similar principles; the pamphlet declared
                    itself to be the expression of the opinion not of an individual, but of a party
                    in the Chamber. The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> attacked both M.
                    Garnier’s speech and M. Carnot’s (son of the celebrated member of
                    the Convention and Republican minister of war) pamphlet, and tried to provoke
                    the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> to a declaration. But the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> remained silent. The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> rightly declared that the policy proposed by both deputies
                    would tend to nothing but to place the Democratic party wholly under the control
                    of <choice>
                        <sic>M.M.</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">MM.</corr>
                    </choice> Thiers and Barrot, and break it up entirely as a distinct party. 3rd.
                    The <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> following up in practice during the Reform
                    banquet agitation, the policy proposed by M. Carnot. 4th. Its virulent and
                    calumniating attacks upon the Communists, while proposing at the same time no
                    practicable or effective remedy for the misery of the working people.</p>
                <p>The dispute has been going on for a week at least. At last the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> retired from the contest, after having conducted it in a very
                    improper manner. It has been regularly beaten; but, in order to mask its defeat,
                    it finally accepted M. Ledru’s proposal of a Democratic jury.</p>
                <p>We can only declare our full adhesion to the part the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> has taken in this affair. It has saved the honour,
                    independence, and the strength of French Democracy as a distinct party. It has
                    maintained the principle of the Revolution, which were endangered by the course
                    pursued by the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi>. It has asserted the rights of
                    the working classes in opposition to middle-class encroachments. It has unmasked
                    these <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi> radicals — who would make the
                    people believe that no class oppression exists — who will not see the
                    frightful civil war of class against class in modern society — and who
                    have nothing but vain words for the working people. The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> by keeping up this contest, until it has succeeded in forcing
                    its haughty rival to break silence, to wave, to retract, to explain, and at last
                    to withdraw — the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, we say, has well
                    merited of Democracy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>