<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="letter mega" xml:id="B00005" xml:lang="de">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">France</title>
                <title type="sub">Extraordinary Revelations — Abd-el-Kader — Guizot’s Foreign
                    Policy</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-09-19</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich:] France. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 535, 22. Januar 1848. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">France.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Extraordinary Revelations — Abd-el-Kader — Guizot’s Foreign Policy.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1848-01-22</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">535</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1848-01-11" notAfter="1848-01-20">Mitte Januar 1848</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Extraordinary Revelations — Abd-el-Kader
                            — Guizot’s Foreign Policy.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From our own Paris Correspondent.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>A curious document has just been published and distributed, as if for a New
                    Years’ gift, to the Chamber of Deputies. It is a statement of facts explaining
                    how a certain M. Petit got the place of a tax collector <hi rendition="#i">(receveur particulier)</hi> at Corbeil, near Paris, and has been published
                    by M. Petit himself. M. Petit has been forced to this act in consequence of a
                    suit for separation pending between himself and his wife, and in which action it
                    had been alleged that he had bought his place by prostituting his wife to a
                    gentleman intimately connected with M. Guizot. He now declares in his
                    publication — “Yes, my place was bought, as all places are bought now-a-day; but
                    it was bought not with prostitution, but with hard cash only.” Then he goes on
                    to detail how he first aspired to the office of a Councillor Referendary at the
                    Court of Accounts. How the ministry promised him that place, if he only could
                    procure the resignation of one of the councillors; how the minister’s secretary
                    intimated to him, which of the Councillors would most likely sell their charge;
                    how he then, for 15.000 francs, procured the wished-for resignation; how then he
                    was told he must procure a resignation of a Councillor Referendary, not of the
                    second, but of the first class, as the government wanted such a one in order to
                    fulfil a promise made by them on their coming into office; how by makeshifts of
                    different sorts, the difference of price of the two resignations was made up;
                    how at last the resignation was procured; how then the ministry wanted not only
                    a resignation like that tendered, but one of a higher degree still, of a Master
                    Councillor; how this new resignation was also procured by the means of “cash
                    down”; how finally it was offered to M. Petit to accept the tax collectorship of
                    Corbeil, rather than the place in the Court of Accounts; how M. Petit accepted
                    of this; how then the different resignations were signed and exchanged against
                    the amounts of money stipulated; and how, two days later, the whole of the royal
                    ordinances were published, accepting the resignations and promoting and naming
                    the several individuals concerned, to the offices stipulated by the
                    transaction.</p>
                <p>These are the principal facts of the matter. There are some others of less
                    importance, proving how M. Petit, as soon as he was once hooked by having paid
                    the first sum, was made to pay more and more. But these I pass over. I only
                    mention, that in the publication of M. Petit all the names are given in
                    full.</p>
                <p>You will easily imagine what a noise this little pamphlet has made in Paris. All
                    papers are full of it, and the more so, as the Minister of Finance (to which
                    department the Court of Accounts belongs) under whose direction the above
                    transactions took place, had openly denied anything of the sort ever having
                    occurred, when questioned about it in the Chamber by M. Luneau. M. Luneau, at
                    the time, declared the sale of places in the above department to be a matter of
                    public notoriety. Known to the majority, as well as to the opposition. Known to
                    every one, in short, except, it appeared, to the minister himself. M. Lacave met
                    this by a flat denial. Now the matter has come out in a manner which makes all
                    burking impossible. And yet, although all Paris has been full of it for almost a
                    week past, the government has not opened its mouth.</p>
                <p>We only repeat the words of M. Dupin the elder, pronounced when M. Luneau brought
                    the matter forward in the Chamber — “It was hardly worth while to
                    make a revolution to abolish the venality of places; if this infamous system is
                    suffered to lift up its head again.”</p>
                <p>The next subject occupying the papers is the capture of Abd-el-Kader, and the
                    resolution which the government will come to as to his future location. There is
                    no doubt they will confirm and execute the Duke D’Aumale’s promise,
                    and send the Emir to Egypt.<note place="foot" rendition="*">This letter should
                        have reached us last week, but was only delivered to us, by the friend who
                        brought it from Paris, on Tuesday last. Before this time our correspondent
                        will have discovered his error in imagining for a moment the possibility of
                        Louis-Philippe, or his man of all work, performing a just or generous
                        action. Abd-el-Kader will not be sent to Egypt; he is to be kept a close
                        prisoner in France. Another specimen of the <hi rendition="#i">honour</hi>
                        of kings! — the <hi rendition="#i">honour</hi> of Philippe the
                        Infamous! — <hi rendition="#k">Ed. N. S.</hi></note> It is curious
                    that almost all the papers of the Opposition, from the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> to the <hi rendition="#k">Constitutionnel</hi>, demanded the
                    breach of that promise. Now, there is no doubt the promise was granted
                    conditionally, and leaving the government free to confirm, or not to confirm it.
                    The refusal of confirmation would not directly imply, as the <hi rendition="#k">Sun</hi> has it, an <hi rendition="#i">infamy</hi>. But there is no doubt,
                    neither, that a similar act on the part of any other government, particularly
                    the English, would have been treated by those very same papers as the most
                    infamous treason. It is evident, that it being impossible to replace matters in
                    the same state as they were when Abd-el-Kader conditionally surrendered it would
                    imply a want of generosity of the first order, to refuse to him the confirmation
                    of the conditions of surrender. But in such questions these <hi rendition="#i">national</hi> papers are blind, and would commit the same acts for whose
                    commission they blame others. The only two papers which have spoken in favour of
                    confirming the treaty with Abd-el-Kader, are the <hi rendition="#k">Presse</hi>
                    and the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>. The first, a monarchical paper, wanted
                    it confirmed, because the government could not give the lie to a son of the
                    king, to a <hi rendition="#i">son of France</hi>; thus reviving the old title of
                    the princes of Royal blood before the revolution. “No”, said the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, “the matter is a delicate one — the
                    honour of our country is implied; in such matters we had better be too generous
                    than too narrow, and therefore confirm the word given, <hi rendition="#i">were
                        it even that of a prince</hi>.” Again, the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> alone has taken the right view of the matter.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole it is, in our opinion, very fortunate that the Arabian chief has
                    been <choice>
                        <sic>taked</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">taken</corr>
                    </choice>. The struggle of the Bedouins was a hopeless one, and though the
                    manner in which brutal soldiers, like Bugeaud, have carried on the war is highly
                    blameable, the conquest of Algeria is an important and fortunate fact for the
                    progress of civilisation. The piracies of the Barbaresque states, never
                    interfered with by the English government as long as they did not disturb their
                    ships, could not be put down but by the conquest of one of these states. And the
                    conquest of Algeria has already forced the Beys of Tunis and Tripoli, and even
                    the Emperor of Morocco, to enter upon the road of civilisation. They were
                    obliged to find other employment for their people than piracy, and other means
                    of filling their exchequer than tributes paid to them by the smaller states of
                    Europe. And if we may regret that the liberty of the Bedouins of the desert has
                    been destroyed, we must not forget that these same Bedouins were a nation of
                    robbers, — whose principal means of living consisted in making excursions
                    either upon each other, or upon the settled villagers, taking what they found,
                    slaughtering all those who resisted, and selling the remaining prisoners as
                    slaves. All these nations of free barbarians look very proud, noble, and
                    glorious at a distance, but only come near them and you will find that they, as
                    well as the more civilised nations, are ruled by the lust of gain, and only
                    employ ruder and more cruel means. And after all, the modern <hi rendition="#i">bourgeois</hi>, with civilisation, industry, order, and at least relative
                    enlightenment following him, is preferable to the feudal lord or to the
                    marauding robber, with the barbarian state of society to which they beloong.</p>
                <p>M. Guizot has laid before the Chambers part of the diplomatic correspondence
                    relating to Switzerland and Italy. The first proves again that he has been
                    regularly <hi rendition="#i">done</hi> by Lord Palmerston, and both prove the
                    intimate alliance France has entered into with Austria. That was the last infamy
                    which as yet had been spared to Louis-Philippistic France. The representative of
                    tyranny, of oppression attained by means the most infamous — the country
                    of stability and reaction, the ally of France, as reconstituted by two
                    revolutions! Deeper she cannot sink. But this is quite well. The deeper the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> brings down this country, the nearer draws
                    the day of reckoning. And it will come, before the <hi rendition="#i">bourgeoisie</hi> think of it. There is a party they do not take into
                    account, and that party is the noble, the generous, the brave French people.</p>
                <p>The dispute between the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> and the <hi rendition="#k">National</hi> has been submitted to a jury selected by both
                    parties. All hostilities are suspended. By the end of this month the decision
                    will be given. May it be as it will, we hope the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>
                    will continue in the only course which can save the Democracy of France.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>