<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_p4p_pss_wfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Polish Revolution</title>
                <title type="sub">Important Public Meeting</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-11-22</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">The Polish Revolution. Important Public Meeting. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 528, 4. Dezember 1847. S. 1.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Polish Revolution.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Important Public Meeting.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-12-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">528</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">5-6</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>George Julian Harney?</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-11-30" notAfter="1847-12-03">Zwischen 30. November und 3. Dezember 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Polish Revolution.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Important Public Meeting.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>The anniversary of the Polish Insurrection of 1830, was celebrated on Monday
                    last, the 29th of November, by a public meeting, at the German Society’s
                    Hall, Drury-lane.</p>
                <p>The meeting had been called by the society of Fraternal Democrats, in conjunction
                    with the Democratic Committee for Poland’s Regeneration. The room was
                    crowded with natives of England, Scotland, Ireland, France, Germany, Belgium,
                    and Poland.</p>
                <p>Mr <hi rendition="#k">John Arnott</hi> was elected president. Having stated the
                    object of the meeting, the chairman called on Mr Stallwood to move the first
                    resolution.</p>
                <p>Mr <hi rendition="#k">Stallwood</hi>, after recounting the heroism of the brave Poles at Warsaw, and their unbounded devotion to the cause of liberty, and eulogising the “Cracow manifesto” as a model for democratic creeds, moved the first resolution as follows: —</p>
                <p>“That we regard the dismemberment of Poland as an atrocious crime worthy of
                    the everlasting execration of the human race. That we remember with grateful
                    admiration the heroic efforts made by the Polish people in 1830-31 for the
                    recovery of their country’s independence. That we honour the sacred
                    memories of the martyrs who have perished in the glorious struggle to redeem
                    their nation from slavery; and that we sympathise with all the victims of
                    oppression at present suffering in dungeons, chains, and exile.”</p>
                <p>The Chairman then introduced</p>
                <p>Mr <hi rendition="#k">Ernest Jones</hi> to second the resolution. Mr Jones said:
                    To night, seventeen years ago, Poland woke from her death-sleep, for her
                    death-struggle; to-night, seventeen years ago, she strained her bleeding limbs
                    on the Russian rack, and burst her cords; to-night, seventeen years ago, she
                    rose from a province into a nation! (Cheers.) Warsaw was silent. Russia never
                    less expected insurrection — when the flame burst forth. Mr Jones then
                    gave a vivid description of the progress and triumph of the insurrection in
                    Warsaw, particularly dwelling on the circumstance, that until the populace were
                    armed, the issue was doubtful. Then the effect was electrical, and in a few
                    hours, Constantine, the mighty prince, had passed the barrier of Mockstow, with
                    his 11.000 Russians, and spent the night a shivering outcast, beneath a leafless
                    tree. (Applause.) The speaker then alluded to the subsequent course of the
                    insurrection, and expressed his belief that it would have been successful, had
                    it been an insurrection of the people, instead of the aristocracy — had it
                    been based on a manifesto, like the glorious one of Cracow. (Cheers.) But still
                    we need not despond — Poland is ready for a fresh struggle — we have
                    an army of martyrs to canonise — we have an army of heroes to come —
                    and the aspect of Europe forebodes their triumph. The speaker then showed how
                    every country in Europe was on the brink of internal change, analysed the secret
                    weakness of the great powers, and, after a forcible and stirring allusion to
                    Ireland, concluded by calling on his hearers to prepare for the approaching
                    struggle at home and abroad. Mr Jones’s speech was one of great force and
                    eloquence, and excited enthusiastic applause.</p>
                <p>M. <hi rendition="#k">Michelot</hi>, in an energetic speech, delivered in the French language, supported the resolution, which was carried unanimously.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Carl Schapper</hi> rose, amidst great applause, to move the
                    second resolution, and said: Citizens, when men struggle onwards for truth and
                    liberty in a great cause, though they may not at first succeed, they must
                    ultimately prevail — and such men were worthy of all honour — and
                    hence he said honour to the brave Poles. (Loud cheers.) Honour to those who died
                    before Warsaw — honour to those who died by the hand of the public
                    executioner — honour to those who fell at Cracow, and to all the martyrs
                    for liberty. (Great applause.) In July, 1830, France had her revolution, and in
                    the November following, the cry for universal liberty prevailed, and many wished
                    Poland free from Russia, but did not wish Polish serfdom abolished; and he
                    verily believed, had it not been for this desire on the part of the Polish
                    nobles to perpetuate the slavery of the masses, the revolution would have
                    succeeded, and the whole Slavonic race would now have been free. (Loud cheers.)
                    But the Polish proletarians asked, “What is it to us if Poland be free
                    from Russian domination, whilst I am subject to the knout of the Polish
                    noble?” (Hear, hear.) Well, the revolution failed and Poland’s sons
                    emigrated, carrying the seeds of freedom with them to Germany, to France, to
                    England, and other nations, and returned with renewed spirit to the Polish soil
                    in 1845; and issued their famous and ever glorious manifesto of democratic
                    sentiments from the Republic of Cracow. (Great applause.) But, alas, the effort
                    was futile, the bad seed sown in 1830 produced a bad harvest, the tyrants were
                    enabled to employ the peasantry against the patriots, and the revolt was
                    crushed, and the black spirit of Metternich again gloated in the blood of the
                    fallen martyrs of Poland. (Hear, hear.) But happily fraternity was fast
                    spreading, the principles of political and social equality were abroad. (Loud
                    cheers.) Look at Switzerland. (Great applause.) And liberty would progress in
                    spite of the old bloodless spider of the Tuilleries. (Groans for “the
                    spider”.) The Swiss Radicals had beaten Louis-Philippe and Guizot. Then
                    came the beautiful Lord Palmerston, who said “Let us have the thing
                    settled amicably.” <choice>
                        <sic>“Ay,</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">“Ay”,</corr>
                    </choice> responded the helpless old spider of <choice>
                        <sic>Paris”,</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">Paris,</corr>
                    </choice> “that’s just what I wanted.” (Laughter.) And not a
                    single regiment had entered Switzerland, the old spider dared not send them.
                    (Loud cheers.) Well, this was the progress of democracy. Who were the
                    conspirators now? Why, Metternich, the bloodless old spider in France, Lord
                    Palmerston, and the Jesuits. (Loud cheers.) But the people would very quickly
                    put down their conspiracy. (Great cheering.) He had some glorious news for them,
                    a Democratic Society, that was a Society of Fraternal Democrats had been
                    established in Brussels, and that society had sent a deputy, the learned Dr
                    Marx, to represent them at this meeting. (Great applause.) Citizen Schapper here
                    read the following document: —</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">“<hi rendition="#i">To the Members of the Society of Fraternal Democrats Assembling in London.</hi></hi></p>
                <p>We, the undersigned members of the committee of the Democratic Society,
                    established at Brussels, for advancing the Union and Fraternity of all Nations,
                    have the honour to delegate to you, Dr Charles Marx, vice-president of this
                    committee, for the purpose of establishing relations of correspondence and
                    sympathy between the two societies. M. Marx has full power to act in the name of
                    this committee for the purposes above mentioned.</p>
                <p>We present to you our fraternal salutations.<lb/><hi rendition="#et2"><hi rendition="#k">Mellinet</hi> (General), honorary <choice><sic>president</sic><corr cert="high">president.</corr></choice><lb/><hi rendition="#k">Jottrand</hi>, president.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Imbert</hi>, vice-president.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Picard</hi>, secretary.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">George Weerth</hi>.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">Lelewell</hi>.</hi><lb/>Brussels, Nov. 26th, 1847.”</p>
                <p>The above address was received with enthusiastic applause. C. Schapper after
                    highly complimenting the great Polish patriot Lelewell, and the grey-haired
                    veteran — “the child of the French Republic” — General Mellinet, concluded by proposing the following resolution: —</p>
                <p>“That in pledging all the aid in our power to the Polish patriots, we
                    desire to express our unqualified dissent from the aristocratic spirit which so
                    fatally influenced the struggle of 1830. We recognise in the Cracow Manifesto of
                    1845 the manifestation of Polish progress, embracing the broad principles of
                    political democracy and social justice, on which alone can be founded veritable
                    liberty and public happiness.”</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">T. Lucas</hi> in seconding the resolution, expressed his
                    pleasure in meeting so many of his brother democrats. Certain he was that when
                    the English democrats (the Chartists) obtained their liberty, that they would be
                    enabled to say to “the old spider in Paris” and all other tyrants
                    “thus far shall ye go but no farther”. (Cheers.) The resolution was
                    then unanimously adopted.</p>
                <p>Dr <hi rendition="#k">Marx</hi>, the delegate from Brussels, then came forward,
                    and was greeted with every demonstration of welcome, and delivered an energetic
                    oration in the German language, the substance of which was as follows — He
                    had been sent by the Democrats of Brussels to speak in their name to the
                    Democrats of London, and through them to the Democrats of Britain, to call on
                    them to cause to be holden a congress of nations — a congress of working
                    men, to establish liberty all over the world. (Loud cheers.) The middle classes,
                    the Free Traders, had held a congress, but their fraternity was a one sided one,
                    and the moment they found that such congresses were likely to benefit working
                    men, that moment their fraternity would cease, and their congresses be
                    dissolved. (Hear, hear.) The Democrats of Belgium felt that the Chartists of
                    England were the real Democrats, and that the moment they carried the six points
                    of their Charter, the road to liberty would be opened to the whole world.
                    “Effect this grand object, then, you working men of England”, said
                    the speaker, “and you will be hailed as the saviours of the whole human
                    race.” (Tremendous cheering.)</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Julian Harney</hi> moved the next resolution as follows: —</p>
                <p>“That this meeting rejoices to learn of the establishment of a Society of
                    Fraternal Democrats in Brussels, and responding to the alliance offered by that
                    society, receives its delegate, Dr Marx, with every feeling of fraternal regard;
                    and their meeting hails with excitation the proposition to hold a Democratic
                    Congress of all nations, pledging itself to send delegates to that Congress
                    whenever summoned by the Fraternal Democratic Societies of London and
                    Brussels.”</p>
                <p>The mover of the resolution then proceeded to address the meeting at considerable
                    length, on the Polish insurrection of 1830, the progress of Chartism, the
                    prospect of an energetic movement in this country for the obtainment of the
                    Charter, the importance of the society of Fraternal Democrats, and the vast
                    utility of the suggested Democratic Congress of all nations. His remarks were
                    enthusiastically cheered.</p>
                <p>Mr <hi rendition="#k">Stallwoood</hi> seconded the resolution, which was carried
                    unanimously.</p>
                <p>Three thundering cheers were then given for the glorious Lelewell, three for the
                    heroic General Mellinet, and three for the democrats of Brussels.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Charles Keen</hi> moved the fourth resolution as follows:</p>
                <p>“That recognising the brotherhood of all men, we consider it our duty to
                    struggle for the triumph of democratic principles in all countries, and
                    believing that the establishment of the ‘People’s Charter’
                    would enable the people of Great Britain to afford aid to the Polish cause, more
                    effective than the paper ‘protests’ hitherto employed by the British
                    government, we hail with joy the prospect of an energetic effort on the part of
                    the British people to obtain the legislative recognition and parliamentary
                    enactment of their long-withheld rights and franchises.”</p>
                <p>The speaker said they taught Universal Brotherhood, because they felt the evils
                    resulting from the want of it. Very true, at churches and chapels on a Sunday,
                    they were told that “we are all brethren”, but should it rain on
                    their leaving such churches or chapels, and they were to attempt to get into
                    some of their wealthy brethren’s carriages, what a row there would be.
                    (Loud laughter.) Yet, ten minutes before those very same men would have been
                    responding to the sentiment, “All men are brethren.” (Hear, hear.)
                    Notwithstanding this, Fraternity was a great truism, and before any great
                    lasting and practical good could be accomplished, it must be universally
                    acknowledged, ay, and practised too. (Loud cheers.) They had met to celebrate
                    the Polish Revolution, and the question was, what could they do to aid Poland?
                    Without power — nothing. Let them get the Charter and they would have
                    power. (Cheers.)</p>
                <p>Citizen <hi rendition="#k">Engels</hi> (from Paris), in seconding the resolution
                    said — Fellow Citizens, this commemoration of the Polish Revolution is not
                    only an advantage to Poland but to the whole world, as <choice>
                        <sic>is</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">it</corr>
                    </choice> causes the principles of democracy to be spread far and wide. (Hear,
                    hear.) He, as a German, had great interest in Polish success, as it would much
                    hasten liberty in Germany, and freedom Germany had resolved to obtain sooner or
                    later. (Loud cheers.) And he firmly believed that no one nation could be free
                    without benefitting all others. He had resided for some time in England, and was
                    proud to boast himself a Chartist “name and all”. (Great cheering.)
                    Who were now their chief oppressors? Not the aristocracy, but the wealth takers
                    and scrapers, the middle classes. (Loud cheers.) Hence, it was the duty of the
                    working classes of all nations to unite and establish freedom for all.
                    (Rapturous applause.)</p>
                <p>Citizen <hi rendition="#k">Tedesco</hi> (from Brussels, who addressed the meeting
                    in the French language in most eloquent terms, which the following abstract does
                    anything but justice to), said the men of Belgium looked on the English
                    democrats as a leading party, and trusted they would obtain that great measure,
                    the People’s Charter. He was delighted with the spirit that prevailed. He
                    should return to Brussels, and relate the good and enthusiastic feeling with
                    which the proletarians of this country were imbued, and their determination to
                    proceed until they had obtained their Charter, and sure he was, that that
                    measure would carry with it a fair day’s wages for a fair day’s
                    labour. (Hear, hear.) And give such an impulse to the cause of progress, that
                    the whole continent would follow, and universal liberty be established. (Loud
                    cheers.)</p>
                <p>Colonel <hi rendition="#k">Oborski</hi>, a Polish exile, said, at the outbreak of
                    the Polish Revolution, two hundred non-commissioned officers had kept three
                    Russian regiments at bay, and when some of the regiments found it was against
                    Poland they were fighting, they turned their arms and fought against their
                    oppressors. Although Old Poland was dead, Young Poland would arise, and become
                    far mightier than her ancestor. (Loud cheers.) He yet hoped to see Poland the
                    first battle field for liberty. With grateful thanks to the English people he
                    would shout “Hurrah for Democracy!” (Great applause.)</p>
                <p>Citizen <hi rendition="#k">Engels</hi> here said, that he had but recently come
                    from Paris, and that the real democrats in that city were in favour of a
                    Congress of Nations. (Loud cheers.) The resolution was then carried
                    unanimously.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Julian Harney</hi> again came forward and read extracts from
                    the defence of Louis Mieroslawski, one of the chiefs of the insurrection of
                    1846, and now lying in the dungeons of Berlin under sentence of death. The
                    reading of the said extracts excited great sensation in the meeting. J. Harney
                    then said, he had been particularly gratified by the remarks of his friend
                    Engels. He was glad to see that the feeling of fraternal sympathy for the Poles
                    was strong amongst the Germans. He was sure that if once the Germans obtained
                    their liberties, they would hasten to perform a great act of national
                    reparation, by undoing the work which the Austrian and Prussian despots helped
                    Catherine to accomplish — the destruction of Poland. He knew that if
                    Frenchmen were free, if they had broken down that disgraceful despotism which
                    had prostrated their country to the lowest depths of shame, their first thought
                    would be the liberation of Poland. (Cheers.) The next time France marched in the
                    direction of Moscow it would not be with an Emperor for her leader. It was a
                    maxim of Napoleon’s, “that a political blunder was worse than a
                    political crime”. He was guilty of both crime and blunder of the worst
                    character; when on reaching Warsaw on his march to Russia, he refused to
                    proclaim the restoration of Poland. Had he proclaimed the republic of Poland to
                    the full extent of its ancient boundaries, he would have re-created the soul of
                    a nation, and twenty millions of people would have formed his army of reserve
                    — an army animated by an unconquerable spirit of enthusiasm and devotion
                    to their emancipator. But no, Napoleon though the scourger of kings was the
                    tyrant of the people; though the most deadly enemy of “divine
                    right”, he was not less the enemy of popular sovereignty. He desired to
                    dictate terms to the Northern Autocrat, but for himself, not for Poland, and the
                    other nations trampled under that autocrat’s iron heel. His selfishness
                    found the reward it merited. When flying before the avenging lance of the
                    Cossack, and the still more dreadful shafts of the icy tempest and the
                    snow-storm, with their auxiliaries famine and pestilence; then Napoleon found
                    Poland no rampart of defence, behind which he might have thrown himself to give
                    his stricken hosts time to breathe, and turn upon their pursuers. He had refused
                    to recall Poland to life, and so when he needed her living arm to save him from
                    the blows of the Muscovite, that arm was not. But the coming republic would
                    repair the political crime of the Emperor, and the day was nigh <choice>
                        <sic>at at</sic>
                        <corr cert="high">at</corr>
                    </choice> hand when France would be a Republic and the people of England have
                    their Charter. (Great applause.) The speaker concluded by moving a vote of
                    thanks to the chairman.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">Carl Schapper</hi> seconded the vote of thanks, which was
                    supported by Mr Isaac Wilson, who expressed how much more pleased he was with
                    the proceedings he had just witnessed, than he was with those of a meeting held
                    some fortnight since under the presidency of Dr Bowring, at the Crown and
                    Anchor, at which he was necessitated to move an amendment. (Cheers.) The vote of
                    thanks was then carried by acclamation.</p>
                <p>The chairman having acknowledged the compliment, three cheers were given
                    “for the heroic martyr Mieroslawski”; three for the “<hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi> and the <hi rendition="#k">German
                        Universal Gazette</hi>”; and “ three dreadful groans for the <hi rendition="#k">Times</hi>, <hi rendition="#k">Journal des Debats</hi>, and
                        <hi rendition="#k">Austrian Observer</hi>”. The “Marseillaise
                    Hymn” was then sung in splendid style by Citizen Moll, and closed these
                    interesting proceedings.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>