<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_fpw_dh1_xfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Poland</title>
                <title type="sub">The Fraternity of Nations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-11-23</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">Poland. The Fraternity of Nations. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 528, 4. Dezember 1847. S. 4.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">Poland.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">The Fraternity of Nations.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-12-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">528</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">3-4</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>Feargus O’Connor?</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-11-30" notAfter="1847-12-03">Zwischen 30. November und 3. Dezember 1847</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="aricle">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k"><?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20181126T111213+0100" comment="In 1. Ausg.: Poland.
In 2. Ausg. Titel erweitert"?>Poland
                            and Ireland.<?oxy_comment_end?></hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Fraternity of Nations.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p>Another “29th of November” has come and gone. The seventeenth
                    anniversary of the Insurrection of 1830 sees Poland still groaning beneath the
                    weight of her chains, and bedewing the earth with “tears of blood”,
                    forced from her by the scourge of her oppressors.</p>
                <p>Twelve months ago we had to lament the failure of the Cracow Insurrection, and
                    mourn over the victims immolated at Siedlic, and massacred in Gallicia. The past
                    year has also had its martyrs. The patriots who escaped the assassin Szela’s
                    knife have been doomed to the dungeon and the gibbet.
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20181126T111743+0100" comment="In 1. Ausg.: Wiescznewski
In 2. Ausg. korrigiert"?>Wiesnewski<?oxy_comment_end?>
                    and Kapuscinski have added their names to the list of their country’s sainted
                    heroes. Condemned to die on the gallows, they bravely encountered their horrible
                    doom, and turned what was intended to be a death of shame to a triumphant
                    departure from a life of slavery and torture. Their last words were, “Long Live
                    Poland!” “Poland for Ever!” — a cry re-echoed by the thousands who, attending at
                    their execution, worshipped at their feet, and uttering curses both loud and
                    deep upon the murderers of the martyrs, they at the same time swore that Poland
                    should “live”, and live “for ever”. So true it is that</p>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l>“Body-killing tyrants cannot kill</l><lb/>
                    <l>The public soul, the hereditary will,</l><lb/>
                    <l>Which downward as from sire to son it goes,</l><lb/>
                    <l>By shifting bosoms more intensely glows.</l><lb/>
                    <l>Its heir-loom is the heart, and slaughter’d men</l><lb/>
                    <l>Fight fiercer in their orphans e’er again!”</l><lb/>
                </lg>
                <p>The King of Prussia, too cowardly to play the brigand-part of a Nicholas, or the
                    assassin-part of a Metternich, is, like our coercion-loving Whigs, a
                    “mild-measure” man. Accordingly the 260 suspected patriots, captured
                    in Posen, in February, 1846, have, after eighteen months incarceration, been
                    brought to trial, and some of them condemned to death. We print, in another
                    column, a translation of the defence of Louis Mieroslawski, who appears to have
                    been the chief appointed by the Democratic Emigration to conduct the
                    insurrection, but who was, unfortunately, arrested at Posen on the eve of the
                    intended outbreak. Although the speech, which appears in our third page, is but
                    a fragment of Mieroslawski’s intended defence, he having been interrupted
                    by his judges, and prevented from completing his discourse, still though a
                    fragment it is such a fragment as Plutarch would have treasured for the wonder
                    and admiration of mankind. As yet the doom of Mieroslawski is uncertain —
                    he may perish beneath the axe of the executioner, or be reserved for a worse
                    fate — the suffering of years of agony in the dungeons of the <hi rendition="#i">merciful</hi> Prussian King. In either case he will be
                    another added to the long list of the “noble army of martyrs”, who
                    have suffered and died for the regeneration of Poland. Whether condemned to the
                    painless grave, or the torturing dungeon, his name shall not be forgotten; it
                    shall be a spell to rouse the Polish youth to deeds of vengeance and of glory.
                    Oh! come, quickly come, that day of retribution and victory, when the Polish
                    Eagle shall again wing her triumphant way over the now desolated plains of
                    hapless Sarmatia.</p>
                <p>Again the warriors of the Emigration have met, and sworn on their swords, and by
                    the memories of their martyred brethren, to <hi rendition="#i">regenerate
                        Poland, or die</hi>! Again the Democrats of France, Belgium, Germany,
                    England, and every land where the banner of progress is unfurled, have
                    assembled, and sworn by their cherished hopes of liberty, to give aid to their
                    Polish brethren, now and for evermore, until Sarmatia’s stricken, but
                    still determined, warriors are triumphant over all their foes. “Each for
                    all, and all for each”, is the motto of all true democrats, and, acting in
                    accordance therewith, they must, and will, prevail.</p>
                <p>The report of the public meeting, holden on Monday last, in this metropolis, to
                    commemorate the Polish Revolution, will be read with satisfaction by all true
                    Democrats. Men of England, Ireland, Scotland, France, Germany, Belgium, and
                    other countries, fraternised on that occasion to swear eternal hatred to
                    Poland’s oppressors. A most remarkable feature of the evening’s
                    proceedings, was the appearance of a delegation from Brussels —
                    ambassadors, charged with the holy mission of organising the alliance of
                    nations. The delegation represented no second-rate men. Here are the names of
                    the Council of the Brussels society of Fraternal Democrats: —</p>
                <p>General <hi rendition="#i">Mellinet</hi>, a soldier of the French Republic, now a
                    grey-haired veteran of eighty years of age. General Mellinet is adored by the
                    Belgian Democrats, who justly regard him as “the bravest of the brave”.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Jottrand</hi> is a Belgian barrister. Chief editor of a
                    Democratic journal published in Brussels before the Revolution of 1830, he
                    suffered considerable persecution for his manly defence of his country’s
                    liberties. He was a member of the Constituent Congress, previous to the calling
                    of Leopold to the throne. Subsequently he edited the <hi rendition="#i">Courrier
                        Belge</hi>, a Radical journal, and is at the present time editor of the <hi rendition="#i">Debats Social</hi>, a journal devoted to the people.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Imbert</hi>, formerly editor of the <hi rendition="#i">Peuple
                        Souverain</hi> of Marseilles, fought in the revolution of 1830. He shared
                    the perils of the Republicans in the celebrated trial of 1834, and played a
                    conspicuous and heroic part on that occasion.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Picard</hi> is a Belgian barrister, and a well known Radical
                    Reformer.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Weerth</hi> is a name well known to our readers, who will
                    remember the gallant services of this gentleman at the late Free Trade Congress
                    at Brussels. He has been nominated by the English Chartists as their
                    representative. What more need we say of Weerth? unless we add that he is a poet
                    of no mean pretensions, whose songs tell of the sufferings of Labour’s
                    sons, and their aspirations for a better future.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#i">Lelewell!</hi> Here is a name beside the glory of which the
                    names of haughtiest monarchs pale their fires. Lelewell is the greatest of
                    Polish historians, and for literary eminence stands second to but few —
                        <hi rendition="#i">if any</hi> — on the roll of time. Originally a
                    professor at the University of Vilua, he was for his patriotism expelled from
                    his chair by the Russian Despotism. Retiring to Warsaw, he was nominated a
                    member of the Diet. On the breaking out of the Revolution, and the expulsion of
                    Constantine, Lelewell was appointed a member of the National Government. In that
                    capacity he advised measures which, had they been adopted, would have secured
                    the triumph of the Revolution. He strenuously urged the justice and necessity of
                    emancipating the masses, arming them, and making them possessors of the soil. He
                    urged, that the war should be carried into Podolia, Volhynia, Lithuania, and the
                    other ancient provinces of Poland; that the Polish nation should everywhere be
                    roused to arms, and the Slavonic race appealed to in the names of fraternity and
                    equality. Unhappily, the majority of the members of the government and diet were
                    temporisers and heart-and-soul aristocrats, who hated the very thought of
                    emancipating the people much more than they hated the Russian domination.
                    Lelewell’s counsel was rejected, and the revolution succumbed. Since then,
                    this great man has been living in exile. Denied a home in France, by that hater
                    of all honest men, Louis-Philippe, the Polish historian and patriot has taken up
                    his residence in Brussels. He is the recognised chief of the “United
                    Emigration”, which embodies the majority of the Polish exiles. He is the
                    very model of an incorruptible Republican — the Aristides of his country.</p>
                <p>Lastly, the delegate sent by the Brussels society, Dr <hi rendition="#i"><?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20181126T110350+0100" comment="In 1. Ausg.: Mark
In 2. Ausg. korrigiert"?>Marx<?oxy_comment_end?></hi>,
                    is a celebrated writer on political economy and social philosophy. Banished from
                    Germany, his native land, his works, nevertheless, circulate beyond the Rhine,
                    and, in defiance of the censorship, find their way to the hands of the people —
                    that people whose destiny is to work out a mighty social, as well as political
                    change in the heart of Europe.</p>
                <p>Such are the men who tender to us Englishmen the olive-branch of Fraternity. The
                    Democrats of Great Britain will respond with heart and voice to their
                    appeal.</p>
                <p>All the continental speakers at Monday’s meeting, French, German, and
                    Belgians, united in declaring that the real Reformers of the continent looked up
                    to the English Chartists, as the pioneers of progress, and looked forward to the
                    carrying of the Charter, as the great means of commencing the emancipation not
                    only of Englishmen, but the entire family of European nations. This “great
                    fact” should be a great incentive to the Working Classes of these Islands,
                    to struggle determinedly for the obtainment of their political rights, and
                    winning them, make England</p>
                <lg type="poem">
                    <l>“The anchor and hope of the world.”</l><lb/>
                </lg>
                <p>Monday last, — the anniversary of Poland’s unsuccessful struggle for freedom, was
                    selected, by Sir George Grey, for bringing forward the Whig Coercion Bill
                    directed against Ireland, — the Poland of the West. But, if Irishmen will only
                    unite with the people of England, the Whigs shall never succeed in their
                    Russianlike designs against the sister country. The people of England and the
                    people of Ireland have until recently warred against each other, instead of
                    warring against their common oppressors; and hence, both have been enslaved. Let
                    fraternity take the place of hatred, and union take the place of strife, and
                    both nations will speedily gain their liberties. Who ever opposes that union, or
                    holds back from that fraternisation <hi rendition="#i">now</hi>, is an enemy to
                    Ireland, and a traitor to the cause of Freedom. United we conquer — divided we
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="pagel" timestamp="20181126T111114+0100" comment="In 1. Ausg.: fall!&quot;
In 2. Ausg. korrigiert"?>fall!<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>