<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_iq5_x4c_yfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">English Democracy and Irish Repeal</title>
                <title type="sub">Feargus O’Connor in Parliament. Views of the Continental Press</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney?</persName>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-11-27</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Harney, George Julian (?), Friedrich Engels:] English Democracy and Irish Repeal. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 534, 15. Januar 1848. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">English Democracy and Irish Repeal.</title>
                        <title level="a" type="sub">Feargus O’Connor in Parliament. Views of the Continental Press.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1848-01-15</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">534</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">1-2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>George Julian Harney?</persName>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1848-01-10" notAfter="1848-01-13">Zwischen 10. und 13. Januar 1848</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div n="1">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">English Democracy and Irish Repeal.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Feargus O’Connor in Parliament. Views of the Continental Press.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi>, Paris paper, says, in speaking of the Irish
                    Coercion Bill, Mr John O’Connell has found a formidable rival in Mr
                    O’Connor. This great democratic leader has placed himself at one bound at
                    the head of the Irish party. It was he alone who fully opposed the Coercion
                    Bill. It was he who lead the opposition. It was he who opposed every clause, and
                    retarded to the utmost the passing of the bill. It was he who concentrated in
                    his speeches the whole spirit of the opposition. It was he, in fine, who, for
                    the first time since 1835, brought forward a motion for Repeal, which no other
                    Irish member would have done.</p>
                <p>The Irish members have bowed to his leadership with but a bad grace. Whigs in
                    their hearts, they hate the democratic energy of Mr. O’Connor. He will no
                    longer allow them to make Repeal a sordid cry of faction. The real Repeal
                    members, however, cannot do without such a leader as O’Connor, and are
                    obliged to submit, athough they try to undermine his growing popularity in
                    Ireland.</p>
                <p>After the session, Mr O’Connor will probably make the tour of Ireland, to
                    re-create the agitation, and found a true democracy. No doubt he will succeed,
                    and in less than six months be the recognised leader of the Irish people.</p>
                <p>Uniting thus the guidance of the democracy in the three kingdoms, he will be
                    placed in a position stronger than any agitator, including O’Connell, has
                    ever yet occupied.</p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#k">Brussels German Gazette</hi> of the 9th inst., in an
                    article entitled,<lb/>
                    <hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">Feargus O’Connor and the Irish
                            People,</hi></hi><lb/> dispatiates at great length on Mr
                    O’Connor’s address in the <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi> of
                    the 1st inst., and observes: “This address ought to be read and treasured
                    by every democrat. The results of this magnificent address will soon show
                    themselves with a powerful influence. ... Feargus O’Connor is the man that
                    Ireland wants. He has the wealth of millions truly at heart — their
                    welfare is, with him, no empty cry, no mask to get government patronage.</p>
                <p>In his address he shows the Irish people how, for thirteen years, it has been led
                    by the nose by Daniel O’Connell, the political thimble-rigger, with the
                    cry of ‘Repeal’. He places in its proper light the conduct of John
                    O’Connell, his father’s political heir, and who, like his father,
                    sacrifices millions of credulous Irishmen to his personal plans and interests
                    — but all the fine words and hypocrisy of John O’Connell will be
                    insufficient to wipe away the stain he has contracted in the ‘Coercion
                    Bill’ Debate. This address must open the eyes of the Irish people, and it
                    will then spurn the knot of sham Repealers who laugh in their sleeves at their
                    credulity.</p>
                <p>But the address has greater importance still, as emanating, not only from an
                    Irishman, but also from an English Democrat and Chartist. He shows with a
                    clearness that must carry conviction even to the most obtuse, the necessity for
                    a close union between the Irish and the English working classes; and that Repeal
                    can only be successful for Ireland when joined with the Charter. He further
                    points to the fact that the English Chartists petitioned to the number of three
                    and a half millions for Repeal — that they have now again petitioned
                    against the Coercion Bill — and that the oppressed of both countries must
                    stand or fall together.”</p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#k">Cologne Gazette</hi> observes, in allusion to Mr
                    O’Connor, his motion for Repeal, and his address in the <hi rendition="#k">Star</hi>: —</p>
                <p>“Descended from the oldest aristocracy of Ireland, nay! tracing his
                    pedigree to the remote and chivalrous kings of Green Erin; intimately connected
                    with the misfortunes of his country, through the sufferings of his more
                    immediate ancestors; constantly busied with her present fortunes and her future
                    prospects, O’Connor stands before us, a specimen of those men who remind
                    us at once of past glories and of future hopes; and from whose lips we receive
                    with equal pleasure the traditions of the former, and the prophecies of the
                    coming times.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">* * *</hi></p>
                <p>Parliament sees with terror that Daniel O’Connell has found a successor in
                    his countryman, Feargus O’Connor, who once more brings forward the
                    question of Repeal, and whose indomitable perseverance bodes a more formidable
                    struggle than that waged by the deceased O’Connell.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">* * *</hi></p>
                <p>In his speech on Repeal, O’Connor described the history of this country
                    with appalling accuracy. He described the fall of his royal ancestry. He
                    narrated the sufferings of his noble hearted and betrayed countrymen. As you
                    hear him, the crushed Catholic writhing in his blood, the war-cry of a hundred
                    revolts is recalled to your memory — the whole history of unhappy Erin, all the woes of the ‘Niobe of nations’ are spread before you.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c">* * *</hi></p>
                <p>The first number of the <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi> for this year
                    contains an admirable address from Mr O’Connor to the Irish people,
                    recommending the Charter as a necessary concomitant with Repeal, since the one
                    without the other, would be incomplete.”</p>
                <p>We have received copies of the following Dutch papers: — <hi rendition="#k">De Burger</hi> (the Citizen) and the <hi rendition="#k">Batavian
                        Courier</hi>, both published at the Hague, containing columns of the
                    proceedings of the English Chartists and the Fraternal Democrats. The editor, M.
                    Adrien van Bevarvoorde, appears to be a talented, eloquent and energetic
                    defender of the principles of Democracy.</p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> of Monday last contains a translation of the
                    address of the Fraternal Democrats to the working men of Great Britain and
                    Ireland, published in our last number.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>