<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_nzr_j4k_yfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">French Views of Chartism</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>George Julian Harney?</persName>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-11-28</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Harney, George Julian (?), Friedrich Engels:] French Views of Chartism. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 536, 29. Januar 1848. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">French Views of Chartism.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1848-01-29</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">536</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2-3</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>George Julian Harney?</persName>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</placeName>
                <placeName key="ed_cn4_12j_wx">Paris</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1848-01-21" notAfter="1848-01-27">Zwischen 21. und 27. Januar 1848</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">French Views of Chartism.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#i">(From the</hi><hi rendition="#k">Atelier</hi><hi rendition="#i">, a Paris journal conducted by Working Men.)</hi></hi></p>
                <p>The English Democratic agitation again occupies public thought, and assumes more
                    than its original importance on the other side of the Channel.</p>
                <p>The Chartists (unlike the Free-traders) do not concern themselves with the export
                    of a few additional pieces of cotton, or tons of iron; their aim is to ascertain
                    whether the English people, oppressed for centuries by an insatiable
                    aristocracy, will be able to free themselves from the state of misery and
                    degradation to which their masters have condemned them.</p>
                <p>It is to obtain this result that the Chartists have formed that vast association,
                    which aims at obtaining all those ameliorations, all those rights, all that
                    freedom, proclaimed sixty years ago by the French nation.</p>
                <p>Petitions, signed by many millions of persons, have already been presented to
                    Parliament; but hitherto the government would not entertain them. The
                    aristocracy of rank and wealth have opposed all improvement in the social
                    condition of the people. But far from being discouraged, the Chartist party have
                    increased alike in numbers and in weight, and anxious to try all conciliatory
                    means before appealing to force, continue to demand a constitution, a <hi rendition="#k">Charter</hi>, which giving to all the adult population the
                    right of suffrage, shall be the first grand step in the march of social
                    reform.</p>
                <p>Thanks to the power of <hi rendition="#i">Union</hi>, they have constant meetings
                    in all important places. They have an executive committee, an official journal
                    (the <hi rendition="#k">Northern Star</hi>), lecturers who traverse the length
                    and breadth of the land, popular orators whose eloquence convinces all minds of
                    the eternal justice of their principles, and even representatives in the
                    Commons’ House of Parliament.</p>
                <p>To ameliorate the present condition of the people, and to pave the way for their
                    admission to social and political rights, the Land Company has been established.
                    None can doubt that the Chartists, thus made proprietors of a part of the soil,
                    will be in a position to carry out all the reforms they may desire. This
                    conviction animates the Chartists themselves, who have just addressed to the
                    Commons two petitions, praying for the exemption of the transactions of the
                    Company from the oppression of the stamp duties, and the materials from the
                    heavy taxes imposed on such articles — the other, praying that the waste
                    lands, the property of the public, and hitherto disposed of in bulk to large
                    landholders, should be sold in small fields, with facility of payment, to the
                    poor.</p>
                <p>Thus the Chartists neglect nothing that can forward their grand aim — the
                    Emancipation of the People, and they have become a body whose power must be
                    respected by the old parties of the state. That which gives so much strength and
                    power to their association is, not only that their demands are founded on truth
                    and justice, but that they have learnt practically to apply the old maxim, “Help yourself, and heaven will help you.”</p>
                <p>(The notice of the Chartists winds up with a long extract from a speech of Julian
                    Harney on the Church, the House of Commons, &amp;c., the Queen’s speech,
                    &amp;c.)</p>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> of the 19th of January, gives long extracts
                    from the speeches of Julian Harney and Ernest Jones at a recent meeting,
                    prefacing their quotations by these remarks: —</p>
                <p>“We have already drawn the attention of our readers to the Chartist
                    agitation. Up to the present time, the <hi rendition="#k">Reforme</hi> is the
                    only French journal which has noticed this vast organisation, whose moral as
                    well as numerical force increases daily; and which must, in a certain period,
                    overturn the monstrous edifice of the English oligarchy.</p>
                <p>To-day we publish the speeches of two of the leading Chartist orators; in reading
                    them, we learn to what a point of excitement and irritation the masses have
                    arrived. We shall understand, too, the feeling of discouragement which induced
                    Sir Robert Peel to resign the premiership, notwithstanding he had attempted more
                    measures for the relief of the labouring classes than any other man or
                    administration would have dared.</p>
                <p>To enter into the spirit of the Chartist orators, we must understand that the
                    higher classes seek to draw the attention of the people from the state of the
                    internal affairs, by propagating the idea of foreign invasion. They do not yet
                    propose to fortify London, but a great increase in the standing army is spoken
                    of. In short, the English government would treat its subjects as the Parisians
                    have been treated by their chief. The speeches show how the English people
                    receive these insinuations.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>