<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_gcl_gv5_zfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Antwortschreiben der Association démocratique an die Fraternal Democrats zu London vom 13. Februar 1848 [MEGA1]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-12-03</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">The Association Democratique of Brussels to the Fraternal Democrats Assembling in London. In: Northern Star. Vol. XI. Nr. 548, 4. März 1848. S. 1</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">The Association Democratique of Brussels to the Fraternal Democrats Assembling in London.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1848-03-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">XI</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">548</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">4</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName>?</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel</placeName>
                <date when="1848-02-13"/>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="document">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">The Association Democratique of Brussels to the Fraternal Democrats Assembling in London.</hi></hi></head>
                <p><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr"/></p>
                <p>We received your letter of December last, the proposals contained in which
                    concerning the Democratic Congress of all nations and the establishment of a
                    monthly correspondence between your society and ours were immediately taken into
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>The propositions of holding the first Democratic Congress here in Brussels, with
                    a view of calling the second in London; the first Congress to be called by our
                    society for the anniversary of the Belgian revolution in September next, and the
                    programme of business to be prepared by the committee of this society; these
                    propositions were agreed to unanimously and enthusiastically.</p>
                <p>The offer of entering into a regular and monthly correspondence with our society
                    was equally hailed with the greatest enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>We now proceed to give you an abstract of our progress and general situation.</p>
                <p>The state of our society is as prosperous as can possibly be desired. The number
                    of our members is increasing weekly, and the interest taken by the public in
                    general, and by the working classes in particular, in our proceedings is equally
                    on the increase.</p>
                <p>The best proof, however, of our progress is the interest excited in the provinces
                    of the country by our movements. From the most important towns of Belgium we
                    have received summons to send delegates for the purpose of establishing
                    democratic societies similar to ours, and keeping up constant relations with the
                    metropolitan association.</p>
                <p>We have given to these appeals our immediate attention. We sent a deputation to
                    Ghent to call a public meeting with a view of establishing a branch society. The
                    meeting was exceedingly numerous, and received our deputation, consisting of
                    members belonging to several nations, with an enthusiasm hardly to be described.
                    The foundation of a democratic society was immediately decided upon, and the
                    names of members taken down. Since then we have received from Ghent the news
                    that the society is definitively constituted, and has held a second meeting
                    exceeding the first in numbers and enthusiasm. More than three thousand citizens
                    were present, and, we are happy to say, they mostly consisted of working
                    men.</p>
                <p>We consider the ground gained at Ghent as a most important progress of our cause
                    in this country. Ghent is the chief manufacturing town of Belgium, numbering
                    above a hundred thousand inhabitants, and being in a great measure the centre of
                    attraction for the whole labouring population of Flanders. The position taken by
                    Ghent is decisive for all working class movement of the country. Thus we may
                    accept the adhesion of the factory workers of that Belgian Manchester to the
                    revival of a pure democratic movement, as implying and foreboding the adhesion
                    of the generality of the Belgian proletarians.</p>
                <p>We hope to report in our next further progress in other towns of the country,
                    thus arriving by-and-by at the reconstitution of a strong, united, and organised
                    democratic party in Belgium.</p>
                <p>We entirely share in the view which in your recent address to the working people
                    of Great Britain and Ireland you have taken of the question of “National
                    Defences”. We hope that this address will contribute in a great measure to
                    the enlightenment of the people of England as to the question who are their
                    veritable enemies.</p>
                <p>We have equally seen with great pleasure the steps taken by the mass of the
                    English Chartists to arrive, at last, at a close alliance between the Irish
                    people and that of Great Britain. We have seen that there is a better chance now
                    than ever before to break down that prejudice which prompted the Irish people to
                    confound in one common hatred the oppressed classes of England with the
                    oppressors of both countries. We hope to see very shortly united in the hands of
                    Feargus O’Connor the direction both of the English and the Irish popular
                    movement; and we consider this approaching alliance of the oppressed classes of
                    both countries, under the banner of democracy, as a most important progress of
                    our cause in general.</p>
                <p><hi rendition="#et1">We conclude by offering to you our fraternal salutations.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rendition="#k">The Committee of the Association Democratique.</hi><lb/>
                <hi rendition="#et2"><hi rendition="#k">L. Jottrand</hi>, Chairman.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">K. Marx</hi>, Vice-President.<lb/><hi rendition="#k">A. Picard</hi>, Avt., Secretary.</hi></p>
                <p>Brussels, 13th February, 1848.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>