<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:telota="http://www.telota.de" telota:doctype="document mega" xml:id="mega_xd2_bqw_vfb">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">France</title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels</persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018-11-19</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="JA">[Engels, Friedrich?:] France. In: Northern Star. Vol. X. Nr. 518, 25. September 1847. S. 7.</bibl>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="a" type="main">France.</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>
                        <measure type="pages">1</measure>
                    </extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Feargus O’Connor?</publisher>
                        <pubPlace key="ed_wz2_shs_qx">London</pubPlace>
                        <date type="publication">1847-09-25</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <title level="j" type="main">The Northern Star, and National Trades’ Journal</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">518</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="column">2</biblScope>
                    </seriesStmt>                    
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_eyg_crj_sx">Friedrich Engels?</persName>
                <placeName key="ed_jtx_hgv_cbb">Brüssel?</placeName>
                <date notBefore="1847-09-17" notAfter="1847-09-23">?</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head><hi rendition="#c"><hi rendition="#k">France.</hi></hi></head>
                <p>Louis-Philippe has appointed his son, the Duke d’Aumale, Governor-General of
                    Algeria, in the room of Marshal Bugeaud. An official visit, paid by the Marquis
                    of Normandby to M. Guizot, has excited considerable discussion. Lord Normanby is
                    said to have formally communicated to M. Guizot a despatch of Lord Parlmerston
                    to Lord Ponsonby, your Ambassador at Vienna, declaring (as my letter of Thursday
                    stated), the resolve of Great Britain to suffer no attack on the independence of
                    any of the Italian states by Austria. The <hi rendition="#i">Union
                        Monarchique</hi> states, that Ministers have resolved to form a camp of
                    40.000 men at the foot of the Pyrenees. At a patriotic dinner given at Cernay,
                    in the Upper Rhine, M. Rissler, the Mayor of the town, proposed the health of
                    the King in these words: — “To the King of the French, to whom France confided
                    seventeen years ago the guardianship of her destinies and glory! May he soon
                    respond to our long expectation!” “That toast”, says the <hi rendition="#i">Courrier d’Alsace</hi>, “was received with cries
                    of <hi rendition="#i">La Marseillaise</hi>!” The councils-general of the
                    eighty-six departments are holding their customary session. The agitation for
                    parliamentary reforms has in many instances found expression in these bodies.
                    This has excited the wrath of the government, and the <hi rendition="#i">Journal
                        des Débats</hi> attacks them for exceeding in this their proper and
                    legitimate functions. The <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> expresses its
                    approbation of the movement which is taking place throughout the provinces, in
                    the shape of reform dinners, after the example of the great demonstration at the
                    Château Rouge, in Paris. “At the very moment we are writing”, says the <hi rendition="#i">National</hi>, —</p>
                <p>“A numerous and patriotic reunion is taking place at Saint Quentin. It
                    follows after that of Soissons, of which we have already spoken. M. Odillon
                    Barrot, who is present at that banquet, delivered at the preceeding dinner a
                    remarkable speech, which, we regret, reached us too late for publication. We
                    congratulate the chief of the ‘the Left’ upon his activity during
                    the interval of the Parliamentary sessions. He fulfils a duty, and gives an
                    excellent example. While we applaud the language of M. Odillon Barrot, with
                    respect to the duties imposed on us by our position as public men, we wish to
                    make some observations on the concluding sentence of his speech. ‘Our
                    greatest and our most alarming trials’, said M. Odillon Barrot, ‘are
                    not to be found in our past history, but are to be apprehended from our
                    future.’ If it be as a friend of the dynasty that he dreads coming events,
                    he is, perhaps, right. The social movement in Europe is not in favour of
                    dynasties, but we do not consider that fact to be a serious cause of uneasiness
                    for men devoted to the greatness and prosperity of a country. Why, then, should
                    France experience any alarm at a renovation become necessary? * * * * We hear
                    the reply; and we have already heard it so frequently from timid men, that we
                    repeat it without fearing to be mistaken — the public is afraid of
                    communism. This spectre has replaced that of 1793. It has grown large in the
                    shade, and report has given to it the most alarming proportions. It is a torrent
                    which is dragging the entire operative class into an abyss. On the first change
                    in our political organisation, this torrent will overflow, and overthrow in its
                    passage property, family, and country. We should wish to show how many
                    operatives could be found to <choice><sic>sacrifice,</sic><corr cert="high">sacrifice</corr></choice> family, and country!”</p>
                <p>The <hi rendition="#i">National</hi> concludes by stating that, —</p>
                <p>“The communists are not to be feared”; that “all that is
                    required is the general amelioration of the social condition of France, the
                    repression and punishment of iniquity, and the re-establishment of
                    justice”; that “the distinction of classes should be effaced, and
                    the labourer be placed in possession of his rights. Such is the object of the
                    renovation announced and promised by the present aspect of public affairs.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>